<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="http://appdev.cul.columbia.edu:8080/exist/rest/db/ead/nnc-rb_staging/schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
   <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
      <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_9051624_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_9051624_ead.xml</eadid>
      <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the Leonid Cherepen'kin
               Papers,</titleproper>
            <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
               Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
               Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
               University Libraries</publisher>
            <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2011-10-18">October 18, 2011 </date>
            <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
               <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT conversion
               <date normal="2011-10-18">October 18, 2011 </date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2011-10-18">2011-10-18</date>
            <item>xml document instance created by Carrie Hintz</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did><origination><persname encodinganalog="100">Cherepen'kin, Leonid Vasil'evich.</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="Leonid Cherepen'kin Papers,">Leonid
            Cherepen'kin Papers,</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1910/1980" type="inclusive">1910s-1980s.</unitdate>
         <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">.25 linear ft. (7 folders)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository encodinganalog="852">
            <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library</subarea>
            </corpname>
            <address><addressline>New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
         <unitid encodinganalog="090$b" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">BA#0532</unitid>
         <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">9051624</unitid>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
            <language langcode="rus"> Material is in Russian </language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract>The papers comprise Leonid Cherepe'nkin's recollection about bombing of Dresden during World War II, his poetry, and family photographs. The collection stored at BAR General Manuscripts Collection.</abstract>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical Note</head>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Leonid Vasil'evich Cherepen'kin was born in Pskov in 1922. His
            life, in many ways, was the typical life of a member of the intelligentsia from that
            time period - he lived through the war, survived prison camps, worked in mines and
            construction, and was always under surveillance by the KGB. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Leonid's father was a mathematics teacher. A first generation
            intellectual, he was scrupulously honest and had an extraordinary appreciation for
            books. He managed to acquire them even in the most straitened circumstances, building an
            excellent library with many rare books and lifetime editions. He instilled in his son a
            similar passion for books and broad knowledge of good literature. Leonid's mother, whom
            he adored and honored all his life, was from a family of priests. Her father, Ivan
            Kulikov, was a true pastor to his parishioners, and many of them voluntarily followed
            him when he was sent to exile after the revolution. After the German occupation of Pskov
            in 1941, Leonid's father agreed to become mayor in order to ameliorate the living
            conditions of Pskov citizens. During the occupation, he helped hide Jewish families.
            Nineteen-year-old Leonid was not called to serve in the army because he was then ill
            with jaundice. He started working at the library during Pskov's occupation. In 1943, the
            Germans in Pskov sent valuable books to Germany, accompanied by those people who had
            prepared the books for shipment. Thus Leonid ended up in the enemy's territory. While
            working in various places, he managed to establish contacts with anti-fascists. Through
            these contacts, Leonid then began to complete small assignments related, as he learned
            long after, to the family affairs of those who were preparing an attempt on Hitler's
            life. Leonid was fluent in German, and he even knew a few dialects. In 1945, he reported
            to the Soviet commandant, and was immediately arrested and accused of collaboration with
            the enemy. Only by chance did he escape execution and was instead sentenced to ten
            years. (His father was sentenced to serve eight years in prison camps. In the novel "V
            chas dnia, vashe prevoskhoditel'stvo" by Arkadii Vasil'ev, Leonid's father figures under
            the name Cherepenin, as a traitor, a servant of the occupiers, etc.). Leonid served his
            sentence in Kazakhstan, in Dzheskazgan, working there as a rate-fixer. He participated
            in the revolt of prisoners in Kengir (this uprising was later described by
            Solzhenitsyn), which was suppressed by tanks. In the camp, Leonid met many wonderful
            people, who later became well known as dissidents, writers, and scientists. He
            personally knew all the prototypes of <title render="italic">One Day in the Life of Ivan
               Denisovich</title> by Solzhenitsyn. He was released in 1955. He could not return to
            Pskov, because it would be impossible for him to get a job and live a normal life there.
            So, he married and lived in Kharkov, then Lipetsk, where there was a need for
            construction workers. He graduated from the Faculty of Philology at the Pedagogical
            Institute. Though he wrote a promising thesis on Dante, he continued to work as a fixer,
            as it was difficult to make a living as a teacher. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Leonid Vasil'evich Cherepen'kin died in 1991. He was buried in
            Pskov, next to the grave of his mother, according to his wish.</p>
         <p>Source: Biographical note written based on information provided by Tatiana Shmulevich. </p>
         <p/>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>The collection consists of Leonid Cherepen'kin's writings and photographs.</p>
         <p>The manuscript "Dies Irae i mnogoe drugo", written in the beginning of 1980s, is a
            recollection of author's experience in Dresden in early 1945. Describing the bombing of
            Dresden, which Leonid Cherepen'kin miraculously survived, author presents the scenes of
            German order and chaos in the face of inevitable capitulation; conversations with people
            he met, the mood of the civilian population, his first love to a German girl, refugees
            who were running to the West fearing of the advancing Red Army. Of all his ordeals and
            tribulations in Germany, the author chose this episode of his life, because it was the
            most terrible of the nearness of death and left the most lasting impression.</p>
         <p>There are also Leonid Cherepen'kin's poetry, family photographs, and biographical note
            written by Tatiana Shmulevich in 2010.</p>
         <p>The collection stored at BAR General Manuscripts Collection.</p>

      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is organized in three series<list type="marked">
                    <item>Series I:
                  Writings, 1970s-1980s</item>
                    <item>Series II: Photographs,
                  1910s-1979</item>
                    <item>Series III: Biographical Note, 2010</item>
                </list>
            </p>
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">World War II--Personal narratives.</subject>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="Source">Manuscripts.</genreform>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Memoirs.</genreform>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Photographs.</genreform>
       
      </controlaccess>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>This collection is located on-site as part of the BAR General Manuscripts Collection. </p>
         <p>This collection has no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition</head>
         <p>Family Gift 2009</p>
      </acqinfo>


      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); Leonid Cherepen'kin Papers; Bakhmeteff
            General Manuscripts Collection; Bakhmeteff Archive, Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
            Columbia University Library.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>This collection was processed by Katia Shraga. Finding aid written by Katia Shraga in
            October 2011.</p>

      </processinfo>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
         <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish material
            from the collection must be requested from the Curator of the Bakhmeteff Archive. The
            RBML approves permission to publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to
            secure copyright permission rests with the patron.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <dsc><c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series I: Writings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1970s-1980s</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
                <scopecontent><p>The series consists of the manuscript "Dies Irae i mnogoe drugoe…" and poetry (mostly cards and greetings to Tania) by Leonid Cherepen'kin.</p>
                </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1 to 3 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>"Dies Irae i mnogoe drugoe…", [1980s]</unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>(manuscripts in three notebooks)</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4 to 5 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>Poetry--mostly cards and greetings to Tania, [1970s-1980s]</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series II: Photographs, <unitdate type="inclusive">1910s-1979</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
                <scopecontent><p>The series comprises photographs of Leonid Cherepen'kin, his grandfather Ivan Kulikov and other family members.</p>
                </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>Cherepen'kin, Leonid, <unitdate type="inclusive">1924-1979</unitdate>
                     (11 photographs)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>Fedotova, Ania, <unitdate>1929</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>Kharlamova, M.I., <unitdate>1929</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>Kulikov, Ivan (Cherepen'kin's grandfather, priest), [1910s] (2
                     photographs)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>Shmulevich, Tatiana, <unitdate>1978</unitdate> (2
                     photographs)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>Volodina, Elia, <unitdate>1929</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series III: Biographical Note</unittitle>
            </did>
                <scopecontent><p>Biographical note written by Tatiana Shmulevich, Cherepen'kin's friend.</p>
                </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box">BAR General Manuscripts</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7 of 7</container>
                  <unittitle>Biographical note written by Tatiana Shmulevich,
                        <unitdate>2010</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>