<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="http://eadrepo.cul.columbia.edu:8080/exist/rest/db/ead/nnc-rb_staging/schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
   <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
      <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_6913793_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_6913793_ead.xml</eadid>
      <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the James H. Sheldon Papers,</titleproper>
            <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
               Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
               Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
               University Libraries</publisher>
            <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2012-07-17">July 17, 2012 </date>
            <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
               <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT conversion
               <date normal="2012-07-17">July 17, 2012 </date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langusage>
         <descrules> Finding aid adheres to that prescribed by <title render="italic">Describing
               Archives: A Content Standard</title>
         </descrules>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2012-07-17">2012-07-17</date>
            <item>xml document instance created by Megan Darlington.</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did><origination><persname encodinganalog="100">Sheldon, James H.</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="James H. Sheldon Papers,">James H. Sheldon
            Papers,</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1945/1971" type="inclusive">1945-1971</unitdate>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">[Bulk Dates: 1958-1964].</unitdate>
         <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">8.85 linear ft. (13 boxes)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository encodinganalog="852">
            <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library</subarea>
            </corpname>
            <address><addressline>New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
         <unitid encodinganalog="090$b" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">MS#1617</unitid>
         <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">6913793</unitid>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
            <language langcode="eng"> Materials are in English. </language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract> The James H. Sheldon Papers document a lengthy portion of the author’s career,
            though its bulk corresponds with the years between 1958 and 1964. While Sheldon was
            involved in a number of diverse pursuits, his papers emphasize his professional activity
            in the Nationalities Division of the Democratic National Committee, the American
            Association of United Nations, and the now-defunct newspaper, the <title render="italic">American Examiner</title> The collection is comprised of an array of materials such
            as: correspondence, drafts of press releases and speeches, handwritten notes, reports,
            programs, pamphlets, clippings, and scrapbooks. Sheldon’s papers are arranged in eight
            series and six subseries. </abstract>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical Note</head>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->James H. Sheldon was born on May 15, 1907 in Marietta, Ohio to
            his father, an attorney, and his mother, a schoolteacher. Due to chronic illness, he was
            home-schooled for much of his life before receiving a scholarship to attend Marietta
            College. Graduating in 1927, he went on to earn a Master degree in Political Science
            from Harvard University in 1928, followed by a stint as an assistant professor at Boston
            University. There, Sheldon taught international law, constitutional law, and general
            American government courses until the Great Depression turned his attention to public
            service. </p>
         <p>Working on the administrative staff of the Emergency Relief Administration, he left in
            1938 to run for Congress in Massachusetts. Though defeated, he gained respect within the
            Democratic Party, and returned to the Emergency Relief Administration in 1939 as
            coordinator of the statistics department. In 1941, Sheldon moved to New York to begin
            work as Director of the Non-Sectarian Anti-Nazi League, of which he previously served as
            Administrative Chairman.</p>
         <p>The mission of the Anti-Nazi League was to counter Nazi, anti-ethnic propaganda. For
            example, the organization operated radio programs in both Italian and German to
            challenge fascist propaganda targeted at the Italian- and German-American communities.
            Sheldon’s experience directing the Anti-Nazi League reinforced his concern for ethnic
            groups, and he became an authority on political views within American ethnic groups.
            This led to his involvement with the Nationalities Division of the Democratic National
            Committee, in which he was active between 1948 and 1968. </p>
         <p>Formally established in 1952, the Nationalities Division canvassed ethnic and racial
            groups of American voters to determine their individual political interests. This
            information was used to develop campaign strategies for appealing to an increasingly
            diverse voter population. From its inception, Sheldon served as the Public Relations
            Director, a role that entailed the drafting of press releases, radio programs, speeches,
            and other publicized information on behalf of various campaigns. Ultimately, he was
            responsible for those sections of the Democratic platform which related to ethnic and
            minority affairs as well as civil rights. As Public Relations Director of the
            Nationalities Division, Sheldon worked for Adlai Stevenson’s 1952 and 1956 presidential
            campaigns, John F. Kennedy’s 1960 presidential campaign, and Robert F. Kennedy’s
            senatorial campaign, among others.</p>
         <p>In addition to his position as Public Relations Director of the Nationalities Division,
            Sheldon was an active journalist who wrote mostly on foreign affairs, serving as a
            foreign correspondent as well as an officer of the Overseas Press Club of America.
            Beginning in 1950 and for about twenty years thereafter, he contributed a twice-monthly
            column on inter-group relations to the <title render="italic">American Examiner</title>,
            a newspaper with an approximate circulation of 200,000 at the time.</p>
         <p>Sheldon was also actively involved with the American Association of United Nations,
            serving two terms as Chairman of its Manhattan Chapter. Other organizations with which
            Sheldon was affiliated include the United Church of Christ Committee on International
            Affairs, the Christian Social Action Department of the New York Conference, and the
            Protestant Council of the City of New York.</p>
         <p>Sheldon died in 1975 at the age of 68. His legacy is in his enduring commitment to human
            rights, both at home and abroad. </p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>By and large, the collection is comprised of materials relating to Sheldon's activities
            in the Democratic National Committee, the American Association of the United Nations,
            and the <title render="italic">American Examiner</title>. The material is diverse and
            includes, but is not limited to, correspondence, drafts of press releases and speeches,
            handwritten notes, reports, programs, pamphlets, clippings, and scrapbooks. The
            collection spans between 1945 and 1971, but its bulk is concentrated between 1958 and
            1964. Series I and II are arranged thematically, while Series III, IV, V, and VI are
            arranged chronologically.</p>
         <p/>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged in six series<list type="marked">
                    <item>Series I. Democratic
                  National Conventions, 1960, 1964<list type="marked">
                            <item>Subseries I.1 1960 Democratic
                        National Convention, 1960</item>
                            <item>Subseries I.2 1964 Democratic National
                        Convention, 1964</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Series II. Campaigns, 1958-1954<list type="marked">
                            <item>Subseries II.1 John F. Kennedy
                        Presidential campaign, 1960</item>
                     <item>Subseries II.2 Robert F. Kennedy Senatorial campaign, 1964
                        </item>
                            <item>Subseries II.3 W. Averell Harriman campaign for NYS Governor,
                        1958</item>
                     <item>Subseries II.4 Robert F. Wagner, Jr. campaign for NYC Mayor, 1961</item>
                  </list>
                    </item>
               <item>Series III. Democratic National Committee - Nationalities Division, General
                  files, 1952-1961</item>
               <item>Series IV. American Association of the United Nations, 1956-1965</item>
               <item>Series V. General files, 1952-1960</item>
               <item>Series VI. Scrapbooks, 1951-1970</item>
                </list>
            </p>
      </arrangement>
      <relatedmaterial><head>Selected Related Material-- at Columbia</head>
         <p>Non-Sectarian Anti-Nazi League Records</p>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://oralhistoryportal.cul.columbia.edu/document.php?id=ldpd_4073260">Reminiscences of James H. Sheldon : oral history, 1972.</extref>
         </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610">Democratic National Committee (U.S.)</corpname>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610">Democratic Party (U.S.)</corpname>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610">United Nations.</corpname>
         <corpname encodinganalog="611">Democratic National Convention (1960 :--Los Angeles,
            Calif.)</corpname>
         <corpname encodinganalog="611">Democratic National Convention (1964 :--Atlantic City,
            N.J.)</corpname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Sheldon, James H.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell),
            1891-1986.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Keating, Kenneth B. (Kenneth Barnard), 1900-1975.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1910-1991.</persname>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651">United States--Politics and
            government--1945-1989.</geogname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Human rights.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Immigrants--United States--History--20th century.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Presidents--United States--Election--1960.</subject>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">newspaper clippings.</genreform>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">pamphlets.</genreform>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">scrapbooks.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least
            twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript
            Library reading room. </p>
         <p>This collection has no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition</head>
         <p>James H. Sheldon Gift</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); James H. Sheldon Papers; Box and
            Folder (if known); Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University Library.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>Papers processed 5/15/2012 Megan Darlington, University of Michigan, School of
            Information 2013 </p>
         <p>Finding aid written 5/15/2012 Megan Darlington</p>
      </processinfo>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
         <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. The RBML maintains ownership of
            the physical material only. Copyright remains with the creator and his/her heirs. The
            responsibility to secure copyright permission rests with the patron.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <dsc><c level="series">
            <did><unittitle> Series I: Democratic National Conventions</unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p> This series is comprised of various materials relating to the 1960 and 1964
                  Democratic National Conventions.</p>
            </scopecontent>

            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle> Subseries I.1: <unitdate type="inclusive">1960</unitdate> Democratic
                     National Convention, <unitdate type="inclusive">1960</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Held in Los Angeles, CA in July 1960, this subseries contains papers relating
                     the convention. It includes, but is not limited to: programs, pamphlets,
                     correspondence, speeches, and press releases. While much of the material
                     pertains to the event itself, a sizable portion relates to potential political
                     issues to highlight in the upcoming 1960 Democratic Party platform.</p>
               </scopecontent>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">1 </container>
                     <unittitle> Democratic National Convention </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(2 folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>


            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle> Subseries I.2: <unitdate type="inclusive">1964</unitdate> Democratic
                     National Convention, <unitdate type="inclusive">1964</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Held in Atlantic City, NJ in August 1964, this subseries contains papers
                     relating to the convention. Unlike I.1, however, I.2 is comprised primarily of
                     publicity-related papers, especially press releases. </p>
               </scopecontent>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">1 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1964 Democratic National Convention </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(3 folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
         </c>



         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle> Series II: Campaigns, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1964</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>A majority of the papers relating to the Democratic National Committee document
                  Sheldon’s work with various campaigns. Although he worked for additional campaigns
                  not documented by this collection, this series contains materials concerning JFK’s
                  1960 presidential campaign, RFK’s 1964 senatorial campaign, Averell Harriman’s
                  1958 campaign for New York State governor, and Robert Wagner’s 1961 campaign for
                  mayor of New York City. </p>
            </scopecontent>

            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle> Subseries II.1: JFK Presidential Campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1960</unitdate> August -November </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The bulk of this subseries is constituted by press releases and speeches, many
                     of which Sheldon wrote to explicitly address various ethnic groups such as
                     Germans, Italians, Poles, and Chinese. In addition, the subseries also contains
                     handwritten notes, correspondence, and pamphlets pertaining to JFK’s
                     presidential campaign between the months of August and November, 1960. Of all
                     the campaigns documented by this collection, the material relating to JFK’s is
                     the most voluminous. </p>
               </scopecontent>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">1 </container>
                     <unittitle> JFK Presidential Campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1960</unitdate> August -November (2 folders)</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
                     <unittitle> JFK Presidential Campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1960</unitdate> August -November (8 folders)</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>


            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle> Subseries II.2: RFK Senatorial Campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1964</unitdate> September -November </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Similar to II.1, II.2 is comprised mainly of press releases and speeches, but
                     also features some handwritten notes and correspondence. In addition, the
                     subseries contains a rather lengthy booklet entitled “The Myth of Keating’s
                     Liberalism,” which refers to RFK’s opponent, Senator Kenneth Barnard Keating.
                     Serving as Senator of New York between 1959 and 1965, he ran for re-election
                     against RFK in 1964. Considered a moderate Republican, the aforementioned
                     booklet challenges his self-proclaimed liberalism, and was likely used by
                     Sheldon for reference in drafting publicity statements on behalf of RFK’s
                     campaign. </p>
               </scopecontent>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">3 </container>
                     <unittitle> RFK Senatorial Campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1964</unitdate>
                        September -November (5 folders)</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>


            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle> Subseries II.3: Harriman campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Like II.1 and II.2, II.3 also contains speeches and press releases relating to
                     Harriman’s 1958 campaign; however, this subseries is comprised more heavily by
                     campaign-related ephemera, mainly in the form of pamphlets. There is also some
                     campaign material generated by Harriman’s Republican opponents. </p>
               </scopecontent>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">3 </container>
                     <unittitle> Harriman campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(2 folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>


            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle> Subseries II.4: Wagner campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1961</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The least voluminous of the four documented campaigns, this subseries is
                     comprised mostly of publicity-related material and some ephemera relating to
                     Wagner’s 1961 campaign. </p>
               </scopecontent>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">3 </container>
                     <unittitle> Wagner campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive">1961</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(1 folder)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
         </c>



         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle> Series III: Democratic National Committee-Nationalities Division, General
                  files, <unitdate type="inclusive">1952-1960</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>While the majority of material pertaining to the Democratic National Committee is
                  directly associated with conventions and campaigns, the collection also contains
                  material related to the general business of the Nationalities Division between
                  1952 and 1961, the bulk of which spans between January and December 1958. This
                  series is comprised mostly of publicity-related material, correspondence,
                  handwritten notes, clippings, meeting agendas, and newsletters. </p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle> DNC General files</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1952-1957</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">4 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1958</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">4 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1959 January -October </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">4 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1959 November </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">4 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1959 November -December </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">4 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1960</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
         </c>



         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle> Series IV: American Association of United Nations, <unitdate type="inclusive">1956-1965</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>A considerable portion of the collection pertains to Sheldon’s work with the
                  American Association of the United Nations, and documents his activities within
                  the organization between 1956 and 1965, with heavy emphasis on the years 1963 and
                  1964. This series is comprised of papers relating to the AAUN, most of which are
                  correspondence, handwritten notes, meeting agendas, and membership lists. The
                  series also features a booklet entitled “Manhattan Ethnic Group Distribution
                  Statistics and Data,” which is a detailed account of the ethnic demographics of
                  Manhattan in 1960. While Sheldon may have consulted this booklet during JFK’s
                  campaign, it was found amongst his AAUN papers and has thus been included in this
                  series. </p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle> AAUN</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1956-1957</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">5 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1958</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">5 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1959</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">5 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1960</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">5 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1961 January -March</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">5 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1961 April -December </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 January </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 February</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 March</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 April </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 May </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 May </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 June </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 July </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">6 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 August </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">7 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 September </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">7 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 October </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">7 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 November </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">7 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 November </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">7 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1962 December </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">7 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 January </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">7 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 February</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">8 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 March</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">8 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 April </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">8 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 May </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">8 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 June </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">8 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 July -August </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">8 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 September </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">8 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 October (2 folders)</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">9 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 November </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">9 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1963 December </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">9 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1964 January -April </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">9 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1964 May -December </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">9 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1965 January -August </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">9 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1965 September -December </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">9 </container>
                     <unittitle> Membership Lists, <unitdate type="inclusive">1962-1963</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
         </c>



         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle> Series V: General files, <unitdate type="inclusive">1948-1971</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>In addition to material relating directly to specific organizations, there is a
                  very small series of general files which are unrelated and span between 1945 and
                  1971. It includes papers relating the Metropolitan Council on Fair Employment
                  Practice, the Non-Sectarian Anti-Nazi League, and a biographical letter written
                  upon request to the president of Morris Brown College, among others. </p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="box" label="Box">9 </container>
                  <unittitle> General files, <unitdate type="inclusive">1948-1971</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <physdesc><extent>(1 folder)</extent>
                  </physdesc>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>



         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle> Series VI: Scrapbooks, <unitdate type="inclusive">1951-1970</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>The collection includes 5 bound scrapbooks and 20 loose pages containing clippings
                  of Sheldon’s twice-monthly column in the <title render="italic">American Examiner</title> between December 1951
                  and October 1970. It should be noted that that the newspaper was formally known as
                  the <title render="italic"> American Hebrew </title> until 1956, the year it was changed to the <title render="italic">American Examiner</title>;
                  thus, the scrapbooks pertain to the same publication.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle><title render="italic">American Hebrew</title>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">10 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1951 December -1953 December </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="box" label="Box">11 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1954 January -1956 September </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle><title render="italic">American Examiner</title>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">12 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1957 January -1967 December </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">13 </container>
                     <unittitle> 1968 January -1970 October </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
         </c>



      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>