<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
    <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
        <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_6892024_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_6892024_ead.xml</eadid>
        <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the Professorial Memorial Collection:
                    J. Bartlet Brebner, Stephen Koss, Garret Mattingly,</titleproper>
                <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
                    Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
                    Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
                    University Libraries</publisher>
                <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2009-03-05">March 5, 2009 </date>
                <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
                    <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
                    <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT
                conversion <date normal="2009-03-05">March 5, 2009 </date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
            </langusage>
        </profiledesc>
        <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2009-03-05">2009-03-05</date>
                <item>File created.</item>
            </change>
            <change><date normal="2009-04-13">2009-04-13</date>
                <item>xml document instance created by Carrie Hintz</item>
            </change>
        </revisiondesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
        <did><origination><persname encodinganalog="100">R.K. (Robert Kieter) Webb, 1922-</persname>
            </origination>
            <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="Professorial Memorial Collection: J. Bartlet Brebner, Stephen Koss, Garret Mattingly,">Professorial Memorial Collection: J. Bartlet Brebner, Stephen Koss, Garret
                Mattingly,</unittitle>
            <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1963/1975" type="inclusive">1927-1993</unitdate>
            <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">1 linear foot (2 document boxes).</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository encodinganalog="852">
                <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library, University
                        Archives</subarea>
                </corpname>
                <address><addressline>New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
                </address>
            </repository>
            <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">6892024</unitid>
            <unitid encodinganalog="852$j" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">UA#0142</unitid>
            <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
                <language langcode="eng">In English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract>This collection contains materials related to the lives and work, and
                memorials for, three Columbia University professors known by R.K. Webb: J. Bartlet
                Brebner, Stephen Koss, and Garrett Mattingly. R.K. Webb, Professor of History
                Emeritus at University of Maryland-Baltimore County, studied under Professors
                Brebner and Mattingly as a graduate student at Columbia University, later taught at
                Columbia University in the Department of History, and served as editor of the
                American Historical Review.</abstract>
        </did>
        <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
            <head>Historical Note</head>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Professor of History Emeritus R.K. Webb, University of
                Maryland-Baltimore County, graduated from Columbia University with a Ph.D. in
                History in 1951 and taught in the History department at Columbia from 1953 to 1985,
                before moving to the Department of History at UMBC. Webb is a noted scholar of
                British social history and British working-class literature, and a former editor of
                the American Historical Review, the central scholarly history journal for the
                history profession in the United States. The papers in this collection document the
                lives and work of three professors whom Webb knew personally. As a graduate student
                at Columbia University, Webb received instruction from Professor of History John
                Bartlet Brebner (1895-1957), a well-known historian of Great Britain, British
                constitutional law and history, and Atlantic and Canadian history who taught at
                Columbia from 1925 until he died in 1957, and Professor of History Garrett Mattingly
                (1900-1962), who taught the history of early modern Europe at Columbia from 1948
                until 1962, one year before he died. As Professor of History at Columbia University
                in the 1950s and 1960s, Webb instructed and mentored Stephen Koss (1940-1984), who
                later taught at Barnard and Columbia University until his death in 1984. </p>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Webb was central to preserving the memory of the lives and
                contributions of Professors Brebner, Koss and Mattingly to Columbia University and
                the historical profession. Webb co-founded and coordinated the Brebner Memorial Fund
                (which was chaired by Professor Garrett Mattingly) soon after Brebner's death. The
                Memorial Fund was intended to foster Columbia University Department of History
                graduate students' study of historical topics relevant to Brebner's research by
                facilitating the acquisition of microfilms of British newspapers and other primary
                sources. Webb also preserved Brebner's research notes and chapter drafts of an
                unfinished book on industrializing Britain that Brebner was preparing when he died.
                According to Webb, the book and the accompanying notes and drafts had their origins
                in a popular lecture course Brebner taught at Columbia in the 1940s and 1950s. Webb
                and other colleagues interested in Brebner's project decided that Brebner's four
                chapter drafts in these files, while "admirable and elegant as they are as summaries
                of his matured views on the mid-eighteenth century," were not ready for publication
                at the time. </p>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Webb also participated in the memorialization of Barnard
                College Professor of History Stephen Koss, a former gradate student of Webb's at
                Columbia, and later colleague and friend. Correspondence between Webb and Koss in
                1965 regarding Koss's dissertation, which Webb determined had to be nearly
                completely revised, caused considerable tension between Koss and his mentor, and in
                part illustrates the shifting norms of formality and formal communication and
                address in academic and professional life in the 1960s. This "contretemps" was
                clearly a sensitive matter for Webb, who attached to it his only note regarding any
                of the papers he donated in this collection. </p>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Webb noted that his very formal addressing of Koss as "Dr.
                Mr. [sic] Koss," after recently addressing his correspondence to Koss with "Dear
                Stephen," had to be appreciated in a context of not only correspondence regarding
                Koss's dissertation, but Webb's professional maturation in the rather more formal
                environment that characterized academic life before the cultural revolutions of the
                1960s, "a background that probably few of my younger colleagues could understand in
                this informal age. I recall so vividly the transition from 'Mr.' to first-name
                status with my own teachers - - Howard Robinson at Oberlin, J.B. Brebner and Garrett
                Mattingly at Columbia, H.L. Beales at the London School of Economics - - it was long
                in coming and arrived at rather late in each of the relationships. And I know that
                in the 1960s I was still concerned about scrupulousness in this matter: in the
                simplest form that, prior to completion of the doctorate, when one was still, so to
                speak, sitting in judgment, maintaining a formal style was more appropriate. I have
                largely abandoned that scruple because present-day undergraduates would find it
                astonishing to be addressed by anything other than a first name, a case applying a
                fortiori to graduate students." Webb also followed Koss's frustrated efforts to
                facilitate access to The Woods Collection, an archive dealing with the history of
                the twentieth-century British political press, a topic on which Koss was an expert,
                and contributed to professional memorials for Koss that culminated in a volume in
                his honor, J.M.W. Bean, ed., <title altrender="italic">The Political Culture of Modern Britain: Studies in
                    Memory of Stephen Koss (London: Hamish Hamilton, 1987).</title>
            </p>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Webb also preserved materials concerning the professional
                memorial and festschrift for Columbia University Professor of History Garrett
                Mattingly, who supervised Webb's studies as a graduate student at Columbia along
                with Brebner. Webb participated in the professional memorial and helped to prepare a
                volume of essays dedicated to the memory of Mattingly and his scholarship, <title altrender="italic">From the
                Renaissance to the Counter-Reformation: Essays in Honor of Garrett Mattingly</title>, edited
                and with an introduction by Charles H. Carter (New York: Random House, 1965).</p>
            <p/>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>R. K. Webb's Professorial Memorial Collection contains materials related to the lives
                and work, and professional memorials for, three Columbia University professors known
                by Webb: J. Bartlet Brebner, Stephen Koss, and Garrett Mattingly. The collection
                documents the work of the Brebner Memorial Fund, and includes promotional and
                organizational records, correspondence to and from Webb and other officers of the
                Fund, lists of microfilm materials to be acquired by the Fund, and papers regarding
                the memorial volume for Brebner. Other materials regarding Brebner include Brebner's
                research notes and chapter drafts of his unfinished book on industrializing Britain,
                academic articles retained by Brebner and some unrelated ephemera. </p>
            <p>The Professorial Memorial Collection also documents the activities of, and
                professional memorial for, Stephen Koss, and the relationship between this student
                of Webb's, and later, Webb's colleague and friend. The collection includes materials
                from Koss's memorial, extensive correspondence between Webb and Koss, Webb's letters
                of recommendation for Koss, and other material concerning Koss's efforts to
                facilitate access to The Woods Collection. </p>
            <p>Lastly, the collection contains materials concerning the professional memorial and
                <emph altrender="italic"> festschrift</emph> for Columbia University Professor of History Garrett Mattingly.</p>
            <p/>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>This collection is arranged in three series. </p>
            <p><list type="marked">
                    <item>Series I: John Bartlet Brebner, 1927-1960s 
                        <list type="marked">
                            <item>Subseries I.1: Memorial Fund, 1927-1960s</item> 
                        <item>Subseries I.2: Manuscript Research Notes and Drafts, 1940s-1950s</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>

                    <item>Series II. Stephen Koss, 1963-1993 </item>
                    <item>Series III. Garrett Mattingly, 1950s</item>
                      
                </list>
            </p>
        </arrangement>
        <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
            <persname encodinganalog="600">Brebner, John Bartlet, 1895-1957.</persname>
            <persname encodinganalog="600">Koss, Stephen E.</persname>
            <persname encodinganalog="600">Mattingly, Garrett, 1900-1962.</persname>
            <persname encodinganalog="600">Webb, R. K. (Robert Kiefer), 1922-</persname>
        </controlaccess>
        <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>This collection is located offsite. You will need to request this material at least
                twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and
                Manuscript Library reading room. </p>
            <p>This collection has no restrictions. Some personal material may be restricted due to
                the presence of personal names and information.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
            <head>Acquisition</head>
            <p>Professor Emeritus R.K. Webb 1993</p>
        </acqinfo>
        <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); Professorial Memorial Collection:
                Brebner, Koss, Mattingly, Box and Folder; University Archives, Rare Book and
                Manuscript Library, Columbia University Library.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>Collection processed in June 2008 by Justin Jackson (GSAS 2012). </p>
            <p>Finding aid written by Justin Jackson, 2008.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
            <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
            <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish material
                from the collection must be requested from the Curator of Manuscripts and University
                Archivist, Rare Book and Manuscript Library (RBML). The RBML approves permission to
                publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to secure copyright
                permission rests with the patron.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <otherfindaid encodinganalog="555">
            <p>Finding aid in repository; folder level control. </p>

        </otherfindaid>
        <relatedmaterial><head>Selected Related Material at Columbia</head>
           <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/lweb/archival/collections/ldpd_4079650/index.html">John Bartlet Brebner Papers, MS#0146</extref>
           </p>
            
            <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/lweb/archival/collections/ldpd_4079090/index.html">Garrett Mattingly Papers, MS#0857</extref>
            </p>
        
        </relatedmaterial>
       
        <dsc><c level="series">
                <did><unittitle>Series I: John Bartlett Brebner, <unitdate type="inclusive">1927-1960s</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                </did>
                <scopecontent><p>This series comprises records and documents from the early operations of the John Bartlet Brebner Memorial Fund and the research notes and chapter drafts of Brebner's unfinished manuscript on the history of early modern and industrializing Britain. Material in this series is arranged chronologically.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c level="subseries">
                    <did><unittitle>Subseries I.1: Memorial Fund, <unitdate type="inclusive">1927-1960s</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent><p>This subseries includes organizational and promotional materials that document the creation and early operation of the Brebner Memorial Fund. They include correspondence to and from Webb and other officers of the Memorial Fund, correspondence with various donors, including many former students and colleagues of Brebner, memorials to Brebner, and some of Brebner's personal ephemera.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                            <unittitle>Committee, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1960</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
                        </did>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                                <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1959-1977</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                                <unittitle>Controller's Office, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1961</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                                <unittitle>From Donors, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1960</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                                <unittitle>To Donors, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1960</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                            <unittitle>General Material, <unitdate type="inclusive">1957-1960</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
                            <unittitle>Historiography Project, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1961</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                            <unittitle>Microfilm Materials--Lists,
                            <unitdate>1960s</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">9</container>
                            <unittitle>Project Arrangements, <unitdate type="inclusive">1927-1959</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                </c>
                <c level="subseries">
                    <did><unittitle>Subseries I.2: Manuscript Research Notes and Drafts, <unitdate type="inclusive">1950s-1960s</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent><p>Contained in this subseries are academic articles, newspaper and magazine clippings, and research notes and research materials relevant to Brebner's unfinished historical manuscript on early modern and industrializing Britain, which he was preparing when he died in 1857. These files also contain various drafts of four chapters on Britain in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">10</container>
                            <unittitle>Book Project--General, <unitdate type="inclusive">1955-1957</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><unittitle>Drafts</unittitle>
                        </did>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">11</container>
                                <unittitle>Chapter-- "Undercurrents," circa
                                    <unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">12</container>
                                <unittitle>Chapter Three--"Commitment to Industrialization
                                    (1760-1790)," circa <unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">13</container>
                                <unittitle>Chapters, circa <unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><unittitle>Notes</unittitle>
                        </did>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">14</container>
                                <unittitle>"Before 1650," circa
                                <unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">15</container>
                                <unittitle>"Cherished Stability (1750)," circa
                                    <unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1 to 2</container>
                                <unittitle>"The Climate of Opinion, 1760-90," circa
                                    <unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                <physdesc><extent>(2 folders)</extent>
                                </physdesc>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3 to 5</container>
                                <unittitle>"The Changing Polity, <unitdate type="inclusive">1760-1790</unitdate> Discarded," circa
                                    <unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                <physdesc><extent>(3 folders)</extent>
                                </physdesc>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                                <unittitle>"The Economy About 1760-1790," circa
                                    <unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
                                <unittitle>"Social Change, 1760-1790," circa,
                                    <unitdate>1950s</unitdate> (Originally marked "Somewhat Slight
                                    Needs Pervasive Ideas")</unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                    </c>
                </c>
            </c>
            <c level="series">
                <did><unittitle>Series II: Stephen Koss, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1993</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                </did>
                <scopecontent><p>This series contains correspondence between Koss and Webb, letters of recommendation for Koss written by Webb, and papers and documents focusing on the death of, and professional memorial for, Stephen Koss, including material related to the memorial volume. This series also contains correspondence and other documents related to Koss's efforts to facilitate the acquisition of The Woods Collection. Material in this series is arranged chronologically.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c level="file">
                    <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                        <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1993</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c>
                <c level="file">
                    <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">9</container>
                        <unittitle>Death and Memorial, <unitdate type="inclusive">1984-1985</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c>
                <c level="file">
                    <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">10</container>
                        <unittitle>The Woods Collection, <unitdate type="inclusive">1979-1982</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c>
            </c>
            <c level="series">
                <did><unittitle>Series III: Garrett Mattingly, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1964</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                </did>
                <scopecontent><p>Series III contains documents and correspondence regarding the death of, and memorial for, Garrett Mattingly, including papers related to the memorial volume for Mattingly. Material in this series is arranged chronologically.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c level="file">
                    <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">11</container>
                        <unittitle>Memorial Minutes, <unitdate>1963</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c>
                <c level="file">
                    <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">12</container>
                        <unittitle>Memorial Volume, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1964</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                </c>
                <c level="file">
                    <did><unittitle/>
                    </did>
                </c>
            </c>



        </dsc>
    </archdesc>


</ead>