<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="http://eadrepo.cul.columbia.edu:8080/exist/rest/db/ead/nnc-rb_staging/schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
   <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
      <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_9025181_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_9025181_ead.xml</eadid>
      <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the Maxwell Bodenheim papers,</titleproper>
            <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
               Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
               Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
               University Libraries</publisher>
            <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2012-02-09">February 9, 2012 </date>
            <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
               <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT conversion
               <date normal="2012-02-09">February 9, 2012 </date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2012-02-09">2012-02-09</date>
            <item>xml document instance created by Carrie Hintz</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did><origination><persname encodinganalog="100">Bodenheim, Maxwell, 1893-1954.</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="Maxwell Bodenheim papers,">Maxwell Bodenheim
            papers,</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1917/1981" type="inclusive">1917-1981</unitdate>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">[Bulk Dates: 1917-1938].</unitdate>
         <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">1.68 linear ft. (4 document boxes)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository encodinganalog="852">
            <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library</subarea>
            </corpname>
            <address><addressline>New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
         <unitid encodinganalog="090$b" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">MS#1590</unitid>
         <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">9025181</unitid>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
            <language langcode="eng"> Material is in English </language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract>Maxwell Bodenheim (1892-1954) was a poet and novelist who was pervasive
            throughout the bohemian scenes in Chicago and New York's Greenwich Village in the first
            half of the 20th century. The collection consists of a broad scope of materials produced
            by Bodenheim from 1917 to the mid 1930s, including correspondence (mostly with his wife
            Minna), drafts of talks and writings, and records of business dealings with publishers
            and legal issues surrounding his divorce and an obscenity suit against him.</abstract>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical Note</head>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Maxwell Bodenheim was born Maxwell Bodenheimer in May of 1892
            in Hermanville, Mississippi. At the age of nine he moved with his family to Chicago. In
            1908 Bodenheim was expelled from high school and joined the army. Following an attempted
            desertion he was caught and jailed at Ft Leavenworth, Kansas where he served the rest of
            his tour of duty. After completing his service he spent time traveling around the
            Southwestern United States.</p>
         <p>In 1912 Bodenheim moved back to Chicago and worked to establish himself in the literary
            scene there, developing a friendship with novelist and screenwriter Ben Hecht. The two
            would continue to collaborate and quarrel through the end of Bodenheim's life. It was
            also in Chicago that he met critic and editor Harriet Monroe, and published poems in her
            journal Poetry, as well as in <title render="italic">The Little Review.</title>
            </p>
         <p>Bodenheim moved to New York in 1916 and settled in Greenwich Village. He established a
            friendship with poet Alfred Kreymborg with whom he had been in ongoing correspondence,
            and continued to publish poetry. Between 1916 and 1918 his poems appeared in journals
            the <title render="italic">New Republic</title>, the <title render="italic">Seven
               Arts,</title> the <title render="italic">Pagan,</title> and the <title render="italic">Egoist,</title> and he edited the magazine the <title render="italic">Others.</title> As an <title render="italic">Others</title> editor he became friend
            with poets William Carlos Williams and Marianne Moore, who contributed frequently to the
            writing and editing of the magazine. <title render="italic">Minna and Myself,</title>
            his first book of poems, was published in 1918 and he married Minna Schein, for whom the
            book is titled, in November of that year. In 1920 she gave birth to their only son
            Solbert.</p>
         <p>Throughout the 1920s Bodenheim continued to write and publish prolifically, finishing
            six books of poetry and eight novels by 1930. His 1925 novel <title render="italic">Replenishing Jessica</title> brought obscenity charges against himself and publisher
            Horace Liveright, however both were easily acquitted. The trial brought a brief surge in
            Bodenheim's popularity and book sales, but he was dismayed by the damage to his
            reputation and wrote to friends that he felt "neglected" and "isolated." Though he
            remained married to Minna he had become notorious after a 1928 string of highly
            publicized suicides by former and current girlfriends, all apparently spurred by his
            rejection, and by the end of the decade Bodenheim had firmly established himself as a
            resident and colorful, if poorly-behaved and sometimes recalcitrant, Greenwich Village
            bohemian. </p>
         <p>By the 1930s Bodenheim was becoming increasingly destitute but he continued to write and
            publish through the first half of the decade, and by 1934 he had put out another seven
            novels and one more book of poetry. A 1932 stint in Hollywood however, left him sick and
            and his financial condition unimproved and in 1935 he marched with a small group on city
            hall to protest the dwindling writer's relief funds on which he depended to live.
            Bodenheim was divorced by Minna in 1938, and married his second wife Grace Finan shortly
            after in 1939. Finan was quickly bedridden with cancer and Bodenheim--when he was
            able--nursed her until her death in 1950.</p>
         <p>Throughout most of his second marriage Bodenheim was a regular in Village bars and
            streets, where he would sell poems for money to buy drinks. He lived mostly on the
            streets when he was not otherwise bouncing from room to room. In 1951 Bodenheim married
            his third wife, Ruth Fagan who was almost 30 years his younger, and the two of them
            slept on benches and panhandled for a living. Finally on the night of February 6 1954,
            Bodenheim and Fagan accepted an invitation to spend the night at the apartment of Harold
            Weinberg, who they had known for about a year. In an argument over the sexual
            relationship between Ruth and Weinberg, Weinberg shot Bodenheim in the chest, killing
            him, and stabbed Ruth to death with a hunting knife.</p>
         <p/>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>The collection consists of correspondence to and from Bodenheim and his wife Minna, a
            few files on individuals, and manuscripts and typescripts of Bodenheim's poetry, novels,
            plays, essays, and talks. Correspondence to Bodenheim is mostly from publishers with a
            few items from friends. Some personal correspondence from friends to Minna Bodenheim is
            also included. The vast majority of the correspondence is from from Maxwell Bodenheim to
            Minna Bodenheim, and runs from the 1920s to the mid 1930s.</p>
         <p>Most of the collection is made up of the manuscript and typescript drafts of Bodenheim's
            novels, poems, and plays. Covering the period between 1917 and the mid 1930s, the drafts
            contain material that Bodenheim would go on to publish both as novels and books of
            poetry, as well as various essays and talks that would be published in journals over the
            course of Bodenheim's life. The manuscripts for <title render="italic">Georgie
               MayM</title> (1928), <title render="italic">Crazy Man</title> (1924), and <title render="italic">Sixty Seconds</title> (1929) are included, as well as some of the
            material from Bodenheim's first published book of poetry, <title render="italic">Minna
               and Myself</title> (1918).</p>
         <p/>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged in 3 series <list type="marked">
                    <item>Series I:
                  Correspondence, 1917-1981</item>
               <item>Series II: People, 1920-1966</item>
                    <item>Series III: Writings,
               1917-1932</item>
                </list>
            </p>
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Bodenheim, Maxwell, 1893-1954.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Putnam, Samuel, 1892-1950.</persname>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651">Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.)--Intellectual life--20th
            century.</geogname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Modernism (Literature)--New York (State)--New York.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>This collection is located on-site. </p>
         <p>This collection has no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition</head>
         <p>Glenn Howowitz Purchase, 9/20/2011 2011-2012-M036</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); Maxwell Bodenheim Papers; Box and
            Folder; Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University Library.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>Papers processed 11/--/2011 Charles Macquarie, Pratt Institute 2012. </p>
         <p>Findign aid written 11/--/2011 Charles Macquarie, Pratt Institute 2012.</p>
      </processinfo>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
         <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. The RBML approves permission to
            publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to secure copyright permission
            rests with the patron.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <dsc><c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series I: Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1917-1981</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series contains correspondence that was exchanged between Bodenheim and his
                  wife Minna, letters sent to Bodenheim from friends, colleagues, and publishers,
                  and letters sent to Minna Bodenheim from individuals other than Maxwell Bodenheim
                  The material is arranged chronologically by year. The series also includes
                  correspondence about Bodenheim's divorce and the suit brought against him for
                     <title render="italic">Replenishing Jessica,</title> along with royalty
                  statements and contracts from publishers.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle>To Maxwell Bodenheim--General, <unitdate type="inclusive">1919-1935</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>To Minna Bodenheim</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                     <unittitle>General, <unitdate type="inclusive">1930-1954</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3 to 12</container>
                     <unittitle>From Maxwell Bodenheim, <unitdate type="inclusive">1917-1939</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(19 Folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1 to 9</container>
                     <unittitle>From Maxwell Bodenheim, <unitdate type="inclusive">1917-1939</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(19 Folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">10</container>
                  <unittitle>Legal Proceedings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1935-1981</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">11</container>
                  <unittitle>Contracts and Royalty Statements, <unitdate type="inclusive">1929-1934</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series II: People, <unitdate type="inclusive">1920-1966</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series consists of two folders containing materials on Bodenheim's son
                  Solbert and on Louis Grudin, respectively. Some materials relating to Solbert's
                  childhood are included. Included in the Grudin folder are several letters from
                  Bodenheim as well as an outline for the <title render="italic">Seven Sneers
                     Manifesto</title> which Bodenheim proposed to Grudin, drafts of several poems
                  sent by Bodenheim, and Grudin's eulogy for Bodenheim, which was never read.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">12</container>
                  <unittitle>Bodenheim, Solbert, <unitdate type="inclusive">1920-1932</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">13</container>
                  <unittitle>Grudin, Louis, <unitdate type="inclusive">1924-1966</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series III: Writings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1917-1932</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series is arranged into seven subdivisions by type of material--essays, novels,
                  plays, poems, reports, shorts stories, and talks. These subdivisions are arranged
                  alphabetically, and except for the poetry file which is arranged
                  chronologically, the folders and materials within them are arranged alphabetically
                  by title. The essays file contains critical essays, published and
                  unpublished, written between the mid 1920s and 1930s. The novels file
                  contains typescripts and manuscripts of published and unpublished novels from 1924
                  to 1932, including <title render="italic">Georgie May,</title> 
                  <title render="italic">Crazy Man,</title> 
                  <title render="italic">Six A.M.,</title> and <title render="italic">Sixty Seconds.</title> The plays
                  file includes manuscripts and typescripts of various plays by Bodenheim, all
                  of which are unpublished. The poems file contains manuscripts and typescripts
                  of poem drafts and translations written between 1917 and the 1930s. Included are
                  poems for <title render="italic">Minna and Myself</title> and poems from the unpublished collection <title render="italic">Tenderly.</title> The
                  reports subseries contains drafts of undated reports by Bodenheim on Fyodor
                  Dostoevsky and Karl Wasserman. The short stories file is made up of
                  manuscripts and typescripts of 3 undated short stories--"Alarm Clock", "Paris
                  Negro", and "The Silver Locket." The talks file contains Bodenheim's text for
                  several undated talks and discussions.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">14</container>
                  <unittitle>General</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Essays</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">15</container>
                     <unittitle>"The American Menagerie" and "Crime and the Underworld",
                           <unitdate>1929</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">16</container>
                     <unittitle>"Georgie May Answers the 'Virtuous' Critics", circa
                           <unitdate>1928</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1 to 7</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Laughing at Bombast,</title> circa
                           <unitdate>1930s</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(7 Folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                     <unittitle>"The Relation of Economics to Poetry", "Should Sex Dominate American
                        Literature?", and "What's Wrong with American Literature", circa
                           <unitdate>1930s</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Novels</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><unittitle><title render="italic">Crazy Man</title>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c level="file">
                     <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">9</container>
                        <unittitle>Manuscript, circa <unitdate>1924</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c>
                  <c level="file">
                     <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">10 to 11</container>
                        <unittitle>Typescript, circa <unitdate>1924</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                        <physdesc><extent>(2 Folders)</extent>
                        </physdesc>
                     </did>
                  </c>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">12</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Georgie May</title> manuscript, circa
                           <unitdate>1928</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">13</container>
                     <unittitle>"Incredible Manuscript", <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">14</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Six A.M.</title> typescript, circa
                           <unitdate>1932</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">15</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Sixty Seconds</title> manuscript, circa
                           <unitdate>1929</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1 to 2</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Strange Girl</title> typescript, circa
                           <unitdate>1930</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(2 Folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                     <unittitle>General manuscript, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><unittitle><title render="italic">Dream, Boy!</title>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c level="file">
                     <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                        <unittitle>Manuscript, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c>
                  <c level="file">
                     <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                        <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                        <unittitle>Typescript, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Georgie May</title> typescript, circa
                           <unitdate>1928</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">The Kitchen Absurd</title> typescript,
                           <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Love in Greenwich Village</title> manuscript,
                           <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">9</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">The Merry Priest</title> typescript,
                           <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">10</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">One Street</title> manuscript,
                           <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">11</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">What's it all About?</title> manuscript,
                           <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">12</container>
                     <unittitle>Typescript and manuscript, <unitdate>1917</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">13</container>
                     <unittitle>Typescript, Li Po Translations, circa
                        <unitdate>1917</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">14</container>
                     <unittitle>From <title render="italic">Minna and Myself,</title> typescript and
                        manuscript, circa <unitdate>1918</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">15</container>
                     <unittitle>typescript and manuscript, "Minna Poems", <unitdate type="inclusive">1918-1919</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">16</container>
                     <unittitle>Typescript and manuscript, <unitdate type="inclusive">1921-1928</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">17</container>
                     <unittitle>From <title render="italic">Tenderly</title> typescript and
                        manuscript, <unitdate type="inclusive">1928-1929</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">18</container>
                     <unittitle>"Gray Rivers" published, circa
                        <unitdate>1930s</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">19</container>
                  <unittitle>Reports--"Karl Wasserman" manuscript and typescript and "Fyodor
                     Dostoevsky" manuscript, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Short Stories</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">20</container>
                     <unittitle>"Alarm Clock" typescript, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">21</container>
                     <unittitle>"Paris Negro" manuscript, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">22</container>
                     <unittitle>"The Silver Locket" typescript,
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Talks</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">23</container>
                     <unittitle>Untitled manuscript and "Poetry and Greenwich Village" manuscript,
                           <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">24</container>
                     <unittitle>"Poetry and Sex" manuscript, "What's Wrong with American Novels"
                        typescript, and untitled manuscript pages,
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
         </c>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>