<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
   <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
      <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_7094252_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_7094252_ead.xml</eadid>
      <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the New York Clearing House Association
               Records,</titleproper>
            <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
               Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
               Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
               University Libraries</publisher>
            <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2009-05-02">May 2, 2009 </date>
            <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
               <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT conversion
               <date normal="2009-05-02">May 2, 2009 </date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2009-05-02">2009-05-02</date>
            <item>File created.</item>
         </change>
         <change><date normal="2009-06-02">2009-06-02</date>
            <item>xml document instance created by Lea Osborne.</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did><origination><corpname encodinganalog="110">New York Clearing House Association</corpname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="New York Clearing House Association Records,">New York Clearing House Association Records,</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1868/1950" type="inclusive">1868-1950</unitdate>
         <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">52 linear ft. (42 ledgers)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository encodinganalog="852">
            <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library</subarea>
            </corpname>
            <address><addressline>New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
         <unitid repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">MS#1464</unitid>
         <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">7094252</unitid>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
            <language langcode="&#xA;    eng&#xA;  "> In English. </language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract label="abstract">The New York Clearing House Association Records consist of 42
            large volumes of the association's financial ledgers, which contain daily and
            occasionally monthly accounts of the assets of numerous financial institutions in New
            York City in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. This is not a complete
            set of all New York Clearing House records between 1868 and 1950: missing are volumes
            for the years 1871-1872, 1875-1877, 1918-1922, 1937, and 1940.</abstract>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>History</head>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->The New York Clearing House Association was the first and
            largest bank clearing house in the United States. Established before the Civil War, this
            entity was intended by its founders to systematize and rationalize previously
            disorganized exchanges and settlements between New York City's banks. These institutions
            which established the Clearing House became the very heart of American finance in the
            late nineteenth century as the nation developed a financial system increasingly
            autonomous from the English and European banks on which Americans had previously
            depended for credit and capital investment. During the American Civil War, the federal
            government intervened in a growing financial sector and developed fiscal and monetary
            policies adequate to the Union's military and industrial needs. In the war's aftermath,
            New York's banks, and the credit the banks made available, financed a rapid expansion of
            American industry and transportation infrastructure which made the United States a
            global economic power and conquered the American West by the end of the nineteenth
            century. In the twentieth century, some of the New York Clearing House's member banks,
            symbolized in American society, politics, and culture by "Wall Street," came to
            represent both the awesome power of a robust American financial sector and the greed and
            irresponsibility which many believed precipitated the disastrous stock market crash of
            1929 and the Great Depression of the 1930s. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->The California Gold Rush and an explosion in railroad
            construction marked the four years before 1853, when the Clearing House was founded. In
            this same period the number of New York City's banks more than doubled, from 24 to 57.
            Before the Clearing House, banks had settled their accounts in a laborious manner,
            employing porters to travel from bank to bank to exchange checks for gold specie. This
            process became a daily event as the number of banks multiplied. However, the actual
            reckoning of accounts between banks typically occurred on Fridays in front of a Wall
            Street bank, in what came to be called the "Porter's Exchange." This practice
            necessarily led to errors in records and abuse. Several bankers looked to London's
            Clearing House system as a model for resolving the cumbersome weekly settlement process
            as others expressed frustration with the current system. In 1831, Albert Gallatin,
            previously the Secretary of the Treasury for the United States and President of the
            National Bank of New York, wrote that the lack of a daily exchange of drafts among banks
            "produces relaxations, favors improper expansions and is attended with serious
            inconveniences." </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->In 1851, George D. Lyman, a New York bank's bookkeeper,
            suggested in an anonymous article that banks should consider sending and receiving
            checks through a central office. On August 18, 1853, he repeated his proposal in another
            article to which he affixed his name, and asked interested cashiers to contact him if
            they endorsed his plan. The city's banks responded enthusiastically. On October 4, 1853,
            the New York Clearing House was officially established by a group of cashiers led by
            Francis E. Edmonds of the Mechanics Bank. On October 11, in the basement of 14 Wall
            Street, 52 banks participated in the first transaction, exchanging checks worth $22.6
            million. Two decades later, the average daily clearing approached $100 million. At the
            new Clearing House, specie certificates replaced gold as the means of settling balances.
            Porters exchanging certificates for gold deposited at the Clearing House's member banks
            now no longer exchanged specie, thus experiencing fewer errors and risks. The use of
            specie certificates also relieved the strain of the banks' cash flows and reduced the
            potential for runs on deposits. Requirements for all member banks, such as weekly
            audits, minimum reserve levels, and a daily settlement of all balances, ensured
            increasingly efficient and regularized exchanges. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Lyman retired from his position as manager of the Clearing
            House in 1864, and was succeeded by William A. Camp. Camp had previously been appointed
            in 1855 as a discount clerk in the Importers and Traders' Bank of New York. Appointed
            first teller of the Artisans' Bank the next year, Camp in 1857 was hired as the
            assistant manager at the Clearing House. He was manager for the Clearing House for the
            years in which the first volumes of these records began to be kept. "To executive
            ability of a high order," Albert S. Bolles wrote of Camp and his Clearing House in
               <title render="italic">Practical Banking </title>(1884), Camp "unites unusual
            accuracy and promptness in the dispatch[sic] of business, as well as a wide
            acquaintance, both theoretical and practical, with financial subjects...": </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->"It speaks volumes for the care and scrupulous accuracy with
            which the business has been conducted, that in the entire history of the Clearing-house,
            extending over nearly thirty-one years, its transactions have always balanced to a cent.
            The only instance on record of an error in any statement emanating from it occurred a
            few years ago in the weekly bank statement, and this was due to an error of one of the
            clerks in transcribing the figures. In making the entries, the officials at the
            Clearing-house and their subordinates use ink only. The clerks sent by the banks may at
            their option make their entries in pencil." </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->The New York Clearing House naturally became an instrument of
            financial self-regulation in the numerous economic downturns and financial panics that
            occurred on average every five-and-a-half years between 1853 and 1913, in a rapidly
            expanding American economy. Leading Clearing House member banks first attempted to
            stabilize a tottering financial system in the 1857 panic. When specie payments were
            suspended, Clearing House banks, in an effort to shorten the panic's duration and
            increase public confidence, started to issue "Clearing House Loan Certificates."
            Effectively a kind of currency, these certificates were backed not by gold but by
            discounted county and state bank notes held by member banks. Printed with the words
            "Payable Through the Clearing House," these loan certificates were the joint liability
            of all Clearing House member banks, making them a far more secure form of payment. They
            were issued in smaller denominations in the 1873 panic, and were maintained by member
            banks as a substitute currency in later financial crises, including the depression which
            began in 1893-1894. Though it has been argued that these certificates violated federal
            laws against privately-issued currencies, a contemporary once wrote that the Clearing
            House's loan certificates "performed so valuable a service...in moving the crops and
            keeping business machinery in motion, that the government...wisely forbore to
            prosecute." </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Because of their stability during financial panics, the
            Clearing House Loan Certificate's value became a reliable measure of the financial
            health of the American economy as a whole. Bolstered by discounted collateral, each Loan
            Certificate was worth more than its dollar equivalent. The currency premium, or exchange
            rate, between Clearing House money and greenbacks (or gold specie) thus operated as an
            indicator of the gradual restoration in bank money. When the premium dropped to zero, a
            one-to-one relationship obtained between certificates and currency, making substitution
            unnecessary. In 1913, the passage of the Federal Reserve Act by the U.S. Congress
            established a clearing house system at the federal government level, modeled after the
            private New York Clearing House and other similar financial exchange institutions across
            the nation. The Federal Reserve system subsequently and effectively assumed the role
            which private clearing houses had played in stabilizing and regularizing exchanges and
            mitigating financial panics.</p>
         <p/>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>The New York Clearing House Association Records consist of 42 large bound volumes.</p>
         <p/>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged chronologically.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610">New York Clearing House Association.</corpname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Banks and Banking--Accounting.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Banks and Banking--New York (State)</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Banks and Banking--New York (State)--New York.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Finance--New York (State)</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Finance--United States.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Finance--United States--Accounting.</subject>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Ledgers (account books)</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least
            twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript
            Library reading room. </p>
         <p>This collection has no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition</head>
         <p>Clearing House Payments Company Gift, 2008</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); New York Clearing House Association
            Records; Box and Folder; Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University
         Library.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>Papers processed in March 2009 by Justin Jackson, GSAS 2012</p>
         <p>Finding aid written in March 2009 by Justin Jackson, GSAS 2012</p>
      </processinfo>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
         <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish material
            from the collection must be requested from the Curator of Manuscripts/University
            Archivist, Rare Book and Manuscript Library (RBML). The RBML approves permission to
            publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to secure copyright permission
            rests with the patron.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <dsc><c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Ledgers</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1868-1870</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1873-1874</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1878-1883</unitdate> (Monthly
                  Records)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1878-1880</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1880-1882</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1883-1885</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">7</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1885-1887</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">8</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1887-1889</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">9</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1889-1891</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">10</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1891-1893</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">11</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1894-1895</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">12</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1896-1897</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">13</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1898-1899</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">14</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1900-1901</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">15</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1902-1903</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">16</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1904-1905</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">17</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1906-1907</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">18</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1908-1909</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">19</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1910-1911</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">20</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1912-1913</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">21</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1914-1915</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">22</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1916-1917</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">23</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1923</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">24</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1924</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">25</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1925</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">26</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1926</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">27</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1927</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">28</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1928</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">29</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1929</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">30</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1930</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">31</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1931</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">32</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1932</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">33</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1933</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">34</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1934</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">35</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1935</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">36</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1936</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">37</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1938</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">38</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1939</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">39</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1941-1942</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">40</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1943-1944</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">41</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>1945</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">42</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1945-1950</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>