<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
   <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
      <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_7299068_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_7299068_ead.xml</eadid>
      <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the James Harper papers,</titleproper>
            <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
               Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
               Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
               University Libraries</publisher>
            <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2010-04-07">April 7, 2010 </date>
            <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
               <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT conversion
               <date normal="2010-04-07">April 7, 2010 </date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2010-04-07">2010-04-07</date>
            <item>xml document instance created by Carrie Hintz.</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did><origination><persname encodinganalog="100">Harper, James, 1795-1869</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="James Harper papers,">James Harper
            Papers,</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1800/1925" type="inclusive">1800-1925.</unitdate>
         <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">4.59 linear ft. (5 document boxes 2 record cartons 1
               oversize box)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository encodinganalog="852">
            <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library</subarea>
            </corpname>
            <address><addressline>Butler Library, 6th Fl. East, 535 West 114th St., New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
         <unitid encodinganalog="090$b" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">MS#1495</unitid>
         <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">7299068</unitid>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
            <language langcode="eng"> Material is in English. </language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract>The collection consists of diverse materials, photographs, correspondence and legal papers documenting the history of Harper family. The collection also includes books owned by members of the Harper family and books published by Harper &amp; Brothers.  </abstract>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical Note</head>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Harper &amp; Brothers was one of most prestigious American
            printing houses of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. The original company, named
            J&amp;J Harper, was established in 1817 in offices on Dover Street in New York by
            the two eldest of the four Harper brothers, James and John. The brothers were the sons
            of an English Methodist schoolmaster and carpenter who settled in Newtown, New York in
            1740. Though James and John started the company, other members of the Harper family soon
            became involved in the business. After being apprentices for several years, the two
            younger brothers, Joseph Wesley and Fletcher, were included into the firm, which became
            in 1833 Harper Brothers with offices and printing house at 81 and 82 Cliff Street, New
            York. James, the eldest of the brothers, was perceived as the nominal head of the
            company while Fletcher was recognized as the authentic head of the business. James was
            the initiator of <title render="italic">Harper's Magazine</title> while Fletcher controlled the business and was
            responsible for the <title render="italic">Weekly</title> and the <title render="italic">Bazaar.</title> In 1844 James was also elected mayor of New
            York. He was a prominent figure of New York political life and enjoyed an exceptional
            repute. He died in a carriage accident in 1869. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->After the death or retirement of the founders, the sons and
            grand-sons of the original Harper brothers continued their legacy. The later generations
            continued the tradition of coordinating the business as a family company under the
            strict rule of non acceptance of partners unrelated with the family. Until the middle of
            the twentieth century the company remained under the sole authority of the Harper family
            descendents. As directly instructed by Fletcher, the youngest of the first four
            initiators of the firm, all the sons entering the family business had to receive the
            highest education and after traveling through Europe for the purpose of learning foreign
            languages they had to enter the composition room. Under the direction of the foreman
            they had to learn to set a page as any compositor in the office and be able to earn a
            living in case of any vicissitudes. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->In 1896, at the death of the last survivor of the second
            generation of Harpers, Philip Jacob Arcularius, the firm was under the control of seven
            cousins, each with separate responsibilities in a distinct department. Philip, born on
            October 21st 1824 was the son of James, one of the four founders of the company. He
            married Harriet Meade (Hyde) on June 30th 1846 and had a son James born in 1847. James
            married Lillie Mercein (Hyde) and had a son James Harper Jr. (1879 -1944) and a daughter
            Lillie Hyde Harper (1881-1941). James Harper Jr. married Helen Leale and had a son,
            James Harper (Jamie) born on 4th of July 1919. The present collection reflects mainly
            the lives of these members of Harper family and of the families related to them.</p>
         <p/>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>The collection is composed of photographs, letters, diaries, legal documents, books and
            personal items from the estate of Helen Leale Harper Jr., great-great-grand daughter of
            James Harper, one of the four brothers that founded Harper &amp; Brothers. Some of
            the items in the collection are albums, photographs and Bibles recording the history of
            Harper family in-laws-- the Copcutt, Meade, Hyde and Leale families. While part of the
            collection's articles document Harper firm activity, others are miscellaneous personal
            chronicle items as: letters, drawings, locks of hair, diaries and photographs.</p> 
         <p>Some of
            the items of particular historic value include the marriage certificate of James Harper
            and Maria Arcularius, Bibles belonging to Philip Harper, James Harper and Copcutt family
            - with records of births, marriages and deaths in the family, and books printed by the
            Harper and Brothers firm in the first years of activity.</p>
         <p/>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged in four series: <list type="marked">
                    <item>Series I: Photographs, 1800-1920</item>
                    <item>Series II:
            Correspondence, 1882-1952</item>
                    <item>Series III: Miscellaneous papers, 1818-1919</item>
                    <item>Series IV:
               Books, from 1808 to 1917<list type="marked">
                            <item>Subseries IV.1 Books owned by members of Harper family</item>
                            <item>Subseries IV.2: Bibles owned by Harper Family, 1842-1855</item>
                            <item>Subseries IV.3 Books printed by J&amp;J Harper and Harper &amp; Brothers</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </p>
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Harper, Lillie Hyde, 1881-1941.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Harper, James, 1795-1869.</persname>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651">Geographic</geogname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Literature Publishing.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Publishers and publishing--New York (State)--New
            York.</subject>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Correspondence.</genreform>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Photographs.</genreform>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Bible records.</genreform>
         <occupation encodinganalog="656" source="lcsh">Publishers.</occupation>
      </controlaccess>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>The following boxes are located off-site: 1-7. You will need to request this material
            from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to
            use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room. </p>
         <p>This collection has no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition</head>
         <p>James Cummins Booksellers Purchase. July, 2009</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <custodhist encodinganalog="561">
         <p>All items in the collection from the estate of Helen Leale Harper, Jr.</p>
      </custodhist>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); James Harper Papers; Box and Folder
            (if known); Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University Library.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>Papers processed 12/2009 Cela Peterson, Pratt Institute School of Library and
            Information Science. </p>
         <p>Finding aid written 12/2009 Cela Peterson, Pratt Institute School of Library and
            Information Science.</p>
      </processinfo>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
         <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish material
            from the collection must be requested from the Curator of Manuscripts/University
            Archivist, Rare Book and Manuscript Library (RBML). The RBML approves permission to
            publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to secure copyright permission
            rests with the patron.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <relatedmaterial><head>Selected Related Material-- At Columbia</head>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/lweb/archival/collections/ldpd_4079530/index.html">Harper &amp; Bros. Records, 1817-1929</extref> Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library</p>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/lweb/archival/collections/ldpd_4078866/index.html">Harper &amp; Row, Publishers Records, 1935-1973.</extref>Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <dsc><c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series I: Photographs, circa <unitdate type="inclusive">1800-1920</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series is composed of three photograph albums with typical nineteenth century photographic portraits, one recording the Harper-Hyde-Meade branch of the family and the others with portraits of the Leale- Copcutt family members. Four folders of this series contain framed pictures from the beginning of nineteenth century, portraits of Philip A. Harper, from the end of nineteenth century, and pictures of various groups of people, including members and friends of the family, from nineteenth century. Philip A Harper’s folder contains pictures of family members and of the family residence in Far Rockaway. Some of the portrait pictures are captioned on the back, but the majority of the group pictures are hard to identify because of either the lack of captioning or a mere mention of a familial relationship or date and event. The folders in this series are arranged chronologically. </p>
                </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1 </container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1 </container>
                  <unittitle>Photo album Harper family, late Nineteenth Century</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1 </container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Framed photo, circa <unitdate>1800</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1 </container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3 </container>
                  <unittitle>Photos - Philip A. Harper, circa <unitdate>1800</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1 </container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                  <unittitle>Photos - Leale-Copcutt family, late Nineteenth - early Twentieth
                     Century</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Photo album Leale-Copcutt family, Nineteenth Century</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Various photos, circa <unitdate>1800</unitdate> to
                        <unitdate>1920</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Various photos, <unitdate type="inclusive">1881-1923</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">8</container>
                 
                  <unittitle>James Harper, Oversize photograph portrait
                     <unitdate>1869</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series II: Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1882-1952</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>The items in this series are mainly personal letters of family members, some business letters and three folders of sympathy notes related to the death of James Harper, in January 1944. Two folders contain artist’s Lillie Hyde Harper (1881-1941) letters addressed to her brother James, from various European countries, written while she was studying arts in France, in the 1920s. This series contains also letters from Philip a Harper to his grand-mother Maria Arcularius (founder James Harper’s mother) and from Ralph Mead to his son-in-law Philip Harper. The folders in this series are also arranged chronologically.</p>
                </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous Harper Family Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1854-1882</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Harper, James, Jr.</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                     <unittitle>Childhood correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1884-1890</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                     <unittitle>To Mr. and Mrs. James Harper (his parents),
                           <unitdate>1910</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Philip J.A. Harper .</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                     <unittitle>Sawyer, Robert H. to Philip Harper, <unitdate type="inclusive">1858-1861</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                     <unittitle>Mead, Ralph to Philip Harper, <unitdate>1862</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                     <unittitle>Harper, Philip General Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1858-1893</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7 to 9</container>
                  <unittitle>Harper, Lillie Hyde to James Harper and family, <unitdate type="inclusive">1923-1927</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                  <physdesc><extent>(3 Folders)</extent>
                  </physdesc>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">10</container>
                  <unittitle>Helen Leale Harper correspondence and mementos, <unitdate type="inclusive">1944-1952</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1 to 3</container>
                  <unittitle>James Harper- Sympathy Cards, <unitdate>January-August
                        1944</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                  <physdesc><extent>(3 Folders)</extent>
                  </physdesc>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><container type="Folder" label="Folder"> </container>
               <unittitle>Series III: Miscellaneous, <unitdate type="inclusive">1818-1919</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series is composed of six folders, chronologically organized, of legal papers, diaries and pamphlets, and two over-size folders holding drawings and news-papers. This series includes: Maria Arcularius's diary documenting her trip to Europe in 1835, James Harper Jr.'s baby book, from 1919 (containing a genealogical tree), locks of hair, and short notes of a personal nature. One of the pamphlets in this series is the centennial commemorative 1917 advertisement of the reprint of the first work by Harper printers, <title render="italic">Seneca’s Morals</title> with facsimile pages from the first edition and letter with a sample reservation note from the company. This pamphlet reveals the fact that Joseph Wesley Harper and Fletcher Harper, the two younger brothers of the four founders, worked on the first printed Harper book, in 1817, as compositors. One folder of this series contains a tentative genealogical outline of one branch of Harper family and a history of family names of English origin (Harper included); the author of both documents is not mentioned. Particularly interesting and revealing, of the history of the family, are the clippings from new papers of several obituaries for the death of Philip A. Harper (a second generation); these short articles from the press of the time brings light into the complicated genealogy and succession of Harpers.</p>
                </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Legal papers, <unitdate>1818-1823</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Maria Arcularius Harper, diary, <unitdate>1
                1822-1835</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Pamphlets, <unitdate>1844-circa
                    1850</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                  <unittitle>Prospectus, Seneca reediting <unitdate>1917</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                  <unittitle>James Harper Jr., baby book <unitdate>1919</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous, circa <unitdate>1900</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">8</container>
                  <unittitle>News-papers, oversize Folder, Nineteenth and Twentieth
                     Century</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">8</container>
                  <unittitle>Drawings, Twentieth Century</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series IV: Books, <unitdate type="inclusive">1808-1916</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series is comprised of books owned or published by the Harper Family.</p>
                </scopecontent>
            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle>Subseries IV.1: Books owned by Harper Family, <unitdate type="inclusive">1808-1916</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>  Sub-series IV.1 Books owned by members of Harper family. This sub-series contains two categories of books: general knowledge and bibles, from as early as 1808 to 1912. The general knowledge books are of various subjects as children’s book, Italian grammar, or <title render="italic">Shakespeare and the Precious Stones</title> (signed by the author). The three Bibles belonging to James Harper, Philip Harper and Copcutt family contain some record notes of births, marriages and deaths in the family.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Imitation of Christ,</title> John Wesley,
                        <unitdate>1808</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                     <unittitle>The book of common prayer, <unitdate>1818</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Ring - a - round - a - Rosy,</title> Mary A. Lathbury,
                           <unitdate>1885</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Elementary Italian grammar,</title> Pietro Motti,
                        <unitdate>1912</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Shakespeare and precious stones,</title> George Frederick Kunz,
                           <unitdate>1916</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle>Subseries IV.2: Bibles owned by Harper Family, <unitdate type="inclusive">1842-1855</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
              
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                     <unittitle>Cupcutt family Bible, <unitdate>1842</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                    
                     <unittitle>Philip J.A. Harper Bible, <unitdate>1846</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">6</container>
                   
                     <unittitle>James Harper's Bible, <unitdate>1855</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="subseries">
               <did><unittitle>Subseries IV.3: Books printed by Harper &amp;amp; Brothers,
                        <unitdate type="inclusive">1817-1896</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Sub-series IV.3 Books printed by J&amp;J Harper and Harper &amp; Brothers. The topics of the six books that constitute this sub-series also varies from geography to geology, fairy-tales to Christian philosophy. The books date from 1817 to 1893, and illustrate the craftsmanship of the printing enterprise founded by Harper brothers.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">7</container>
                    
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">A series of discourses on he Christian revelation viewed in
                        connexion with the modern astronomy,</title> Thomas Chalmers,
                           <unitdate>1817</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">7</container>
                  
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">An essay concerning human understanding,</title> John Locke,
                           <unitdate>1818</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">7</container>
                
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">The fairy book,</title> 
                        <unitdate>1853</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">7</container>
                    
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">A tour around New York and my summer acre,</title> John Flavel Mines,
                           <unitdate>1893</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">7</container>
                    
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">The Danube from the Black Forest to the Black Sea,</title> D. Millet,
                           <unitdate>1893</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">7</container>
                    
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">The Student's Lyell,</title> edited by John W. Judd,
                           <unitdate>1896</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle/>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>

      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>