<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
   <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">-
      <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_7269482_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_7269482_ead.xml</eadid>
      <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the Imre Forbáth diaries,</titleproper>
            <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
               Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
               Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
               University Libraries</publisher>
            <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2010-02-18">February 18, 2010 </date>
            <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
               <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT conversion
               <date normal="2010-02-18">February 18, 2010 </date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2010-02-18">2010-02-18</date>
            <item>xml document instance created by Carrie Hintz</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did><origination><persname encodinganalog="100">Forbáth, Imre.</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="Imre Forbáth diaries,">Imre Forbáth
            Diaries,</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1900/1943" type="inclusive">1900-1943.</unitdate>
         <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">2 linear ft. (4 document boxes)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository encodinganalog="852">
            <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Bakhmeteff
                  Archive</subarea>
            </corpname>
            <address><addressline>New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
         <unitid encodinganalog="090$b" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">BA#0527</unitid>
         <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">7269482</unitid>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
            <language langcode="ger"> Material is in Hungarian and German. </language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract>This collection comprises twenty one journals of Imre Forbath (ака Emerich
            Forbath), one of the greatest engineers in Europe. These diaries span the period from
            1900 to 1943.</abstract>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>History</head>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Imre Forbáth (aka Emerich Forbath) was born in 1875 and died in 1944. One of the greatest engineers in Europe, he lived during the turbulent final decades of the Habsburg Monarchy, the First World War, the troubled Twenties and Thirties, and the Second World War. He was an eyewitness to many of the historic events of these times.</p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->The young Hungarian-Jewish engineer Forbáth started his career as a civil engineer in Frankfurt and Berlin after attending universities in the Austro-Hungarian Empire and in Germany. He later worked in cities all over Europe in this period of rapid urban growth. He became known as one of the greatest engineers in Europe.</p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Imre Forbáth took part in the canalization of the major European rivers and in the designing of ports. He also worked on such urban infrastructure projects as water supply, sewage systems, gas works, and power plants. The nitrogen factory he directed for seventeen years, gaining for it an international reputation, still exists in Romania.</p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->His peers regarded him as the best writer on city planning of his time. Forbáth published articles in professional journals and elsewhere on a weekly basis. In 1906, he became a private professor at the Budapest Technical University. Imre Forbáth was regarded as one of the leading figures in Budapest’s engineering and political worlds.</p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->It was his fate to be present during many important historical events. Imre Forbáth took part in the First World War as an engineer with the Austro-Hungarian forces. His division was sent to Przemysl, which was besieged by the Russians. In his journal, he writes movingly about conditions in the surrounded fortress. When all their food ran out, the Austro-Hungarian troops had to surrender. This was one of the crucial moments of the war for Austria-Hungary. Forbáth’s account of this event is the only detailed one that has survived.</p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->After the surrender of the fortress, he became a prisoner of war in Russia with his fellow soldiers and was taken to Siberia, to the cities of Tobolsk and Petropavlovsk, from which he managed to escape. He appeared in Moscow eight months after the Russian Revolution of 1917. He returned to Hungary when a Soviet republic was established there, too, during 1919. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->His house and property were nationalized, but he was looked upon with respect by the revolutionaries as one of Budapest’s leading engineers. He held a position under the regime but resigned before it collapsed. The treaty of Trianon formally ended the First World War for Hungary in 1920, completely redrawing the country’s borders.</p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Forbáth kept his intellectual outlook and optimism for a better future alive throughout this disturbed period. His historical writings, unlike his technical ones, remained unknown and unpublished during his lifetime. Other than a few lines in biographical dictionary articles, nothing was written about his life in Hungary or elsewhere in Europe. Even the fact of his tragic death in the Holocaust in 1944 was not known. The Hungarian biographical lexicon and the Report of the Hungarian Hydraulic Society give his year of death as around 1952.</p>
         <p/>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>The collection contains twenty one journals of Imre Forbath (aka Emerich Forbath), Hungarian engineer. The handwritten journals span the period from 1900 to 1943 and cover many important historical events and provide a valuable record on twentieth-century Hungarian and European history, history of technology, culture, and political life.</p>
         <p>There is also two photographs, one letter, one business card, and one book-plate found as inserts in the diaries and placed in one folder.</p>
         <p>The Budapest Archive has some documents from György Forbáth, engineer, who escaped from Russian captivity. Most likely, these are also a part of Imre Forbáth’s legacy.</p>
         <p/>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>Diaries arranged in chronological order. Various inserts found in journals are placed in one folder and stored at the end of the collection in Box 4.</p>
         <p>Description of the each journal includes a summary of the content and alphabetical list of people, writings, public presentation, and works mentioned in the journal.</p>
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651">Austria--History--1867-1918.</geogname>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651">Europe--History--20th century.</geogname>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651">Hungary--History--20th century.</geogname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">City Planning.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Civil engineering--Hungary--20th century.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Civil engineering--Europe--20th century.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Hydraulic engineering--Europe--20th centruy.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">World War, 1914-1918.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">World War, 1939-1945.</subject>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Diaries.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>This collection is located on-site. </p>
         <p>This collection has no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition</head>
         <p>Pauline Forbáth and William E.Forbáth Gift 2000</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); Imre Forbáth Diaries; Box and Volume;
            Bakhmeteff Archive, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University Library.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>Papers processed 2008 Maria Subert </p>
         <p>Finding aid written 2008 Maria Subert </p>
         <p>Finding aid prepared for publication 2/2010 Katia Shraga</p>
      </processinfo>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
         <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish material
            from the collection must be requested from the Curator of the Bakhmeteff Archive. The
            RBML approves permission to publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to
            secure copyright permission rests with the patron.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="555">
         <p>Finding aid in repository and online</p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <dsc><c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Imre Forbáth Diaries, <unitdate>1900-1943</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 1: <unitdate>March 29, 1900 - November 31, 1901</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>At the time of his first entries, Imre Forbáth is still using his original last
                     name of Fischer. He is twenty-five years old, fluent in Hungarian, German, and
                     French, a recent graduate of the Technical Universities of Vienna, Zurich, and
                     Berlin. Imre Forbáth records his opinions on the latest developments in
                     literature, philosophy, and music. While employed as a civil engineer for the
                     city of Magdeburg, he works on his doctoral dissertation. The young civil
                     engineer falls in love with Trüdchen, a German Christian woman, but has to
                     break up with her. He writes a sensitive reflection on the relationship between
                     Christians and Jews at this time. Conscripted into the Austro-Hungarian army,
                     he is sent to Croatia for military training. While there he records the solar
                     eclipse of May 15, 1901. He wins third place in an international competition
                     for city planning in Bergen. Mother sells her house.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Places mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Bergen</item>
                     <item>Budapest</item>
                     <item>Cologne</item>
                     <item>Érsekujvár</item>
                     <item>Magdeburg</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Hilson</item>
                     <item>Koppány, Géza</item>
                     <item>Kramer</item>
                     <item>Lüschen</item>
                     <item>Trüdchen</item>
                     <item>Unterführung Schörer</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this Period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">Bau der Städte an Flüssen</title> (Building of the
                        Cities by the Rivers)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Canalisation von Mailand </title>(Canalization of
                        Milan)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Chicago Arkadische Canal </title>(Arched Canal of
                        Chicago)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kikötőkerdes: Frankfurt, Mainz, Düsseldorf,
                           Ludvigshafen, Dreschen kikötőirol </title>(Studies on the Frankfurt,
                        Mainz, Düsseldorf, Ludwigshafen, and Dreschen Ports)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Mannheim Csatornázási Terve </title>(Canalization
                        Plans for Mannheim)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Muhlheim Csatornázási Tervei </title>(Canalization
                        Plans for Mühlheim)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Nemet Mérnökok Helyzeterol </title>(About the Lives
                        of the German Engineers)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Nordbrücke Electricitätswerk </title>(Power Plant of
                        Nordbrücke)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Ontozes Városi Szennyvízekkel </title>(Irrigating
                        with Sewage from the City)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Studien von der Riesenfelder </title>(Studies on the
                        Sewage Farms)</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Public Presentations made:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A városok kozegeszsegugyerol a szennycsatornakat
                           erintve </title>(Cities’ Common Health Considering Sewers), Engineers’
                        Society (Mernok Egylet)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Vaskapu szabalyozásáról </title>(Regulation of the
                        Vaskapu), Engineers’ Society (Mernok Egylet)</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Canal of Dwigue</item>
                     <item>Canal of Nyitra</item>
                     <item>Canal of Sarajevo</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 2: <unitdate>December 1, 1901 - October 16, 1904</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>At this time, the writer of the journals uses the family name
                     “Forbáth-Fischer.” He is a paid employee of the city of Frankfurt, working as a
                     civil engineer. He is a member of the Society of Engineers of Frankfurt, as
                     well as of the city’s Skittles Society. He is published regularly in the
                     Technicians’ Association Journal. After getting his Austrian diploma
                     recognized, he earns a doctorate with honors in Darmstadt (his thesis:
                     Stadtebau in Alten und Neuer Zeit/ City Building in the Past and Present). He
                     takes part in a trial concerning Magdeburg’s building supplies. In 1903, Imre
                     Forbáth quits his job in Frankfurt and moves to Berlin, where he becomes head
                     engineer and assistant principal of the office of civil engineering. Rapidly
                     expanding opportunities in the field of city building bring him home to
                     Hungary, where Imre Forbáth establishes a private engineering office in Pest.
                     He loses the network of contacts in government and engineering circles that he
                     had built up in Germany and has to develop a new one. Still quite a young man,
                     he sets out to find work for his private engineering firm. Forbáth meets all
                     the major political leaders of Hungarian cities where improvements are being
                     undertaken. He holds liberal political views, which make him unique in his
                     conservative circle. In Pest, he encounters ultra-radical socialist views for
                     the first time in his life. The young engineer longs to live in England or
                     America. He reads widely and keeps up with everything new in cultural life.
                     Imre Forbáth publishes articles, mainly about the building of ports. For
                     hygienic reasons, cities begin to build slaughterhouses. Forbáth’s plans win
                     first place in a competition for a slaughterhouse in Altenesse. The family
                     attends Joseph's wedding. Mother lives in Vienna. Uncle Rudolph dies.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Places mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Bergen</item>
                     <item>Berlin</item>
                     <item>Budapest</item>
                     <item>Cologne</item>
                     <item>Darmstadt</item>
                     <item>Érsekujvár</item>
                     <item>Frankfurt</item>
                     <item>Magdeburg</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Alesius</item>
                     <item>Altheim</item>
                     <item>Alzheim</item>
                     <item>Bella</item>
                     <item>Berg and Peron</item>
                     <item>Bohm</item>
                     <item>Brix</item>
                     <item>Cauter</item>
                     <item>Drotleff</item>
                     <item>Eichberg</item>
                     <item>Faragó</item>
                     <item>Farkass</item>
                     <item>Feldman</item>
                     <item>Finaly, István</item>
                     <item>Földes (Professor)</item>
                     <item>Ganzerzen, Kertz</item>
                     <item>Goecke</item>
                     <item>Hengsberger (his boss)</item>
                     <item>Hiemesh (Mayor)</item>
                     <item>Hoffman (builder)</item>
                     <item>Hoffman (Professor at Darmstadt)</item>
                     <item>Holeman, Philip</item>
                     <item>Hoszpotzky</item>
                     <item>Jossa</item>
                     <item>Kassay</item>
                     <item>Klonne</item>
                     <item>Kolle (his boss)</item>
                     <item>Kollischert (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Kovács, Aladár I.</item>
                     <item>Lahmeyer, Salamon</item>
                     <item>Láng, Károly</item>
                     <item>Lastyánszky</item>
                     <item>Lion</item>
                     <item>Luthi</item>
                     <item>Pfeffer</item>
                     <item>Pichler</item>
                     <item>Putzer</item>
                     <item>Schongut</item>
                     <item>Schutter (engineer)</item>
                     <item>Tisza, István</item>
                     <item>Tragen</item>
                     <item>Uhlfelder</item>
                     <item>Walbe (Professor at Darmstadt)</item>
                     <item>Wecsei, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Zichmeister (Mayor of Győr)</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Mannheimi Kikötők </title>(Ports of
                        Mannheim)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Altenessei Vágóhíd </title>(Slaughterhouse of
                        Altenesse)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Bau der Städte an Flüssen: Frankfurt am Main
                        </title>(Building of Cities on Rivers: Frankfurt am Main)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Belhajózási Kikötők Fontossága Forgalmi Szempontból
                        </title>(Importance of Ports for Inland Shipping Considering Traffic).
                           <title render="italic">Weekly Shipping Journal (Hajozasi Hetilap)</title>
                     </item>
                     <item>Canalization of Sidney</item>
                     <item>Cement Canal of Westend <title render="italic">Centralblatt</title>
                     </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Egynehány Tengeri és Belhajózási Viteldíj
                           Összehasonlítása </title>(Comparison of Sea and Inland Shipping
                           Fares).<title render="italic">Weekly Informant (Heti Ertesito)</title>
                     </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Goethe.</title>
                        <title render="italic">Zeitschrift für Binneuschrift 5</title>
                     </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kanalisation der Altstadt von
                        Magdeburg</title>(Canalization of Magdeburg). <title render="italic">Centralblatt Cistern of Dortmund; Centralblatt</title>
                     </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kanalisation von Mailand </title>(Canalization of
                        Milan)</item>
                     <item>Ports: Grieslan, Cologne, Dortmund, Kreflo</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Social und Wirtschlaftliche Vorarbeiten für Stadt
                           Erneuerungsplane</title>(Social and Scientific Preparations for
                        Renovation Plans for Cities).<title render="italic">Städtebau</title>
                     </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városaink Rendezése </title>(Arrangement of Our
                        Cities). <title render="italic">Szabolcs</title>
                     </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városfejlesztési Munkák </title>(City Development
                        Works). <title render="italic">Szabolcs</title>
                     </item>
                     <item>Works on the Danube. Ges. Ing.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Public Presentations made:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Majnafrankfurti Új Gabonasiló </title>(Granary in
                        Frankfurt am Main)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Vasút Új Javító Munkálatairól </title>(About the
                        New Train Repair Works), at Mérnök és Ép. Egylet (Engineer and Architect
                        Society)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Az Egészségügyi Mérnöki Munkák Hygiéniai és
                           Közgazdasági Fontosságáról </title>(Hygienic and Economical Importance of
                        the Health Engineer Works)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Az Új Vízvezetéki Díjszabályzat </title>(New Water
                        Supply Fees)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Bau des Stadte an Flüssen in Alter und Neuer Zeit
                        </title>(City Building on Rivers in Old and New Times)</item>
                     <item>Canalization in Nagyszeben <title render="italic">(Nagyszebeni
                           Csatornázás)</title>
                     </item>
                     <item>Canalization in Rodelcheim <title render="italic">(Rodelcheim-i
                           Csatornázás)</title>
                     </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Frankfurt Mérnöki Hivataláról és Annak
                           Munkáiról</title>(Office of Engineering in Frankfurt and its
                        Works)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Nagyszebeni Villamosmű </title>(Power Plant of
                        Nagyszeben)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Népszerű Főiskola-i Tanfolyam Vízvezeték és Csatorna
                           Dolgában </title>(Water Supply and Canalization Course at the Community
                        College)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Pozsonyi Vágóhíd </title>(Slaughterhouse of
                        Bratislava)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Städtebaufragen</title>(Questions of City
                        Building)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Szeged Közvágóhíd </title>(Slaughterhouse of
                        Szeged)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Verkehrspolitische Wert der in Deutschland,
                           Österreich and Ungarn Geplanten </title>(Transportation Fares in Germany,
                        Austria and Hungary)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Wasserstrassen</title>(Waterways), Mérnök és Épitesz
                        Egylet (Engineer and Architect Society)</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Building of Mudling Hotel in Vienna</item>
                     <item>Canal of Salzschlirf</item>
                     <item>Canalization and Water Supply in Epstein</item>
                     <item>Canalization and Water Supply of Kassa and Brasso</item>
                     <item>Canalization of Eberwald</item>
                     <item>Canalization of Königshütte</item>
                     <item>City Building of Temesvár, Nyiregyháza, Szabadka, Gyongyos, and
                        Miskolc</item>
                     <item>City Building Plans for Nyiregyháza</item>
                     <item>Plans and Building of Water Refinement Plant in Budapest</item>
                     <item>Plans and Building of Water Refinement Plant in Nagyszeben</item>
                     <item>Water Supply for Griesheim</item>
                     <item>Water Supply in Nyitra</item>
                     <item>Water Supply of Mainz, Epstein, Hofheim, Hatterheim, and Kriftel</item>
                     <item>Water Supply of Pecs and Kecskemét</item>
                     <item>Water Supply of Wilhelmhafen</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 3: <unitdate>October 26, 1904-April 19, 1908</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The journal’s writer uses the name, “Forbát Imre Dr.” He opens a private
                     engineering office in Budapest. He is not part of the Budapest elite yet, and
                     still has to make a great effort to attract clients. He begins to learn English
                     and travels to Manchester. He also travels to Berlin, Magdeburg, Frankfurt, and
                     Constantinople. He earns his doctorate and becomes a lecturer at the Technical
                     University in Budapest. Imre Forbáth takes his first steps in the field of
                     communal politics. He is a member of the 48 Party, which supports the ideals of
                     the 1848 Revolution, and takes part in national elections. He is a convinced
                     liberal, excited about the political changes in France, especially the
                     separation of church and state. He distances himself from Judaism, valuing it
                     as a culture rather than a religion. He becomes one of Budapest’s leading
                     figures in the fields of public works and city planning. He is a member of the
                     Engineers’ Society. People want him to play a larger role in the city’s
                     leadership, but he refuses. He is asked to appraise gas prices for Budapest.
                     Banki paints his portrait. He wins second place at an international competition
                     in Varna. He comes in first in the Ruscsuk canalization and water supply
                     competition. He writes about the August 29, 1905 solar eclipse.</p>

                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Places Mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Berlin</item>
                     <item>Constantinople</item>
                     <item>Frankfurt</item>
                     <item>Magdeburg</item>
                     <item>Manchester</item>
                     <item>Varna</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Andrassy</item>
                     <item>Apponyi, Count</item>
                     <item>Barabas, Bela</item>
                     <item>Bartok, Bela</item>
                     <item>Becker</item>
                     <item>Cigler (professor)</item>
                     <item>Circle, Erzsébet</item>
                     <item>Circle, Lipot</item>
                     <item>Devecis</item>
                     <item>Fedak, Sari</item>
                     <item>Hatvany, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Heltai, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Hollo, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Kajlinger</item>
                     <item>Kovacs (professor)</item>
                     <item>Leon</item>
                     <item>Manger, Armin</item>
                     <item>Markus, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Szalay, Lajos (Mayor)</item>
                     <item>Szekely, Bertalan</item>
                     <item>Szilagyi, Dezso</item>
                     <item>Tatrai, Lajos (student)</item>
                     <item>Tisza, István</item>
                     <item>Tolnai, Lajos</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A lakaskerdes és Budapest jovoje </title>(Question of
                        Housing and the Future of Budapest); Budapest, 1906</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A vízmuvek rentabilitásáról </title>(About the Profit
                        of the Water Supplies)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Amerikanische Abwasser Reimsgsanhenge
                        </title>(American Water Connections)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Bebauung der Aussengesartiere</title>Budapests
                        (Building of Budapest’s Suburbs)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Berechnung von Städten </title>(Calculation of the
                        Cities)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Budapest jovoje </title>(Future of Budapest)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Haupstädtische Bau</title>(Building of the
                        Capital)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kanalisation der Stadt Nagyszeben
                        </title>(Canalization of Nagyszeben)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kleinwohnungsfürsorge in Glasgow </title>(Low-Income
                        Housing in Glasgow), Gesundheit</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kleinwohnungsfürsorge in Sheffield
                        </title>(Low-Income Housing in Sheffield), Gesundheit</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kleinwohnunksfürsorge in Englischen Städten
                        </title>(Low-Income Housing in the Cities of England), Leipzig, 1906</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Lage der Ingenieure in Ungarn </title>(Position of
                        the Engineer in Hungary)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Muszaki teendoink városaink fejlesztese korul
                        </title>(Technical Works about the Development of Our Cities); Vallalkozok
                        Közlönye</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Ontozes Városi szennyvízekkel </title>(Watering with
                        City Sewage); Budapest, 1905</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Parlament und Freiheitsplatz Viertel in Budapest
                        </title>(Parliament and the Freedom Square Buildings in Budapest)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Ruscsuk víz és csatornázási tervei </title>(Plans of
                        the Water Supply and Canals of Ruscsuk)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városaink Muszaki Ugyei </title>(Our Cities’
                        Engineering Problems)</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Public presentations made:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Kozigazgatasi birosag reformjai </title>(Judicial
                        Reforms of the Administration), Országos Igazsagugyi Muszaki Tanacs
                        (National Technical Rights Committee)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Muszaki Kamara és a Koztisztsegviselok
                        </title>(Technical Chamber and the Administration)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A városok csatornázásarol </title>(On the
                        Canalization of the Cities), Budapesti Muegyetem (Technical University of
                        Budapest)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Artezi furdok beepitendo hullammedence dolgaban
                        </title>(About Wave-Pools in Thermal Baths), Városháza (City Hall)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Csatornázásrol és szennyvíz tisztitasrol
                        </title>(Canalization and Sewage Cleaning); Az Osztrak-Magyar Gaz-és
                        Víztechnikusok Kongresszusa (Congress of Gas and Hydraulic Technicians of
                        Austria-Hungary)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kozepes nagysagu városok rendzeserol
                        </title>(Planning Middle-Sized Cities), Budapesti Muegyetem (Technical
                        University of Budapest)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Ujabb torekvesek a városepites teren, celzassal a
                           Budapesti szabalyozasra</title>(New Plans in City Building: Regulation of
                        Budapest); Mérnök Egylet (Engineer’s Society)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Vagohid és Városterv </title>(Slaughterhouse and City
                        Planning), Varoshaza (City Hall)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városrendezes kozegeszsegugyi szempontbol
                        </title>szempontbol (City Organizing, Focusing on Civil Health
                        Issues)</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Appraisal of the Stone Mine of Sator</item>
                     <item>Canal of Varna</item>
                     <item>Canalization of Nagydisznod and the Starch Factory of Csikosgornok</item>
                     <item>Dam of Jozsefváros</item>
                     <item>Drilling on the Danube for the Water Supply of Goldberg Factory</item>
                     <item>Incinerator at Miskolc</item>
                     <item>Incinerator in Bucharest</item>
                     <item>Plant -Oil Factory of Pest</item>
                     <item>Sewage for Hatvany Sugar Factory</item>
                     <item>Sewage of Jaszbereny and Hatvan</item>
                     <item>Spring of Csillaghegy</item>
                     <item>Water Refinement Plant of Nagyszeben</item>
                     <item>Water Sink of Vienna</item>
                     <item>Water Supply of Zombori</item>
                     <item>Water Supply, Sewer System, and Slaughterhouse of Vojvodina
                        (Ujvidek)</item>
                     <item>Water Works of Bratislava</item>
                     <item>Water Works of Brussa, Nagyberek, Pancsova, Zagrab</item>
                     <item>Water Works of Marko Street; Pest</item>
                     <item>Watering of Vojvodina and Ruscsuk (Resicabánya)</item>
                     <item> Works in Nagyenyed, Segesvár, and Brasso</item>
                     <item>Works in Székesfehérvár, Tatabánya, Siofok, Szatmar, Felegyháza,
                        Hodmezovásárhely, and Hatvan</item>
                     <item> Works on the Slaughterhouse of Altesse</item>


                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 4: <unitdate>April 22, 1908-July 25, 1911</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The author of the journals uses the name, “Imre Forbáth Dr.” He is a lecturer
                     at the new Technical University and is elected to its governing body. He takes
                     part in parliamentary election campaigns. People in many constituencies ask him
                     to run for office, but he refuses. He wants to be financially secure first. He
                     travels to France, Italy, Bulgaria, and Germany. He is the Hungarian
                     representative at the International Exhibition on City Planning held in Berlin.
                     He is one of the Hungarian delegates sent to the jubilee celebration in Rome.
                     He travels to the World’s Fair in Brussels and visits Antwerp to take part in a
                     city planning competition. Forbáth and Vargha submit plans for Antwerp, which
                     take third place. Imre Forbáth’s lifestyle has changed; he is now part of the
                     Hungarian elite, moving in circles beyond those of his family and
                     profession.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Places mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Berlin</item>
                     <item>Brussels</item>
                     <item>Bulgaria</item>
                     <item>France</item>
                     <item>Germany</item>
                     <item>Rome</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Aigner, Rudolf</item>
                     <item>Arnstein, Henrik</item>
                     <item>Barczy (Mayor)</item>
                     <item>Bartha, Kalman</item>
                     <item>Batthyany, Tivadar</item>
                     <item>Beck, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Berbnady, György</item>
                     <item>Bitto</item>
                     <item>Bohm, Imre</item>
                     <item>Brauserwetter</item>
                     <item>Buzath</item>
                     <item>Cazar</item>
                     <item>Czipfer</item>
                     <item>Darvai</item>
                     <item>Domique</item>
                     <item>Fenyvessy, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Ferenczi, Imre </item>
                     <item>Furst, Laszlo </item>
                     <item>Grunwald, Mor</item>
                     <item>Grunwald, Vilmos </item>
                     <item>Gyarmaty, Viktor </item>
                     <item>Harrer</item>
                     <item>Hatvany, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Hederváry, Lehel </item>
                     <item>Hegedus, Lorant</item>
                     <item>Heltay, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Hollo, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Huszar (private professor)</item>
                     <item>Kajlinger</item>
                     <item>Koppany, Geza </item>
                     <item>Kun, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Lechner</item>
                     <item>Lueger</item>
                     <item>Mandells</item>
                     <item>Merse, Pal</item>
                     <item>Michailich</item>
                     <item>Monillard</item>
                     <item>Nemes, Marcell</item>
                     <item>Nyary</item>
                     <item>Parloff (Mayor)</item>
                     <item>Reich</item>
                     <item>Ripke, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Rock, István</item>
                     <item>Romsanek (private professors)</item>
                     <item>Rozsa, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Sandor, Pal</item>
                     <item>Szabo, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Szilagyi, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Tory</item>
                     <item>Ugron, Gabor</item>
                     <item>Unger, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Vazsonyi, Vilmos</item>
                     <item>Weiss, Albert</item>
                     <item>Weiss, Manfred</item>
                     <item>Werner, Hegeman (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Zala, György</item>
                     <item>Zemplen</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A berlini Városepitesi kiallitasrol</title> (On the
                        City Building Exhibition in Berlin), Városok Lapja and Magyarország</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Brassoi gat</title> (Dam of Brasso), Ges.
                        Ing.</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A fovaros muszaki adminisztraciojanak
                           ujjaszervezeserol</title> (On the Reorganization of the Technical
                        Administration of the Capital), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A kissarmasi foldgaz Budapesten</title> (Natural Gas
                        of Kissarmás in Budapest), Fuggetlen Budapest</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A liberalis angol koltsegvetesol</title> (Budget of
                        Liberal England), Magyarország</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Magyar-Dalmat vasutak vízellátásáról</title>
                        (Watering of the Magyar-Dalmat Railroads), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A soroksari Dunaag kikötőve valo
                        kiepiteserol</title>(Building a Port at Soroksár, Tributary of the Danube),
                        published in every daily news</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Ankauf der Stadtbahnen / A fovárosi vasut
                           megvetelerol</title> (Purchase of the City’s Trolleys), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Antwerpen</title> (In Antwerp), Strassebau,
                        Halle</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Barczay nagy 95 milliardos epitesi
                           programjarol</title> (95-Billion Korona Building Program of Mayor
                        Barczay), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Budapest forgalmarol</title> (On Budapest’s Traffic),
                        Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Eisfrage</title> (Question of Ice), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Gasfrage in Budapest / A Budapesti Gaz</title> (Gas
                        of Budapest), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Gedanken über die Brusseler Weltaustellung</title>
                        (Thoughts about the World’s Fair in Brussels), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Magyarország gazdasagi fejlodese</title> (Hungary’s
                        Economic Growth), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Mérnök és jogasz</title> (Engineer and Lawyer),
                        Városok Lapja</item>
                     <item>Székesfehérvar, Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Resicabánya vízellatasa</title> (Watering of
                        Resicabánya), Értesítő</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Public presentations made:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A foldalatti Budapestrol</title> (On the Budapest
                        Underground)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A fovárosi Kozuzemek bevaltasanak
                           folytatásáról</title> (On the Community Factories of the Capital)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A fovárosi villamostelepek bevaltásáról</title> (On
                        the Power Plant of the Capital), at Demokrata Kor (Democratic Circle)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A gazkerdesrol. Grof Festetich Geza a francia-osztrak
                           ajanlat ossszehasonlitasa</title> (On the Problem of Gas)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A lakaskerdes reformja (Housing Reform), at Magyar
                           Tarsadalomtudomanyi Egylet</title> (Hungarian Social Sciences
                        Committee)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A mérnöki hivatal reformjarol</title>(On the Reform
                        of the Engineering Administration)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Nagyszebeni csatornázásrol</title> (Canalization in
                        Nagyseben), Mérnökegylet</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A szekesfováros kozigazgatásáról hozott uj
                           szabalyrendletek</title> (New Regulations in the Capital), Közlöny</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Antwerpen (On Antwerp), at Mérnök Egylet</title>
                        (Engineer’s Committee)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Az Erzsébet Sugarut terveinek elokeszitese</title>
                        (Erzsébet Boulevard, With Dezso Jasz), at Kozmunkatanacs (Committee of
                        Community Works)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Batthyányi teri hid tervpalyazat</title> (Plan of the
                        Batthyányi Square Bridge), at Mérnök Egylet (Engineer’s Committee)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Goethes Stellung zu Gottheit und religion</title>
                        (Goethe’s Opinion on God and Religion), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kertvárosok</title> (Suburbs), Bratislava</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Modern városrendzes a nyugati országokban</title>
                        (Modern City Planning in the Western Countries, technical lectures)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Ruhen von Boston / Bosztoni Városi Parkok</title>
                        (City Parks of Boston), Lloyd </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Sugarut</title> (Parkway, with Dezso Jasz), at
                        Kozmunkatanacs Committee of Community Works</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városrendezesrol</title> (City Building), at Muszaki
                        egy eloadasok (Technical University lectures)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Vízjogi targyalas Tencsenyben</title> (Trial on Water
                        Rights in Tencsény)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Vízvezeték és csatornzas</title> (Water Supply and
                        Sewers), at Székesfehérvári Egylet (Committee of Székesfehérvár)</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Canalization of Deva</item>
                     <item>Expert for Larduzzi in Miskolc</item>
                     <item>Expert in Debrecen</item>
                     <item>Infrastructure of Marosvásárhely, Nagybecskerek (Nagybuskerse),
                        Beszterce, Resicza, Szatmar-nemeti, Nagyszeben, Brasso, Tatabánya, Viova
                        River</item>
                     <item>Infrastructure of Papa, Doman, Rimaszombat, Sziliacsfurdo</item>
                     <item>Plans of Anina and Doman, Szabadka, Székesfehérvár, Lake Sosto</item>
                     <item>Plans of Low-Income Housing in Kispest (For Sandor Wekerle)</item>
                     <item>Spring of Ersekujvár</item>
                     <item>Watering of Screw Factory, Starch Factory, and Goldberger Factory</item>
                     <item>Waterworks in Ujpest</item>

                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 5: <unitdate>July 26, 1911 - July 20, 1914</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Imre Forbáth is a professor at the Technical University. He works with four
                     other engineers: Nagy, Pikler, Indy, and Wagner. The last two are still
                     students. Technical innovations such as new pumping methods and Puech-Chaval
                     filters are introduced. Forbáth travels to Switzerland, Italy, and Dusseldorf,
                     Germany. He visits the Hygienic Exhibition in Dresden. While there, he attends
                     a performance of Isadora Duncan’s dancers. He buys a Mednyansky painting.
                     Forbáth takes out a 50,000-korona life insurance policy with the First
                     Insurance Company. In 1912, his first book, titled <title render="italic">Städtebauliche Studien,</title> is published in Leipzig. At this time, he
                     lives a very active social life. He is a member of the political circle of
                     Lipotvaros and a delegate of the Independent Democratic Party. He is also in
                     the leadership of the municipal Board of Works and is elected to the city
                     council. After István Barczy, he is the biggest vote getter in this municipal
                     election. He criticizes the Minister of Commerce for failing to submit the
                     applications of Hungarian engineers to the Bosnian railroad on the grounds that
                     there was a shortage of engineers in Hungary. He moves to a new house in
                     Budapest, 46 Nador Street. He is financially successful. Imre Forbáth ends the
                     year with a capital of 70,000 korona. He meets Olga Popper, whom he marries on
                     February 1, 1913. On February 2, Rabbi Samuel Kohn performs the religious
                     ceremony. On November 21, 1913, their first daughter, Eva, is born. Olga
                     Popper’s family owns the Latzka and Popper Company. Forbáth and his family move
                     to a new house, 3 Becsey Street. He visits the Picasso exhibition in Munich and
                     an architectural exhibition in Leipzig in 1913. He studies low-income housing
                     in Paris, Stuttgart, Vienna and London. He is invited to San Francisco for an
                     Engineers’ Congress, but will be unable to go because of the outbreak of the
                     First World War. <title render="italic">Lloyd’s</title> editor-in-chief forbids
                     him to write for the <title render="italic">Journal.</title> Mor Revay asks him
                     to write for the new Revai Lexicon. He wins first place for plan of Brasso.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Places mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Budapest</item>
                     <item>Dresden</item>
                     <item>Dusseldorf</item>
                     <item>Italy</item>
                     <item>Leipzig</item>
                     <item>London</item>
                     <item> Munich</item>
                     <item>Paris</item>
                     <item>Stuttgart</item>
                     <item>Switzerland</item>
                     <item>Vienna</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Beothy</item>
                     <item>Bezeredy, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Biro, Elek</item>
                     <item>Bodos (professor)</item>
                     <item>Bohm, Agoston</item>
                     <item>Copper</item>
                     <item>Dohnanyi, Tivadar</item>
                     <item>Duncan, Isadora</item>
                     <item>Fabian</item>
                     <item>Farago, Geza</item>
                     <item>Ferrol, F. (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Fock, Ede</item>
                     <item>Friedmann, Bernat</item>
                     <item>Fuchs, Jeno (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Giovanus</item>
                     <item>Godolloi, Lehel</item>
                     <item>Gorkij</item>
                     <item>Gospick, Alispan</item>
                     <item>Grossfield</item>
                     <item>Grunwald, Vilmos</item>
                     <item>Hainish, Michael (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Halasz, Frigyes</item>
                     <item>Harrer, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Hary, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Hausmann</item>
                     <item>Hegedus</item>
                     <item>Heltay, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Hevesi, Sandor</item>
                     <item>Hosdzpotszky</item>
                     <item>Ivanka, Imre</item>
                     <item>Justh, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Kaiser, Karoly</item>
                     <item>Karolyi, Mihaly</item>
                     <item>Kisfaludy-strobl, Zsigmond</item>
                     <item>Klein, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Kos, Karoly</item>
                     <item>Kovacs, Aladar J.</item>
                     <item>Latzko, Sandor </item>
                     <item>Lenke</item>
                     <item>Leonard (Mayor)</item>
                     <item>Lipot, Hermann</item>
                     <item>Loti, Pierre</item>
                     <item>Lowenstein, Arnold</item>
                     <item>Marc, Aurel</item>
                     <item>Mezey, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Mezossy, Desy</item>
                     <item>Miklos, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Pallenberg, Max</item>
                     <item>Rados</item>
                     <item>Ravasz, Oszkar</item>
                     <item>Reich, Odon</item>
                     <item>Rozsahegyi, Kalman</item>
                     <item>Rupcsics</item>
                     <item>Sandor, Pal</item>
                     <item>Schiller</item>
                     <item>Seneco</item>
                     <item>Serenyi, Gusztav</item>
                     <item>Shiffer</item>
                     <item>Szamosi</item>
                     <item>Szanto, Aladar</item>
                     <item>Szereny, Zoltan</item>
                     <item>Szigeti, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Szirmai, Imre</item>
                     <item>Tornai</item>
                     <item>Vigh, Janos</item>
                     <item>Virag, Geza</item>
                     <item>Weinberger, Miksa (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Zala, György</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of the period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Budapesti hatosagi lakasepitesekrol / Gesetzliche
                           Wohnungspflege</title> (On Government Housing in Budapest); in his book
                        published in Leipzig, Neue Freie Presse, Vienna, Journal</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Budapesti munkaskoloniarol</title> (On the Workers’
                        Community in Budapest); in his book published in Leipzig</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A kozmunka tanacsrol</title> (On the Committee of
                        Public Works), Fovárosi Hirlap</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A palyaudvarok rendezeserol</title> (On the Train
                        Stations), Budapesti Hirlap</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Soroksari Dunaag kikötőve valo kiepiteserol</title>
                        (On the Building of the Port of Soroksár on the Danube), Lloyd, Vilag,
                        Budapesti Hirnap</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Antwerpen</title> (On Antwerp), Strasse, Halle</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Az Adria palota Erzsébet teri arkadjairol</title> (On
                        the Arch of Adriapalota of Erzsébet Square), Egyetertes</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Az Erzsébet sugarut és a kozponti városháza</title>
                        (The Erzsébet Boulevard and the Central City Hall), Fuggetlen
                        Budapest</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Az Erzsébet sugarut terve</title> (The Plan of
                        Erzsébet Boulevard), Harrer</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Az Osztrak-Olasz hatarszelrol</title> (On the
                        Austro-Italian Border), Magyarország</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Az Újvidéki csatornázás </title> (Canalization of
                        Újvidék), Gesundheit</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Gross-Berlin</title> (Greater Berlin), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Haupstadt in 1911</title> (The Capital in
                        19110)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Resicabánya vízellatasa</title> (Watering of
                        Resicabánya), Értesítő</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Schriften zur Forderung eines bessere Stadtebaues und
                           der Kleinwohnungsfürsorge in Städten</title> (Writings for Better City
                        Planning and for Low-Income Housing), Leipzig</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Stadtabauliche Studien</title> (Studies in City
                        Planning)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Székesfehérvár Asszonyvolgy</title> (Székesfehérvár
                        Asszony Valley), Lloyd</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Public presentations of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A folyami kikötők</title> (Riverports),
                        Committee</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A gyari furdok berendezeserol</title> (On the
                        Equipment of the Baths in the Factories), Nepfurdo Egylet</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Soroksari Dunaag kikötőve valo tetelerol</title>
                        (On the Building of the Port of Soroksár on the Danube)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A városepites kozegeszsegugyi vonatkozasai</title>
                        (Relationship of Common Health to City Building), Kozegeszsegugyi
                        Szaktanacs</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Antwerpen</title> (On Antwerp), Mérnökegylet</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kereskedelmi Kikötők</title> (Commercial Ports),
                        Kereskedelmi csarnok (Commercial Hall)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Kispesti allami munkastelep</title> (Workers’
                        Community in Kispest)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Segesvár csatornázása</title> (The Canalization of
                        Segesvár), Városháza</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">The Question of Smog</title> (Fustkerdes); National
                        Public Health Committee (Országos kozegeszsegugyi tanacs)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városrendezesrol</title> (On City Organization),
                        Muszaki egyetem (Technical University)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Vízvezeték és csatornázás</title> (Canalization and
                        Water Supplying), Székesfehérvári Egylet </item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Expert in Kecskemét on Trauzl-Lefeber</item>
                     <item>Expert in Nyitra, Gulin, Paskin, Vahovina</item>
                     <item>Expert on Erzsébetfalva’s Water Supply</item>
                     <item>Expert on Margit Island Beach</item>
                     <item>Expert on Segesvár’s Sewers</item>
                     <item>Expert on Spring Well of Margit Island</item>
                     <item>Extension of the Water Works of Marossvásárhely</item>
                     <item>Goldberg Factory’s watering</item>
                     <item>Magyar-Dalmát Railroad’s Water Supply</item>
                     <item>Plans of Nagybecskerek’s Draining</item>
                     <item>Plans of Ujvidek [With Nagy and Pikler engineers]</item>
                     <item>Power Plant of Nyitra</item>
                     <item>Pumping Sewers of Székesfehérvár</item>
                     <item>Székesfehérvár, Resica, Marodvásárhely, Albertfalva, Segesvár</item>
                     <item>Trial on Water Rights of the Soroksar Avenue Distillation Plant</item>
                     <item>Trials on Water Rights in Pluski on Drelulje and Jeszenka</item>
                     <item>Water Refinement Plant in Nagyszeben</item>
                     <item>Watering of Szabadka</item>
                     <item>Workers’ Quarters of Kispest</item>
                     <item>Works on Pécel Sewers</item>

                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 6: <unitdate>July 21, 1914 - December 26, 1914</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Imre Forbáth and his wife are in England when the newspapers bring word of the
                     outbreak of war, then of the introduction of conscription. They see crowds of
                     people in front of banks trying to withdraw their savings. Urged by friends and
                     family, they leave for home, stopping in Brussels and Hassel. Germany is on the
                     eve of military mobilization. The railroads in Bavaria are protected by armed
                     civilians. Masses of draftees flood trains and stations. Imre Forbáth is called
                     up to serve as an engineer with the Seventh Division of the Thirtieth Infantry
                     Regiment. He has to report for duty in seven days. The Seventh Division
                     consists of 1,500 laborers divided into six parts, with an officer and an
                     engineer at the head of each. Wherever the troops go, the people welcome them
                     with flowers. The Seventh Division is taken to Przemysl. According to the
                     diary, Polish Jews and Ruthenes are sent there as well. In September 1914,
                     Árpád Tamássy takes command of the fort. The workers build barbed wire fences,
                     trenches, and roads. Most of the civilian population leaves. The Russians
                     attack the city, finally surrounding it at the end of September. Both sides
                     suffer many casualties. The besieged troops have to come up with new ideas to
                     supplement their diminishing supplies; they make matches and tie wooden soles
                     to their shoes. On October 12, Austro-Hungarian troops relieve the siege of
                     Przemysl and retake the height of Paportenka. On Christmas day, a mass is held
                     for the troops on the frontline. In this diary, Imre Forbáth reports on the
                     August 23, 1914 solar eclipse.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Places mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Brussels</item>
                     <item>Hassel</item>
                     <item>Przemysl</item>


                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Barabas, Bela</item>
                     <item>Czako, Pal</item>
                     <item>Deer, Erna;</item>
                     <item>Fischer, (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Fodor, Gabor</item>
                     <item>Kear (Captain)</item>
                     <item>Krause, Tivadar</item>
                     <item>Makrai (Engineer)</item>
                     <item>Nonay, Dezso</item>
                     <item>Richnowsky (Captain)</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 7 (Parts 1 and 2): <unitdate>December 1, 1914 - March 22,
                        1915,</unitdate>
                     <unitdate>September 5, 1915 - October 20, 1915.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The Russians had surrounded the fort of Przemysl again on November 8, 1914.
                     Between Christmas and New Year, the fighting stops. The besieged troops are
                     completely worn out and food is scarce. The laborers are armed with Wernil
                     weapons and turned into soldiers. Weapons and ammunition are scarce. The army
                     has to take care of the civilian population, including refugees.</p>
                  <p>In the diary of Imre Forbáth, we get precise data on the number of laborers and
                     soldiers, their pay, their food supplies, and what they do. According to his
                     data, 25,000 Hungarian laborers are at the fort. Half of Forbáth’s division of
                     298 men build a road at Pod Masurani while the other half works at Makara
                     Garai. The soldiers’ pay is 16 fillér per day. The civilians are overpayed for
                     their work. There are 9,200 sick. Due to the harsh winter weather and the lack
                     of food, the men become ill at work. Many freeze to death. At the end of 1914,
                     Archduke Karl, heir to the throne, visits the front. He refuses to allow the
                     surrender of the fort. An order forbids keeping records in writing as of
                     January 7, 1915. The Austro-Hungarian troops sent to relieve Przemysl attack on
                     January 23, 1915. They are defeated on March 20. Meanwhile, Na Gorach has
                     fallen. The fort at Przemysl has been surrounded for four months and all the
                     food has been used up. The fort is famously impregnable to military attack, so
                     the men are willing to endure to the limit of their resources. The smallest
                     portions are served. The horses are slaughtered, so there is meat, but nothing
                     else; all other food, including bread and salt, is gone. On March 22, the
                     Austro-Hungarians decide to surrender the fort. They blow up their cannons,
                     weapons, and vehicles and await the fort’s new rulers. Forbáth’s entries stop
                     here, but we know that the soldiers surrender and are sent to Siberia as
                     prisoners of war. The Hungarian soldiers endured so much because they knew that
                     the fort at Przemysl was the gateway to Hungary for the invading Russians.
                     Their heroism became legendary.</p>
                  <p>The second half of this diary, September 5, 1915 to October 20, 1915, is
                     written in German and in stenography. Forbáth writes on top of his earlier
                     entries, reversed, and starting from the back.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Asimus</item>
                     <item>Bednar</item>

                     <item>Colonel</item>

                     <item>Czapka</item>

                     <item>Daver</item>

                     <item>Epstein</item>

                     <item>Ferenczy</item>

                     <item>Fernchich</item>

                     <item>Fieber</item>

                     <item>Fliger (Captain)</item>

                     <item>Habermann</item>

                     <item>Hashinger</item>

                     <item>Herbst</item>

                     <item>Jausz</item>

                     <item>Kisiliewski</item>

                     <item>Krause</item>

                     <item>Kreische</item>

                     <item>Kusmarek, Herman</item>

                     <item>Lonal</item>

                     <item>Ludwig</item>

                     <item>Makrai</item>

                     <item>Mansfeld</item>

                     <item>Milzer, Pista</item>
                     <item> Nagy</item>

                     <item>Nendtvich</item>
                     <item> Nyiri, Ferenc</item>
                     <item> Ordogh, Antal</item>
                     <item> Országh</item>
                     <item> Pechanek</item>

                     <item>Prokopy</item>

                     <item>Richnowsky (Captain)</item>

                     <item>Schafer</item>

                     <item>Schaumberger</item>

                     <item>Scherer</item>
                     <item>Schwalb</item>
                     <item>Schwartz</item>
                     <item>Seidel</item>
                     <item>Srocziszki</item>
                     <item>Tamássy</item>
                     <item>Tapay</item>
                     <item>Theodorovics</item>
                     <item>Vásárhelyi</item>
                     <item>Vegh, Guido</item>
                     <item>Vidas</item>
                     <item>Werkfehrnelf</item>
                     <item>Wodraschka</item>


                  </list>

               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1 </container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 8: <unitdate>April 13, 1916 - August 12, 1916</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Description: The diary is written in German stenography and is not
                     deciphered</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 9: <unitdate>June 3, 1919 - July 24, 1920</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>No journals survive from the three preceding years. We can reconstruct the
                     events of this period from recollections spread throughout Forbáth’s later
                     journals. The prisoners of war from Przemysl were first taken to Tobol'sk in
                     Siberia, then to the city of Petropavlovsk. Forbáth escapes (according to the
                     March 6, 1920 journal entry). His friend, Beck, escapes in the same way. Eight
                     months after the Bolshevik Revolution, Forbáth is still living in Moscow. The
                     story of his captivity is written in German stenography in journal 8. He
                     translates it into Hungarian, adds the story of his escape, binds it together
                     with a Bible and photographs, and presents it to his son, Tamás, as a gift in
                     1928. He writes it out again in 1936 with the title “Diary of a prisoner of
                     war,” hoping to publish it in England with the help of Samuel Hoare. Hoare has
                     to deal with an unexpected political development, preventing him from meeting
                     Forbáth.</p>
                  <p>In this journal, Forbáth reports that his fellow prisoners Epstein and Tivadar
                     Krause are still in Russia. He discovers that a box of his writings was left in
                     a house at Upranskaja Ulica 64 in Petropavlovsk by A. G. Benzion, under the
                     name F. Dezso.</p>
                  <p>Imre Forbáth arrives back in Hungary from captivity just as war veterans are
                     being called back to service. Forbáth is asked to perform office work. He feels
                     no sense of belonging to either of the two sides, right or left. He draws up a
                     plan to change the peace treaty in Hungary’s favor, with regards to the Danube
                     as a natural boundary.</p>
                  <p>The Fifth District Military Soviet wants Forbáth’s engineering office. They put
                     strangers into every room of the family’s apartment. He has no work. Due to the
                     administrative chaos, nobody pays for his previous work. He is still a member
                     of the Community Work Committee, but he stops attending meetings during the
                     Soviet period.</p>
                  <p>On November 2, 1919, Forbáth’s second daughter, Zsuzsi, is born.</p>
                  <p>On July 14, 1920, the Siberian prisoners of war return to Hungary; many
                     thousands of people await them at the Eastern Train Station. <title render="italic">Világ</title> magazine interviews Imre Forbáth about the
                     port of Csepel. In Közlöny, Forbáth’s very sick younger brother publishes an
                     article “On responsibility for the money distributed during the Soviet
                     republic.” Forbáth’s family has to turn to the American Relief Administration
                     for help buying food. A family member who owns a textile factory in Kispest
                     takes him on as a director. </p>
                  <p>The journal has many references to “secret armed forces that attack Jews.” The
                     attackers force Jews to take an oath to leave their house, city, and country,
                     and never come back.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Places mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Moscow</item>
                     <item>Tobol'sk</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Barczy</item>
                     <item>Bartok</item>
                     <item>Beck, Jozsi</item>
                     <item>Becsey</item>
                     <item>Benko (comrade)</item>
                     <item>Bogdanffy</item>
                     <item>Buday</item>
                     <item>Clark, George </item>
                     <item>Csastkoczy</item>
                     <item>Cseley, István</item>
                     <item>Dienes</item>
                     <item>Dubszky</item>
                     <item>Epstein</item>
                     <item>Farkas, Kalman </item>
                     <item>Feherváry</item>
                     <item>Ferbert</item>
                     <item>Fleishman, Laszlo (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Garami</item>
                     <item>Haubrich</item>
                     <item>Herz</item>
                     <item>Országh, Imre</item>
                     <item>Joo, István</item>
                     <item>Szoke, Joska</item>
                     <item>Jozsef Hirling;</item>
                     <item>Karman, Todor</item>
                     <item>Keller, Andor</item>
                     <item>Kery</item>
                     <item>Kramjansky</item>
                     <item>Krassay, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Krause</item>
                     <item>Laki, Imre</item>
                     <item>Lovaszy</item>
                     <item>Makay (comrade)</item>
                     <item>Markus, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Mihelfy</item>
                     <item>Payer</item>
                     <item>Potok, Armin</item>
                     <item>Reinitz</item>
                     <item>Revesz</item>
                     <item>Schrerer</item>
                     <item>Seifeld, Sandor</item>
                     <item>Sugar, Vilmos</item>
                     <item>Szilas</item>
                     <item>Tapay</item>
                     <item>Vago</item>
                     <item>Varga</item>
                     <item>Vásárhelyi, Dezso</item>
                     <item>Vazsonyi, György Lukács</item>
                     <item>Vazsonyi, István Szabo</item>
                     <item>Zarka</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Duna- kerdes és a Bekekotes </title>(Danube
                        Question and the Peace Agreement)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Proletar Diktatura Tortenete</title>(History of the
                        Hungarian Soviet Republic)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Budapest szabadkikötő</title> (Budapest Free Port),
                        Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Frage des Freihafen für Budapest</title> (Question of
                        Freeports for Budapest)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Hadifoglyok házahozatala</title> (Bringing home the
                        War- Prisoners), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Munkaskerdesrol, Kozmunkak</title> (On the Question
                        of Work, Community Labors), Magyarország</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Szabadkikötők</title> (Free Ports), Encyclopedia
                        Britannica</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Zamard</title> (Zamard), Stadtebau</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Canalization Plans of Esztergom</item>
                     <item>Expert in the canalization of Nagyteteny</item>
                     <item>Expert in the canalization of Duna-Tisza</item>

                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 10: <unitdate>July 25, 1920 - May 7, 1922</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Forbáth still writes about atrocities committed against the Jews. The Soviet
                     republic’s leaders are executed. Jenő Lipocz becomes prime minister. Vilmos
                     Hilbert recommends a census of the Jewish population. The Christian national
                     parties come to power, led by Ottokár Prohászka. </p>
                  <p>Forbáth does not want to take part in political life ever again. Unable to get
                     work, he has to sell off his shares. His private practice has been closed for
                     seven years. In the Gresham coffee house, the Saturday Engineering Community
                     meets regularly. </p>
                  <p>The Foresta Corporation hires Forbáth to work in its operations cutting down
                     forests in Romania. Later, the Nitrogen Company in Diciosanmartin asks him to
                     take over its factory and save it from liquidation. In March 1921, the bankrupt
                     factory’s chief director, Károly Koch, resigns. Forbáth takes his position. The
                     next 17 years of his life are spent saving and consolidating the factory,
                     raising it to the international level. Originally within the borders of the
                     Austro-Hungarian monarchy, the factory had a contract with the monarchy’s
                     Ministry of War. Following the Treaty of Trianon, Diciosanmartin has become
                     part of Romania, and the Romanian Ministry of War wants to take over the
                     factory. It is far larger than any similar operation in Romania, and the
                     Romanians are convinced that the Hungarian government must be in control behind
                     the scenes. Imre Forbáth, a citizen of Hungary, has to find a way to run a
                     factory in Romania. He has to defend himself against the Romanian government,
                     which targets him from the beginning. The case between the Nitrogen Company and
                     the Romanian Ministry of War drags on for years.</p>
                  <p>Imre Forbáth does business with Baron Willman and Dr. Freud (Austrian Minister
                     of National Affairs), selling them nitrogen. He travels to Dresden, Berlin,
                     Cologne, Frankfurt, Rotterdam, London, Belgrade, Sofia, Paris, Nagyszeben,
                     Fogaras, Brasso, and Prague. Soderberg electrodes are used in the Nitrogen
                     Factory.</p>
                  <p>In September 1921, he has a reunion with his fellow ex-prisoners of war in the
                     Bristol Restaurant.</p>
                  <p>Edgar Milhaud, founder of <title render="italic">Les Annales de la Régie
                        Directe,</title> sends Forbáth a letter from Geneva, asking him to be the
                     Hungarian correspondent for the paper. Forbáth declines, giving the opportunity
                     to one of his friends.</p>
                  <p>The Regulation Plans of the Danube at Belgrade won second place.</p>
                  <p>On November 25, 1921, his son, Tamás Forbáth is born.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Places mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Belgrade</item>
                     <item>Berlin</item>
                     <item>Brasso</item>
                     <item>Cologne</item>
                     <item>Dresden</item>
                     <item>Fogaras</item>
                     <item>Frankfurt</item>
                     <item>London</item>
                     <item>Nagyszeben</item>
                     <item>Paris</item>
                     <item>Prague</item>
                     <item>Romania</item>
                     <item>Rotterdam</item>
                     <item>Sofia</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Agoston, Bekenyi</item>
                     <item>Baffe</item>
                     <item>Balogh (Engineer)</item>
                     <item>Dachler</item>
                     <item>Deutsch, Dezso</item>
                     <item>Enescu</item>
                     <item>Gyarmaty, Victor</item>
                     <item>Harver</item>
                     <item>Haubrich</item>
                     <item>Hollosi</item>
                     <item>Katona Rubovits , Mark</item>
                     <item> Koch, Karoly</item>
                     <item>Kommesman (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Kornfeld, Pal</item>
                     <item>Kovacs, Geza</item>
                     <item>Kramer, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Kriesch, Al.</item>
                     <item>Mikes, Camilla</item>
                     <item>Orban, Ignac</item>
                     <item>Rez, Richard</item>
                     <item>Sandor, Janos</item>
                     <item>Shabatiel</item>
                     <item>Skin, Emil</item>
                     <item>Stahelin (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Starcea</item>
                     <item>Tacken (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Tornyai-Schopburger</item>
                     <item>Vadasz, Sandor</item>
                     <item>Vajda, Zs.</item>
                     <item>Vantus</item>
                     <item>Ziry</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Nagylaki hatarkerdes</title> (Question of the
                        Nagylak Border; Note to the Consulate)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Zamardi furdotelep szabalyozasa</title> (Regulation
                        of the Baths of Zamardi), Städtebau</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Belgrad szabalyozasi terve</title> (Plans on the
                        Regulation of Belgrade)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Budapesti kikötők</title> (Ports of Budapest), Le
                        Danube International</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Städtebau: Antant 1</title> (City Building: Entente,
                        1), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Städtebau nach dem Kriege 2</title> (City Building
                        after the War, 2), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Újvidéki víz és csatorna</title> (Water Supply and
                        Canalization of Újvidék), Gesundheit Ingenieur</item>


                  </list>
                  <list><head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Expert on Wagner Factory</item>
                     <item>Expert on the Canalization of Nagyteteny</item>
                     <item>Reconstruction of the Waterworks of the Danube at Szentendre</item>
                     <item>Water Power Plant on the Danube at Moson</item>

                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 11: <unitdate>July 10, 1922 - November 4, 1924</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p> In 1922, the board of directors of the Nitrogen Factory of Diciosanmartin
                     resigns. The new board consists of Baron Paul Kornfeld and Kovács from Pest;
                     Stein and Buchler on behalf of the Commerce Bank in Budapest; Goldfinger and
                     Forbáth on behalf of the factory; two Dutchmen; four Romanians (one of them Dr.
                     Joseph Boila); and one German (Alfred Herzfeld). The same year, they start a
                     new chlorine factory and later, an ammonium sulfate factory. </p>
                  <p>Outlets for the sale of the company’s carbamids are found in London, Hagen,
                     Amsterdam, Rotterdam, Hamburg, Berlin, Cologne, Brussels, Bucharest, and
                     Budapest.</p>
                  <p>Imre Forbáth’s partners are: Acetylea, Vienna; Nitrogen Fertilizer Company,
                     Belgium; Bayer Stickstoffwerke, Berlin; Thorn &amp; Hadick Company, London;
                     Bohm &amp; Company, Berlin; Hirsh Kupfer and Metall AG, Berlin; Camindo,
                     Berlin; Krauss Pachmann AG, Cologne; Kochler, Leipzig; Williem H. Miler, Hagen;
                     Hamer &amp; Les Pelzenburg, Amsterdam, Brussels; Klaber, Budapest; Hungaria
                     Műtrágyagyár, Budapest.</p>
                  <p>A trial takes place concerning the Nitrogen Factory’s fertilizer. A Belgian
                     company claims that Forbáth’s company cannot sell cyanide because it does not
                     have a patent for it. In fact, Forbáth has purchased rights from the patent’s
                     owner, who lives in Cologne. He countersues the Belgian company.</p>
                  <p>To become independent of currency fluctuations, Forbáth makes a deal with the
                     Hungarian sugar industry that provides him with a steady supply of Dutch
                     guilders. He negotiates with banks for the best rates on loans. For banks, the
                     greatest risk factor is that the factory is in Romania. </p>
                  <p>In 1924, all the factory directors in Europe meet to found a Carbide Syndicate.
                     Dr. Wicklein performs an experiment, attempting to replace calcium chloride
                     with nitrogen chloride. The case between Romania and Forbáth is still going on.
                     The Romanian government wants a 200 million lei share and a 60-40 percent ratio
                     in its favor. Until they reach an agreement, every government benefit, such as
                     tax breaks, will be withheld. Forbáth has to prove that this request by the
                     Romanian government is unlawful and exaggerated, and that the Hungarian
                     government was never a shareholder of the Nitrogen Company. </p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Beck, Jozsi</item>
                     <item>Berger</item>
                     <item>Bohm, Thab (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Camindo</item>
                     <item>Constantinus, Tanced</item>
                     <item>Dounth (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Drailo</item>
                     <item>Egri</item>
                     <item>Ellinger</item>
                     <item>Frank (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Goldfinger</item>
                     <item>Hajdu, Arthur (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Hemelsnet</item>
                     <item>Hoddle</item>
                     <item>Hysgo</item>
                     <item>Jorda</item>
                     <item>Jovanovics</item>
                     <item>Kejlinger, Mihaly</item>
                     <item>Keller</item>
                     <item>Monoilescu</item>
                     <item>Pierson, Alard</item>
                     <item>Pierson, Allan</item>
                     <item>Reinitz</item>
                     <item>Rochmann, Pal.</item>
                     <item>Romanesca, Bea</item>
                     <item>Rosenberg (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Schwarz</item>
                     <item>Sezitovszky</item>
                     <item>Siebner (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Stefanescu</item>
                     <item>Stein</item>
                     <item>Stelian, Toma</item>
                     <item>Suter</item>
                     <item>Thoray</item>
                     <item>Thusling (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Tybergheim</item>
                     <item>Vajda</item>
                     <item>Waldeek (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Wasserman (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Wicklei (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Zacharia (Professor)</item>
                     <item>Zsiray, Miklos</item>

                  </list>

               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 12: <unitdate>November 7, 1924 to May 17, 1927</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>

               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The Nitrogen Company’s attempt to fight nationalization continues. Imre Forbáth
                     seeks loans and hopes to improve the credit rating of the company. He does
                     business with the Creditul Industrial of Bucharest. The Nitrogen Factory is
                     working at 50% capacity, which means that one wagon of carbide and four wagons
                     of nitrogen are produced daily. The Romanian Industrial Ministry agrees to the
                     contract that Forbáth made two years previously with Matos. In Diciosanmartin,
                     an International Chemical Congress is organized. </p>
                  <p>The Nitrogen Factory contacts the Zurich company Nitrum AG about building a
                     sodium nitride factory, which would use a common method in which aluminum and
                     ammonia are derived from ammonium nitride, and about the recycling of brown
                     coal and tar. Delegates from Hagen, Amsterdam, and Vienna push for a world
                     trade treaty on cyanide, which would keep American companies out of the
                     European market. This is unsuccessful because the Americans are already behind
                     the Bavarian company. The American Cyanide Company is a growing force in
                     Europe. </p>
                  <p>In 1925, the world’s leading companies come together in the courtroom of the
                     Bayerische Stickstoff Werke. They are already discussing the idea of
                     cooperating with the Americans. The Americans want to buy Forbáth’s Belgian
                     operation. </p>
                  <p>The Carbamide Syndicate in Vienna talks about the Egyptian market. The world’s
                     companies agree to establish the Fertilizer Sales Company, located in London.
                     In half a year, a world organization is formed, originally established to fight
                     the Americans, but in the end unable to do without American funds. The Cartel
                     opens a common sales office in Rotterdam. </p>
                  <p>Forbáth’s business is a success; the Nitrogen Factory has been consolidated,
                     and half of all the production for the next five years has been sold. In
                     addition to the Syndicate, the company makes Romanian, Hungarian, Czechoslovak,
                     Italian, and Greek sales. </p>
                  <p>Forbáth’s other great business success is the sale of the Szurdics brick
                     factory. He wants to start a new private engineering practice again, so he
                     applies to the Engineers’ Chamber. He is asked to take on the directorship of
                     the Hungarian Commerce Bank, but he turns it down. </p>
                  <p>He talks with O’Daniel and Strowell about an American loan and cooperation with
                     the New York cyanide factory. He is thinking about selling shares.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Adolf, Otto</item>
                     <item>Alpar, Ignac</item>
                     <item>Angello</item>
                     <item>August Weyl (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Averescu</item>
                     <item>Banki, Donath</item>
                     <item>Barnauer</item>
                     <item>Becsey</item>
                     <item>Beothy, Laszlo</item>
                     <item>Beregi, Bela</item>
                     <item>Bratianu</item>
                     <item>Buch</item>
                     <item>Buchler</item>
                     <item>Caro</item>
                     <item>Caso, Ratz</item>
                     <item>Chatel</item>
                     <item>Colener</item>
                     <item>Constantinidis, Peter</item>
                     <item>Cox</item>
                     <item>Csosz, Imre</item>
                     <item>Decsey, Toni</item>
                     <item>Dimitrescu</item>
                     <item>Doroki, Ervin</item>
                     <item>Endrody, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Frang (Professor)</item>
                     <item>Gisser, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Goldfinger</item>
                     <item>Grant, Thorn</item>
                     <item>Haining</item>
                     <item>Harkanyy</item>
                     <item>Hevesy, Rabbi</item>
                     <item>Hevesy, Sandor</item>
                     <item>Hopfgartner</item>
                     <item>Horvath, Lipot</item>
                     <item>Kefener</item>
                     <item>Kovacs, Geza</item>
                     <item>Kovacs, Sebestyen Aladar</item>
                     <item>Krapner</item>
                     <item>Kraszaer</item>
                     <item>Lansky</item>
                     <item>Lichermann (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Lorant</item>
                     <item>Malinoff</item>
                     <item>Mangold (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Nane</item>
                     <item>O’Daniel</item>
                     <item>Odon Stern (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Pasons</item>
                     <item>Patak</item>
                     <item>Popoch</item>
                     <item>Prasole</item>
                     <item>Preszlenyi, Aladar</item>
                     <item>Reiter</item>
                     <item>RicardoJualino</item>
                     <item>Roddling</item>
                     <item>Rosenbaum</item>
                     <item>Salusinszky, Ruttai</item>
                     <item>Sanor, Pal</item>
                     <item>Simko</item>
                     <item>Simonovits</item>
                     <item>Srazil</item>
                     <item>Stefanescu</item>
                     <item>Stein</item>
                     <item>Stem, Odon (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Strettler</item>
                     <item>Strowell</item>
                     <item>Tagore, Mahalanobil Rabindranat</item>
                     <item>Terrace</item>
                     <item>Thomanek</item>
                     <item>Thomond, Erno</item>
                     <item>Tolnay</item>
                     <item>Torok, Éva</item>
                     <item>Vajda, György (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Vajda-Vacood, Sandor</item>
                     <item>Vanyi, Dezso</item>
                     <item>Vida</item>
                     <item>Volentine</item>
                     <item>Weinstein, Lazari</item>
                     <item>Wolf, Ulman</item>
                     <item>Zielinszky, Szilard</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">Wohnungsbauten der Stadt Wien </title>(Building of
                        Apartments in Vienna), Lloyd</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Water Supply of the Goldberger Factory in Obuda</item>
                     <item>Canalization of Szeged</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 13: <unitdate>May 18, 1927 - February 29, 1929</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The international nitrogen market is in depression. The Bayerische
                     Stickstoffwerke and the Aluminium Company leave the Cartel. Imre Forbáth renews
                     the Nitrogen Factory’s contract with the Fertilizer Sale Company in Paris for
                     an additional ten years, with new conditions. The Nitrogen Factory itself will
                     no longer export, except to Hungary, Romania, and Czechoslovakia. In Trieste,
                     the Sulfide’s director wants to buy the new electrode method used in
                     Diciosanmartin. The factory’s engineer, Andor Leopold, asserts that the method
                     is his property, and licenses it in his own name. The factory signs a contract
                     with him. Ferdinand, King of Romania, dies. A series of changes occurs in the
                     Romanian government. Manoilescu is tried on charges of intriguing for Prince
                     Carol to become king, but is acquitted. The Romanian ministry demands money
                     from the Nitrogen Factory, but Forbáth proves, using old records, that the
                     previous Romanian government actually owed money to the Company. He collects
                     the money from the new Ministry of War. Two Dutch creditors take over the
                     Szurdics Factory. A new idea arises: licensing the Nitrogen Factory as a
                     Hungarian-Romanian joint company, with the Romanian half under the control of
                     the Ministry of War. In 1927, there are widespread strikes in Vienna to protest
                     the verdict in the Schattendorf trial. Forbáth is in Vienna at the time street
                     violence breaks out.</p>
                  <p>In 1928, Lajos Hatvany returns to Hungary from exile by his own choice. He is
                     put on trial for articles he wrote from 1920 to 1922, published in the Jövő in
                     Vienna. He receives seven years imprisonment, and a 50,000 pengő fine. </p>
                  <p>Imre Forbáth finds a <title render="italic">Mátyás Codex</title> miniature in a
                     library in Brussels. He writes a letter to Petropavlovsk, where his fellow
                     ex-prisoners of war left his papers. In 1928, he writes the story of his
                     Siberian captivity, and binds it with a few photographs and a Bible from
                     Siberia. He gives it to his son, Tamás, as a present.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Balog</item>
                     <item>Blytka</item>
                     <item>Bralianu</item>
                     <item>Constantinidis</item>
                     <item>Drachler</item>
                     <item>Egry, Aurel</item>
                     <item>Gaal, Mozes</item>
                     <item>Goldfinger</item>
                     <item>Greiner, Colos and Hugo</item>
                     <item>Horvath, Lipot</item>
                     <item>Jacoby, Andor (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Kornfeld (Count)</item>
                     <item>Kovacs, Geza</item>
                     <item>Kramer</item>
                     <item>Rohonyi</item>
                     <item>Simontsich</item>
                     <item>Stein ,Emil</item>
                     <item>Stern, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Szitovszky</item>
                     <item>Tilny</item>
                     <item>Torok, Emil</item>
                     <item>Vajda</item>
                     <item>Vida, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Weiss, Fulop</item>
                     <item>Wilchelm, Karoly (Dr.)</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item>"Diary of a Prisoner of War" (about the history of his Siberian captivity
                        and his escape)</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Goldberger Factory in Obuda</item>
                     <item>Wespag Textile Mill</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 14: <unitdate>February 15, 1929 - October 27, 1930</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>In the nationalization trial, the Nitrogen Company of Diciosanmartin stands
                     against the Romanian Ministry of Interior Affairs. The question in dispute is
                     whether there is a successor to the Austro-Hungarian Ministry of War. Forbáth
                     learns that the Austro-Hungarian Ministry of War still exists in Vienna as a
                     liquidation authority; therefore, there is no successor. The defense bases its
                     case on this fact. The trial takes much time and energy, but on the first
                     degree, the court decides in Forbáth’s favor. Manoilescu wants to get rid of
                     all the Hungarian owners. The concerned parties begin to discuss the
                     possibility of Romania buying out the Hungarians’ shares in the company.</p>
                  <p>The structure of the company, including its liaison with the Romanian
                     government, is so efficient that Imre Forbáth is able to direct affairs from
                     his office in Budapest. Forbáth continues to be the international
                     representative of the Nitrogen Factory. He goes to international Cartel and
                     Syndicate meetings in Munich, Berlin, Hamburg, Dortmund, Paris, Strasbourg,
                     Vienna, and Bucharest. The Nitrogen Pact of August 1930 is the biggest
                     industrial pact ever at the time</p>
                  <p>The Romanian and Russian gas industries are beginning to advance greatly.</p>
                  <p>Zeppelins land in Budapest. The International Building Conference and Fair, the
                     Nurnberg Fair, and the Poster Fair open in Budapest. A competition is announced
                     for the planning of Erzsébet Boulevard and for the statue of István Tisza. On
                     Saint Imre Day, the Ecclesiastical History Show opens. After the ceremony,
                     large numbers of people want to protest against unemployment, but the
                     government prohibits the demonstration by the time the workers arrive on the
                     streets. The Social-Democratic leadership demonstrates its power. </p>
                  <p>The Hungarian nitrogen market drops fifty percent due to the hardships of
                     Hungarian agriculture. The Nitrogen Factory hands over Hungarian sales to the
                     Szuperfoszfat Company, which is now under the direction of Krapner, also a
                     director of the Nitrogen Factory. There is a discussion with a Swiss group
                     about the possibility of selling the Nitrogen Factory.</p>
                  <p>Forbáth’s construction plans for Bratislava win an international prize. All the
                     newspapers write about Imre Forbáth winning his eighth international prize. Dr.
                     Antal Szego wants to publish the biographies of the three hundred most
                     important Hungarian Jews in the fiftieth edition of the magazine <title render="italic">Egyenloseg.</title> Imre Forbáth would be one of them.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Balla, Pal</item>
                     <item>Balog</item>
                     <item>Berczely</item>
                     <item>Bernhardt, Tibor</item>
                     <item>Berta</item>
                     <item>Bodnar</item>
                     <item>Boila</item>
                     <item>Bonis, Feri</item>
                     <item>Botka</item>
                     <item>Brunovszky, Pal</item>
                     <item>Christescu, Vitnile</item>
                     <item>Cox</item>
                     <item>Csaszkoczy</item>
                     <item>Dachler</item>
                     <item>Danken</item>
                     <item>Davidis</item>
                     <item>Delen</item>
                     <item>Deutsch, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Dierbauer, Vigil</item>
                     <item>Dindra</item>
                     <item>Dori, Otto</item>
                     <item>Dragominescu</item>
                     <item>Duzy</item>
                     <item>Ehrensperger</item>
                     <item>Elias</item>
                     <item>Farago</item>
                     <item>Farkas, Arpad</item>
                     <item>Fischer, Erno (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Fodor, Janos</item>
                     <item>Geszler</item>
                     <item>Glickstalv</item>
                     <item>Grueber</item>
                     <item>Grunwald</item>
                     <item>Gyoki (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Gyszi, Kadar</item>
                     <item>Harren</item>
                     <item>Heinau</item>
                     <item>Hopfgartner</item>
                     <item>Horvat, Lipot</item>
                     <item>Jabeg</item>
                     <item>Jasz, Dezso</item>
                     <item>Kafsner</item>
                     <item>Kanyy, Hugo</item>
                     <item>Kelemen, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Kornfeld, Pal</item>
                     <item>Korosi, Marietta</item>
                     <item>Kraffner</item>
                     <item>Krapner</item>
                     <item>Langfelder</item>
                     <item>Lecher</item>
                     <item>Leidenberger</item>
                     <item>Lenard, Robert</item>
                     <item>Lenki</item>
                     <item>Lunzer</item>
                     <item>Magyar, Misi</item>
                     <item>Manoilescu</item>
                     <item>Minnus, István</item>
                     <item>Neumann, Janos</item>
                     <item>Nizzola</item>
                     <item>Nyari, Jeno</item>
                     <item>O’ Daniel</item>
                     <item>Oppler</item>
                     <item>Papházy</item>
                     <item>Philipp</item>
                     <item>Pollatschek, Eduard</item>
                     <item>Popper, H.</item>
                     <item>Potok</item>
                     <item>Radovski</item>
                     <item>Rapuch</item>
                     <item>Reuss</item>
                     <item>Richter (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Romulus, Brola</item>
                     <item>Salminszky</item>
                     <item>Sametz</item>
                     <item>Schaffler</item>
                     <item>Schenker</item>
                     <item>Schwarz</item>
                     <item>Spitzer</item>
                     <item>Stein</item>
                     <item>Storwell</item>
                     <item>Strobl, Zsiga</item>
                     <item>Szaray</item>
                     <item>Szego</item>
                     <item>Toifel</item>
                     <item>Torok, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Vajda, Alfred (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Vásárhelyi</item>
                     <item>Vecsey</item>
                     <item>Vest, Baron</item>
                     <item>Veszi</item>
                     <item>Vida, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Vidrigi, Stan</item>
                     <item>Warga</item>
                     <item>Weiss, Fulop</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">Internationale Stickstoffeinigung</title>
                        (International Nitrogen Pact), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Magyar Nitrogen Egyezmeny</title> (Hungarian Nitrogen
                        Pact), Lloyd</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városrendezes cimszo megirasa a Guttenberg Lexicon
                           szamara</title> (City Planning: for the Guttenberg Lexicon),
                        Christensen</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Zur Lage der Welt-Stickstoffindustrie</title> (On the
                        Situation of the World Nitrogen Industry), Lloyd</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Public presentations of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">Pozsony szabalyozasi terverol</title> (On the
                        Regulation Plans for Bratislava), Mérnökegylet</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Ganz factory</item>
                     <item>Goldberger factory</item>
                     <item>Tata-Banhidai Water supply</item>
                     <item>The Danube dam and its flood control</item>

                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 15: <unitdate>October 29, 1930 - May 30, 1932</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The Swiss group steps back from the purchase of the Nitrogen Factory due to the
                     failure of Creditanstalt. After the Nitrogen Factory trial, the Mironescu
                     government falls. </p>
                  <p>Nitrogen prices fall in the worldwide market. The International Nitrogen
                     Agreement ends, as does the collective office in London, European Export
                     Company. The Carbide Syndicate survives. The contract with Solvay is renewed. </p>
                  <p>The Nitrogen Factory begins to provide electricity to Seta. Imre Forbáth
                     continues to meet with Dr. Hiller and to discuss the possibility of producing
                     bauxite. Forbáth travels to Paris, Munich, Vienna, Zurich, Berlin, and
                     Bucharest. </p>
                  <p>Two-thirds of the workers are discharged from the Hungarian office due to the
                     economic crisis. In 1931, the Baustellung Berlin Exhibition invites Forbáth to
                     exhibit his city plans. He prepares plans for Antwerp, Brasso, Zamardi,
                     Belgrade, Birmingham, and Bratislava. The German publication <title render="italic">Deutscher Gelehrter Kalender</title> writes about Imre
                     Forbáth in its third edition (1931).</p>
                  <p>In 1931, he begins to rewrite the diary he wrote in Russia while prisoner of
                     war. That diary was written in German and in stenography, so it cannot be
                     decoded except by him. The diary in stenography is the eighth diary in the
                     collection.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Bachler</item>
                     <item>Balog</item>
                     <item>Baron, Tomi</item>
                     <item>Bence, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Bocke, Kalman</item>
                     <item>Boni</item>
                     <item>Csetenyi, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Dinda</item>
                     <item>Fuchs</item>
                     <item>Gelderen</item>
                     <item>German</item>
                     <item>Goldfinger</item>
                     <item>Greiner, Sandor</item>
                     <item>Halapy, Oszkar</item>
                     <item>Harsanyi, Zsolt</item>
                     <item>Henz</item>
                     <item>Herceg, Peter</item>
                     <item>Kafsner</item>
                     <item>Kiss (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Kornfeld, Baron</item>
                     <item>Kragsner</item>
                     <item>Krauss</item>
                     <item>Lany, Lajos (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Manoilescu</item>
                     <item>Miller, Pali</item>
                     <item>Paloczik</item>
                     <item>Partos</item>
                     <item>Philipp</item>
                     <item>Poposh</item>
                     <item>Rapor, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Raprey</item>
                     <item>Romanescu</item>
                     <item>Ropoch</item>
                     <item>Rosenbaumne</item>
                     <item>Saffer, Misa</item>
                     <item>Salusinszky, Gyula </item>
                     <item>Sebestyen, Karoly </item>
                     <item>Sionovits</item>
                     <item>Stein</item>
                     <item>Stockheim</item>
                     <item>Szekeres, Margit</item>
                     <item>Thomand</item>
                     <item>Torok, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Vajda</item>
                     <item>Vida, Jeno </item>
                     <item>Wehner, Jozsef (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Wittmann, Mihaly</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A modern mutragyagyartas problemai</title> (Problems
                        of Modern Chemical Fertilizer Production), Magyar Szemle</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A mutragya hatasa a Magyar buzara</title> (Effects of
                        Chemical Fertilizer on Hungarian Wheat), For Stiffstoff</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Dualism in Städtebau</title> (Dualism in City
                        Building), Monatshafte, Baukunst and Städtebau</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Hadifogolynaplo</title> (Diary of a Prisoner of
                        War)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Pozsonyi terv</title> (Plan of Bratislava),
                        Közlöny</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Public presentations of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A nemzetkozi Nitrogenkartell Fejlesztese</title>
                        (Expansion of the International Nitrogen Cartel)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Pozsonyi terv</title> (Plan of Bratislava), Mérnök
                        Egylet</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Goldberger Factory </item>
                     <item>Water supply of Cheora Kadisa Jewish Cemetery</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 16: <unitdate>May 30, 1932 - March 5, 1934</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>There are great expectations before the Economic Conference in Lausanne, but it
                     does little to improve the situation. It is impossible to escape the economic
                     depression without the cooperation of all European states. Workers have been
                     let go and wages have been cut in Diciosanmartin and at the Budapest office.
                     Sales of calcium cyanamide fertilizers, which have accounted for most sales for
                     the past four to five years, are decreasing. Romanian sales have completely
                     stopped, and Hungarian sales are minimal. The reason for this, besides the bad
                     Hungarian agricultural situation, is the opening of the Fertilizer Factory in
                     Pet, Hungary. On the other hand, sales of calcium carbamide, caustic potash,
                     and electricity have increased. New profitable products include
                     trichloroethylene, tetrachloride, chromates, hydrochloric acid, borax,
                     ultramarine, and nitric acid. The Ministry of War is the biggest customer for
                     nitric acid. Kerbs, a factory owner from Oslo, discusses the production of
                     hydrogen-superoxide with Forbáth. There are also plans to manufacture gas. The
                     Romanian Minister, Citatiune, countersues Forbáth for 1.5 million lei, which
                     Romania has paid to the Nitrogen Factory in the form of coverage for losses. </p>
                  <p>The second degree verdict, in favor of Imre Forbáth, declares that Romania is
                     not the successor of the Austro-Hungarian War Ministry. The lawyer defending
                     Romania is Rosenthal; Forbáth’s lawyers are Elias and Juniau. The Factory has
                     to go through another trial, against its delegate, Marcu. There are conferences
                     in Berlin about the rebirth of the Carbide Cartel, and in Paris, about the
                     rebirth of the Calcium Cyanamide Cartel. In Hungary, there are restrictions on
                     Romanian foreign exchange and imports. The office of international common
                     sales, Super Export, is closing. Forbáth’s office in Budapest is moving from 1
                     Jozsef Square to 7 Dorottya Street. In 1933, the first ever telephone
                     conversation takes place between the Budapest office and Diciosanmartin.</p>
                  <p>The Przemysl Monument is unveiled in a square on the Buda side of the Margit
                     Bridge, in memory of the prisoners of war from Przemysl who died in Russian
                     captivity. The statue was given to the capital by Captain Tamássy, and accepted
                     by Vice-Major Liber. The veterans, with General Domokos Lazar, parade in lines
                     of four in front of the monument. The Hungarians advertise a competition for
                     the anthem of Balaton.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Alerbst</item>
                     <item>Bachmann</item>
                     <item>Balazs, Peter</item>
                     <item>Balogh, Vajda</item>
                     <item>Bernstein(Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Bock</item>
                     <item>Bodin</item>
                     <item>Boni, Feri</item>
                     <item>Breaud</item>
                     <item>Brokwode</item>
                     <item>Brunner</item>
                     <item>Caurbon, Mario</item>
                     <item>Chorin, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Clurik</item>
                     <item>Csaszkazy</item>
                     <item> Denes, Imre</item>
                     <item>Deuts, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Deutsch, Erno</item>
                     <item>Dottka</item>
                     <item>Ekrest</item>
                     <item>Epstein</item>
                     <item>Erske</item>
                     <item>Fabian</item>
                     <item>Farkas, Heddi</item>
                     <item>Ferenc, Pal</item>
                     <item>Fleischer</item>
                     <item>Frank</item>
                     <item>Frank(Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Freger</item>
                     <item>Gandilleu</item>
                     <item>Gaz</item>
                     <item>Gilchrich</item>
                     <item>Golderen, Max</item>
                     <item>Goldfinger, Leo</item>
                     <item>Hevesi (Rabbi)</item>
                     <item>Hevesy, Sandor</item>
                     <item>Hoffgarten</item>
                     <item>Huy</item>
                     <item>Karnitz-Fodor</item>
                     <item>Kemenyi (Major)</item>
                     <item>Kerbs</item>
                     <item>Kornfeld, Pal</item>
                     <item>Krafsner</item>
                     <item>Krebs</item>
                     <item>Krepler</item>
                     <item>Lajos Nagy</item>
                     <item>Lanczi, Boske</item>
                     <item>Lang</item>
                     <item>Libermann</item>
                     <item>Lippay</item>
                     <item>Magyar, Mihaly</item>
                     <item>Mangold, (Pal)</item>
                     <item>Meyer</item>
                     <item>Muller, Pal</item>
                     <item>Nemes, Olga</item>
                     <item>O’ Sebastian</item>
                     <item>Ory</item>
                     <item>Otvos</item>
                     <item>Padovski, Bucher</item>
                     <item>Parucz</item>
                     <item>Patak</item>
                     <item>Philipp</item>
                     <item>Polski</item>
                     <item>Polya, Lili</item>
                     <item>Poth, Miklos </item>
                     <item>Potok</item>
                     <item>Proszerinmier</item>
                     <item>Ramitz</item>
                     <item>Riddersbuh</item>
                     <item>Rittman</item>
                     <item>Rodling</item>
                     <item>Roman, Aurel</item>
                     <item>Rozsa</item>
                     <item>Ruckert</item>
                     <item>Ruschman</item>
                     <item>Russel</item>
                     <item>Schenjer, Gyula</item>
                     <item>Scherbel</item>
                     <item>Schimitzek</item>
                     <item>Schonberg, Arnol</item>
                     <item>Spitzer</item>
                     <item>Stein</item>
                     <item>Szekely, Bela</item>
                     <item>Szekely, Imre</item>
                     <item>Szigeti, Pal</item>
                     <item>Terrece</item>
                     <item>Thomanek</item>
                     <item>Tomasi</item>
                     <item>Tricher</item>
                     <item>Uzonyi, Bela (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Vajda(Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Vecsey</item>
                     <item>Vida</item>
                     <item>Weiss</item>
                     <item>Wild</item>
                     <item>Wilhelm, Karoly (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Zador, István</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Taban uj tervei</title> (New Plans of Taban)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Roma és Parizs tervezeserol</title> (On the Planning
                        of Rome and Paris), Pesti Naplo</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Goldberg Factory</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 17: <unitdate>March 8, 1934 - February 5, 1936</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The situation of the nitrogen market is improving in Romania; however, exports
                     are still restricted. There are two new branches in the Nitrogen Factory, for
                     the production of tiles and of synthetic ammonias and their derivatives. In the
                     internal market, the demand for these products is so large that the factory
                     plans to enlarge. The buildings surrounding the factory must also be expanded. </p>
                  <p>There are negotiations about the sale of the company to a group of buyers:
                     Pager, Dragonieranu Buzescu, Constantinescu, Gigurtu, and Caramfil. Gigurtu is
                     the Minister of Industry. This group buys the Nitrogen Factory on January 30,
                     1935. The contract is written by the lawyers Vajda and Domong. Though the
                     Romanian Bank does not give permission for the transaction, negotiations go on.
                     Because of the so called Incadrare Law, other problems arise around the
                     factory. The law breaks up workers and administrators into seven groups. In
                     each group, there can be a maximum of 205 foreigners, meaning Jews and
                     Hungarians. In the group to which the Nitrogen Factory belongs, a ministerial
                     committee has the right to fire anyone and appoint a new official. The ministry
                     immediately fires and expels a Hungarian engineer. Imre Forbáth takes these
                     trials calmly, while Romanian impatience with the Nitrogen Factory
                     increases.</p>
                  <p>The case against the Ministry of War takes a new turn: in contrast to the last
                     two verdicts, the highest court of cassation declares the Romanian War Office
                     the successor of the Austro-Hungarian War Office. Forbáth appeals to the
                     Tribunal Arbitral in Paris. Many trials and hearings follow.</p>
                  <p>There is a Carbide Cartel conference in Zurich and Rome and a Middle European
                     Nitrogen meeting in Prague and Vienna. There is a Syndicate meeting in Paris.
                     Forbáth sends a representative to the Berlin conference.</p>
                  <p>He is upset about the apathy of the world towards the persecution of the Jews.
                     Forbáth is enthusiastic about Thomas Mann’s letter on Nazi Germany, published
                     in the <title render="italic">Zürcher Zeitung.</title> Mussolini’s speech is
                     aired on the radio. </p>
                  <p>Forbáth visits the Hungarian Tile Factory. In Hungary, Horthy is chancellor and
                     Gyula Gombos prime minister. Anti-Semitism is growing in the country. </p>
                  <p>After selling the Nitrogen Factory, Imre Forbáth wants to become a private
                     engineer again. The National Association of Engineers elects him President of
                     City Development in Budapest. He is also a delegate of the City Building
                     Council to the Congress of Civil Engineering.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Buchler</item>
                     <item>Danner (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Domonyi, Bator</item>
                     <item>Epressi</item>
                     <item>Fauser, Giacomo</item>
                     <item>Feher, Pal</item>
                     <item>Gigurtu</item>
                     <item>Harrer</item>
                     <item>Horthy</item>
                     <item>Junian</item>
                     <item>Kornfeld (Baron)</item>
                     <item>Kovacs, Geza</item>
                     <item>Krauu</item>
                     <item>Kunz</item>
                     <item>Magnus</item>
                     <item>Maniu</item>
                     <item>Nyari</item>
                     <item>Papp</item>
                     <item>Schiffer</item>
                     <item>Simonkovics</item>
                     <item>Sipos</item>
                     <item>Stein</item>
                     <item>Toszegi</item>
                     <item>Vajda(Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Viforeanu</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Kispesti Munkasnegyed Fotere</title> (Main Square
                        of the Workers’ District in Kispest), Magyar Epitomuveszet</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Taban rendezesi terve</title> (Organization and
                        Plan of Taban), Self-published, Bucharest; Lloyd</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Wells of the Goldberger Factory in Obuda</item>
                     <item>Budafok Plant: Design of the New Water Pump</item>
                  </list>

               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 18: <unitdate>February 6, 1936 - December 21, 1937</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>At the beginning of 1937, the Diciosanmartin Factory is still run by Imre
                     Forbáth from his office in Budapest. After the long controversy with the
                     Romanian government, the Nitrogen Factory is sold to the Romanians. On December
                     14, 1935, the assembly declares that the company’s seat is being moved to
                     Bucharest. The Budapest office is eliminated on May 1, 1936. After the factory
                     is given to Romania, 14 out of 16 Jewish officials of the factory are fired,
                     and most of the Hungarians as well. Imre Forbáth takes responsibility for the
                     fired officials, allowing them to retire formally, and pays them rewards in the
                     name of the former owners of the factory. Forbáth assigns a Hungarian assistant
                     to the new director appointed by the Romanians. </p>
                  <p>The first million lei from the sale of the Nitrogen Factory arrives at the
                     Credit Bank, but the contract signed in 1935 expires without the completion of
                     the purchase. A new contract must be drawn up with Gigortu. The Romanian
                     National Bank takes a long time to approve it. </p>
                  <p>Forbáth continues to represent the factory at International Cartel meetings in
                     London, Berlin, and Paris even after it is sold. Before his London trip,
                     Forbáth writes a letter to Samuel Hoare, in which he congratulates him on his
                     book, The Fourth Seal. He would like to arrange a meeting to discuss the
                     possibility of publishing his diary written in Siberia as a prisoner of war.
                     Hoare replies warmly and invites him to London. Imre Forbáth arrives in London
                     at the moment when Hoare is named First Lord of Admiralty, so their meeting has
                     to be postponed. </p>
                  <p>A competition is announced for plans for the exhibition and market area in
                     Vienna. Forbáth draws up a plan with the engineers Deli and Farago. They take
                     third place, the only foreign plan given an award. </p>
                  <p>A group from the Commerce Bank negotiates with the Hungarian Government about
                     the rental of the Port Authority in Csepel, with Forbáth joining the
                     discussions. He is a leading figure of the Chamber of Engineers and of the
                     press, involved in providing medical care and insurance to engineers. He wants
                     to go back to teaching at the newly reorganized Technological University in
                     Budapest.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <item>Achner</item>
                     <item>Bachler, Lenke</item>
                     <item>Balogh, Jozsi</item>
                     <item>Bence</item>
                     <item>Benes, Imre</item>
                     <item>Berczlettig</item>
                     <item>Berzenczey</item>
                     <item>Bold, Adel</item>
                     <item>Boldizsar</item>
                     <item>Czako (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Czako, Bela</item>
                     <item>Domony (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Drogomiennu</item>
                     <item>Eggel</item>
                     <item>Elek, Kato</item>
                     <item>Engl (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Erdelyi, Natan</item>
                     <item>Farkas, Naci</item>
                     <item>Fenyes, Adolf</item>
                     <item>Gal</item>
                     <item>Gluckstal</item>
                     <item>Gold, Frigyes</item>
                     <item>Goldfinger</item>
                     <item>Grunwald</item>
                     <item>Halom, Margit</item>
                     <item>Harrer</item>
                     <item>Heltay, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Horthy, István</item>
                     <item>Horvath, Lipot</item>
                     <item>Hubert</item>
                     <item>Karzate</item>
                     <item>Krapner</item>
                     <item>Maniu</item>
                     <item>Marcselenyi</item>
                     <item>Mery, Imre</item>
                     <item>Mihailich</item>
                     <item>Mihailik, Frigyes</item>
                     <item>Morgesianu</item>
                     <item>Okanyi, Andor</item>
                     <item>Oppler</item>
                     <item>Pap, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Popper, Gyorgy</item>
                     <item>Quirin</item>
                     <item>Rapuch</item>
                     <item>Ravasz, Laszlo</item>
                     <item>Revai</item>
                     <item>Richter, Gedeon</item>
                     <item>Ritz</item>
                     <item>Rohringer</item>
                     <item>Salusinszky</item>
                     <item>Sandor, Pal</item>
                     <item>Schiffer</item>
                     <item>Schuller</item>
                     <item>Simoncsics</item>
                     <item>Szabo, Bela</item>
                     <item>Szabo, Gusztav</item>
                     <item>Szeben, Dezso</item>
                     <item>Ubul</item>
                     <item>Vajda, András</item>
                     <item>Vajda, György</item>
                     <item>Valentin</item>
                     <item>Ver, Tibor</item>
                     <item>Warga</item>
                     <item>Wertner, Richard</item>
                     <item>Wicklin</item>
                     <item>Wigner</item>
                     <item>Wittenberg</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Presentations of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">Bukarest ujjaepitese</title> (Reconstruction of
                        Bucharest)</item>
                     <item>Vilagkiallitas Parizsban (World Fair in Paris)</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Expert for the Capital’s Waterworks Directory</item>
                     <item>Extension of the Waterworks in Buda</item>
                     <item>Pumps of the Goldberger Factory at the Danube</item>
                     <item>Water Supply and Sewage in Újvidék</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 19: <unitdate>: December 21, 1937 - November 11,
                        1939</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>Imre Forbáth goes to Berlin for the first Carbide Cartel meeting. On the way
                     back, he stops at Vienna, where he sees swastikas and Nazi banners everywhere.
                     The synagogue is burned down and Jewish stores are vandalized and marked.</p>
                  <p>The Nitrogen Factory’s February 15, 1938 meeting declares the factory’s worth
                     to be 11 million pengős. After the company is sold, the main office is
                     relocated to Bucharest. Forbáth donates the factory’s old plans to the
                     Technical Museum of Budapest. </p>
                  <p>British Oxygen tries to dictate conditions for the carbide market. The second
                     Cartel meeting ends in Paris. The meeting of the third Cartel is planned for
                     Geneva on July 1, 1938. Imre Forbáth goes to this meeting with his
                     seventeen-year-old son, Tamás. Afterwards, Imre goes to Paris while Tamás goes
                     to London, where he takes an examination in English at the City of London
                     College.</p>
                  <p>In the Technical University in Budapest, a National Drinking Water Conference
                     is held and the National Common Health Institute is established. The World Fair
                     opens, and an International Eucharistic Congress is held at the same time as
                     the St. István Exhibition. Cardinal Pacelli leads the procession into Budapest,
                     at the side of Horthy. </p>
                  <p>Keren Kajemeth’s representative seeks out Forbáth to collect money for the
                     purchase of Palestinian lands. Jewish refugees from Austria and Germany ask for
                     Forbáth’s help. Emigration from the country is more and more frequent. </p>
                  <p>In 1938, the First Jewish law comes into effect, restricting the number of Jews
                     in the professions and in commercial enterprises to twenty percent. The Jews
                     are being shut out of Hungarian society. Imrédi is forced to resign when it is
                     found that one of his great-grandparents was Jewish. The new Prime Minister,
                     Pál Teleki, pushes through the Second Jewish Law, even harsher and more
                     restrictive than the First. He announces the return of Kárpátalja
                     (Subcarpathia) to Hungary. Military conscription is re-introduced. Young Jews
                     are leaving the country by the thousands. Imre Forbáth discusses these events
                     with his son, Tamás, and wants to send him abroad. After finishing high school
                     on July 12, 1939, Tamás leaves for the Royal College in London, where he
                     prepares for the science examination in the summer. Many young British men have
                     applied to the same college this year, because of conscription; a Royal College
                     degree will automatically make them officers. Feeling he will have a better
                     chance elsewhere, he transfers to the faculty of technology of the University
                     of Manchester.</p>
                  <p>Forbath won a Third Place for the Plans for the Exhibition and Market Area in
                     Vienna</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Agotay</item>
                     <item>Archer, Pal</item>
                     <item>Aschner, Pal</item>
                     <item>Aurel, Egry</item>
                     <item>Babianu</item>
                     <item>Balint, Emma</item>
                     <item>Balint, Jozsef</item>
                     <item>Barabas, Andon</item>
                     <item>Bcher, Lenke</item>
                     <item>Bece</item>
                     <item>Benes, Imre</item>
                     <item>Bereczelli</item>
                     <item>Bruck, Tamás</item>
                     <item>Cariaes (Professor)</item>
                     <item>Desseffy, Miklosne</item>
                     <item>Dinda</item>
                     <item>Dipscher, Istvánne</item>
                     <item>Domony</item>
                     <item>Drajomiseanu</item>
                     <item>Drinda</item>
                     <item>Epstein</item>
                     <item>Farkas, Naci</item>
                     <item>Fekete, Sandorne (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Ferko Boni</item>
                     <item>Fleischmann (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Forbáth, Sandor (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Frank</item>
                     <item>Frazer (Miss)</item>
                     <item>Fuhrer, Miklos</item>
                     <item>German (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Gerna</item>
                     <item>Gluckothal</item>
                     <item>Grumer</item>
                     <item>Grunwald</item>
                     <item>Gyeresi, Gabor</item>
                     <item>Halom</item>
                     <item>Harrer</item>
                     <item>Hatvany, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Hollosy, Odon</item>
                     <item>Horvth, Lipot</item>
                     <item>Icheiser</item>
                     <item>Kapri (Baron)</item>
                     <item>Krapner</item>
                     <item>Lobeger</item>
                     <item>Magyarkallay Miksa</item>
                     <item>Marffy</item>
                     <item>Mikus, Manci</item>
                     <item>Murgusiau</item>
                     <item>Nagy, Zsiga</item>
                     <item>Neumann, Janos</item>
                     <item>Noldy</item>
                     <item>Okanyi, András</item>
                     <item>Oppler</item>
                     <item>Pajor (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Picler, Henrik</item>
                     <item>Polya, Tibor</item>
                     <item>Pompery, Elemer</item>
                     <item>Popper, Edit</item>
                     <item>Rapoch</item>
                     <item>Richter, Gedeon</item>
                     <item>Rocheri, Charlie</item>
                     <item>Rogi, Frank</item>
                     <item>Rudko</item>
                     <item>Saluiszky</item>
                     <item>Spiero</item>
                     <item>Stein, Emil</item>
                     <item>Szechenyi, Balint</item>
                     <item>Szego</item>
                     <item>Tamás, Arpad</item>
                     <item>Ungvar, Imre</item>
                     <item>Vajda</item>
                     <item>Vikar, Geza</item>
                     <item>Viovai, Robert</item>
                     <item>Vlentin</item>
                     <item>Weiss, Fulop</item>
                     <item>Wigner</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">Belgradi Városkozpont</title> (Belgrade’s Downtown),
                        Ter és Forma</item>
                     <item>Bibliography of Imre Forbáth by Dr. Palfy-Endre Budinszky</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Epulo Buda</title> (Building Buda), Budai
                        Naplo</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Imre Forbáth’s biography and his picture,</title>
                        Köpfe (The Head) publishes, Neue Freie Presse</item>
                     <item>Interview with Imre Forbáth in Budai Naplo</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Margit koruti epitkezesekrol</title> (On the Building
                        of the Margit Beltway), Budai Naplo </item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Megjegyzesek a várbeli Julian Szobor
                           felirataihoz</title> (Comments on the Inscriptions on the Julian Statue
                        at the Castle), Budai Naplo</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Pozsony Kispesti Foter,</title> Bratislava, Kispest’s
                        Main Square, Ter és Forma</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Uj epitesi szabalyok</title> (New Rules on Building),
                        Budai Naplo</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városepites Torokországban</title> (City Building in
                        Turkey), Vallalkozok Lapja</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Wien Ausstellungspläne</title> (Plans for the
                        Exhibition Area in Vienna), Ter és Forma</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Zur Frage ders Taban Hotels</title> (On the Question
                        of the Hotels in Taban), Ter és Forma</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Public presentations of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">Building Buda</title>
                     </item>
                     <item>New Rules on Building</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Vilagkiallitasok Parizsban </title> (World Fairs in
                        Paris), Lipotvárosi Kamara</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Expert on the Water Supply for the Paper Factory in Szentendre</item>
                     <item>Expert on the Water Supply of the Csepel Cellulose Factory</item>
                     <item>First Drafts of the Danube Waterworks in Obuda</item>
                     <item>Goldberg Factory’s Water Supply</item>
                     <item>Watering and Canalization of Újvidék</item>

                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal 20: <unitdate>November 12, 1939 - December 20, 1941</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>In 1939, Imre Forbáth obtains his parents’ and grandparents’ papers, which
                     prove that the family has lived in Nyitra, Hungary since 1815. The entire
                     Hungarian population is being compelled to produce similar proofs.</p>
                  <p>The Budapest office of the Nitrogen Factory is liquidated. Due to the war, the
                     Cartel is abolished. The factory in Diciosanmartin continues its liquidation
                     process. Forbáth and Dr. Vajda give the records of the Nitrogen Factory to
                     Bucharest. There is an accidental explosion in the Chlorine Factory in Zernest,
                     resulting in a large number of casualties.</p>
                  <p>At the end of September 1939, Washington announces the Sixteenth International
                     Builders’ Conference. Forbáth sends a contribution on the theme “The
                     Relationship between Population Density and Buildings.” He is invited to the
                     conference but is unable to attend due to the war.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Ag, Peti</item>
                     <item>Bauer</item>
                     <item>Bence, Gyla</item>
                     <item>Berczelli</item>
                     <item>Borbas, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Deli</item>
                     <item>Dreitner, Erich</item>
                     <item>Emigrants</item>
                     <item>Farago</item>
                     <item>Ferencz, Pali</item>
                     <item>Gelieren, Mark, van</item>
                     <item>Gombos, Laszlo</item>
                     <item>Harry</item>
                     <item>Heves, Bandi and Pityu </item>
                     <item>Horvath, Lipoth (and family)</item>
                     <item>Krefonerni (and daughter)</item>
                     <item>Mezei, Veronika</item>
                     <item>Molnar, Imre (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Okanyi, András</item>
                     <item>Oppler, Pista (family)</item>
                     <item>Opples, Emil</item>
                     <item>Papp, Lilly (and her husband)</item>
                     <item>Pogany, Bela (family)</item>
                     <item>Polya, Jancsi (family)</item>
                     <item>Popock</item>
                     <item>Riemes, Jozsi</item>
                     <item>Schwarz, Alfred (family)</item>
                     <item>Szentgyorgyi (Professor)</item>
                     <item>Torok</item>
                     <item>Ullmann</item>
                     <item>Vadasz</item>
                     <item>Vajda</item>
                     <item>Viray, Imre</item>
                     <item>Walkiden</item>
                     <item>Wolf, Nazi (Farkas, Naci)</item>
                     <item>Wottitz</item>
                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Waterworks Plan of the Danube for the Goldberger Factory at Obuda</item>

                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate>Journal 21: December 21, 1941 - December 25, 1943</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>The Office of Land Registry takes away Forbáth’s orchard in Bugyi; however, the
                     family rents it back from the government. Imre Forbáth’s membership in the
                     Board of Engineers ends. He loses his voting rights. He must fill out a survey
                     about how his home can be shared, and about his Jewish origins. It has been 25
                     years since he returned from Siberian captivity. Dr. Arthur Kovacs, a fellow
                     former prisoner of war, holds a gathering to remember their time in the Nikolok
                     Ussurisk prison camp.</p>
                  <p>At the suggestion of one of his professors, Tamás Forbáth leaves England and
                     travels to America because of the war. In 1942, he earns a B. S. in Chemical
                     Engineering at Columbia University in New York. He is able to communicate with
                     his family only very rarely. In Hungary, the male members of the Forbáth family
                     are drafted for labor service. Tamás’s former high school classmates write to
                     Imre Forbáth for support. They have been in labor service in Transylvania for
                     two years. They work barefoot, without blankets, coats, or food. One of them
                     was the national high school champion in mathematics. Forbáth sends them
                     financial aid. The Pro-Palestine Association also asks Forbáth for donations.
                     Imre Forbáth does not have work during the war. He takes care of his properties
                     and he serves as an air raid warden in his community. He tries to build new
                     shelters. Forbáth is thinking about death. He reads texts from the Old and New
                     Testaments. He looks for reasons for the tragic fate of the Jews. He has faith
                     that the worst will never happen in Hungary. He believes that the following
                     year will be a year of wise decisions.</p>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>People mentioned:</head>
                     <item>Andor</item>
                     <item>Balla, Pal</item>
                     <item>Barta</item>
                     <item>Bauer</item>
                     <item>Bence</item>
                     <item>Bencsik</item>
                     <item>Bodnar</item>
                     <item>Borbas, Lajos</item>
                     <item>Dan</item>
                     <item>Denes, Klara</item>
                     <item>Farkas, Heidi</item>
                     <item>Farkas, Naci</item>
                     <item>Forro (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Fried, Pal</item>
                     <item>Fritz, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Gessler</item>
                     <item>Glesinger, Emil</item>
                     <item>Guszti, Alcsuty</item>
                     <item>Harrer, Ferenc</item>
                     <item>Heisler</item>
                     <item>Herceg, Klara</item>
                     <item>Herman, Lipot</item>
                     <item>Katona</item>
                     <item>Kemeny</item>
                     <item>Klenovics</item>
                     <item>Koranyi</item>
                     <item>Kornfeld, Pal</item>
                     <item>Kosa</item>
                     <item>Krauzner</item>
                     <item>Kunváry, Bella</item>
                     <item>Laczko, Andor</item>
                     <item>Lord</item>
                     <item>Ludekes, Tiborne</item>
                     <item>Magyar</item>
                     <item>Mandl, Imre</item>
                     <item>Markos, Viktor</item>
                     <item>Merse, Pal</item>
                     <item>Muller, Dora</item>
                     <item>Nagy, Bela</item>
                     <item>Okanyi</item>
                     <item>Palocz, Bodog</item>
                     <item>Patek</item>
                     <item>Pekri, Geza</item>
                     <item>Polya, Jeno</item>
                     <item>Popper, Laci</item>
                     <item>Proszvimer</item>
                     <item>Puzios</item>
                     <item>Rapech, Geza</item>
                     <item>Rapeck, Andor</item>
                     <item>Richter, Gedeon</item>
                     <item>Roszvinner</item>
                     <item>Sarkany, Feri</item>
                     <item>Stein, Sandor </item>
                     <item>Szabo, Guszti </item>
                     <item>Szekely, Imre</item>
                     <item>Szentirmay (Dr.)</item>
                     <item>Talgay-Roth, Miklos</item>
                     <item>Ullmann, Andor</item>
                     <item>Vadasz</item>
                     <item>Vecsey</item>
                     <item>Virag (Professor)</item>
                     <item>Weber, Tibor</item>
                     <item>Wetzl</item>
                     <item>ador</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Writings of this period:</head>
                     <item><title render="italic">A Budai Kilato ut</title> (Road to the Look Out Tower
                        at Buda), Budai Kronika (in the Emlekkonyv, which was left out due to paper
                        shortages)</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Milliok evacualasara kepes város terve</title> (About
                        a City Capable of Evacuating Millions), Magyar Nemzet</item>
                     <item><title render="italic">Városepites a haboru utan</title> (City Building
                        after the War)</item>

                  </list>
                  <list type="marked">
                     <head>Works of this period:</head>
                     <item>Goldberger Factory</item>
                  </list>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Inserts found in diaries</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <unittitle>Letter to Tamas, <unitdate>11 November, 1941,</unitdate> Budapest
                        (fragment, typescript)</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c level="file">
                     <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                        <unittitle>Forbath, Imre, 1932</unittitle>

                     </did>

                  </c>
                  <c level="file">
                     <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                        <unittitle>Forbath, Imre with family, 1929</unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <unittitle>Business card (with a holograph note)</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <unittitle>Book-Plate (with a holograph note on a back)</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
         </c>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>