<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
    <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
        <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_6892009_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_6892009_ead.xml</eadid>
        <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the Joanne Grant research files,</titleproper>
                <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
                    Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
                    Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
            </titlestmt>
            <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
                    University Libraries</publisher>
                <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2009-03-05">March 5, 2009 </date>
                <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
                    <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
                    <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
                </address>
            </publicationstmt>
        </filedesc>
        <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT
                conversion <date normal="2009-03-05">March 5, 2009 </date>
            </creation>
            <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
            </langusage>
        </profiledesc>
        <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2009-03-05">2009-03-05</date>
                <item>File created.</item>
            </change>
            <change><date normal="2009-04-16">2009-04-16</date>
                <item>xml document instance created by Carrie Hintz</item>
            </change>
        </revisiondesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
        <did><origination><persname encodinganalog="100">Grant, Joanne</persname>
            </origination>
            <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="Joanne Grant research files,">Joanne Grant
                Research Files,</unittitle>
            <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1963/1975" type="inclusive">1963-1968.</unitdate>
            <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">1.44 linear feet (3 document boxes).</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository encodinganalog="852">
                <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library, University
                        Archives</subarea>
                </corpname>
                <address><addressline>New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
                </address>
            </repository>
            <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">6892009</unitid>
            <unitid encodinganalog="852$j" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">UA#0141</unitid>
            <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
                <language langcode="eng">In English</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <abstract>This collection consists of the working materials Joanne Grant, a journalist and activist, collected for the research and publication of her 1969 book <title render="italic">Confrontation on Campus: Columbia Pattern for the New Protest</title> (New York: New American Library, 1969).</abstract>
        </did>
        <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
            <head>Biographical Note</head>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Joanne Grant, born in 1930 in Ithaca, New York to a
                biracial mother and white father, graduated from Syracuse University with a degree
                in history and journalism. At 27, Grant traveled throughout the Soviet Union and
                China, defying state bans on travel to Communist countries, seeking alternatives to
                an American political system that perpetuated segregation and class divides. Grant
                was deeply interested in finding organizing and mobilizing tools through which to
                address the racial and economic inequities of American democracy. Upon her return,
                the young journalist briefly assisted W.E.B. DuBois, noted black scholar,
                intellectual, and activist. DuBois, who had left the National Association for the
                Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), an organization he had founded, as the
                leadership became more mainstream, sought increasingly more radical alliances for
                his activism. Undoubtedly, DuBois' mounting frustrations with the unfulfilled
                promises of equality through integration and his profound interest in creating
                international Communist alliances, influenced Grant. </p>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->With DuBois' referral, Grant took a position as a
                journalist at the Leftist New York weekly <title render="italic">The National
                    Guardian </title>in 1960 and traveled throughout the South to detail Civil
                Rights struggles for the paper, writing on Freedom Summer, the Citizenship School
                movement, marches and voter registration drives. Her reporting connected to her to
                the folks of the Student Non-violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), a militant
                student organization that used direct action to protest segregation, and to SNCC's
                founder, Ella Baker. Baker, who had gotten her start as an activist in the NAACP
                some twenty-five years before, had persuaded Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. to hold a
                college conference in 1960, on the heels of sporadic youth action to desegregate
                college campuses. The symposium birthed SNCC, and Baker left the Southern Christian
                Leadership Conference (SCLC) to become the young organization's advisor. Impressed
                by the expansive direct action program SNCC was implementing, Grant joined the
                organization, both as a journalist and activist. Her journalism for <title render="italic">The Guardian</title> provided a platform for SNCC to
                publicize their work and the repressive responses of politicians, law enforcement
                and white citizens. </p>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->She married Victor Rabinowitz in 1967, a New York lawyer
                and activist who defended many Leftist organizations throughout the various freedom
                struggles of the 1960s including leaders of the Weather Underground, SNCC, and
                high-profile communists. Grant's experiences with SNCC and the Black freedom
                movement informed her comprehensive document- based history of the black struggle
                against oppression entitled <title render="italic">Black Protest: 350 Years of
                    History, Documents, and Analyses</title> (New York: Fawcett, 1968). Her
                involvement with SNCC also led her to cover and participate in the student uprisings
                at Columbia University in 1968. The result was her history and analysis of the
                strike in <title render="italic">Confrontation on Campus: The Columbia Pattern
                    for the New Protest</title>. Evident in her writings is Ms. Grant's overwhelming
                desire to find new means through which to fight oppression and inequality within the
                American democratic system. </p>
            <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Grant and Rabinowitz traveled extensively, including a trip
                to Cuba where Grant charmed Castro into allowing them to accompany the Cuban
                president on a leg of a speaking tour throughout the country. Her later work, a film
                entitled <title render="italic">Fundi</title> (1981) and later book, <title render="italic">Ella Baker: Freedom Bound</title> (New York: Wiley, 1998),
                were both dedicated to exploring the life and grassroots activism of SNCC founder
                Ella Baker.</p>
            <p/>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
            <head>Scope and Content</head>
            <p>This collection is a repository of Joanne Grant's research materials for her 1969
                book Confrontation on Campus: The Columbia Pattern for the New Protest. The
                collection contains both Grant's notes taken throughout the Columbia revolt, as well
                as collected research materials. These materials consist of Strike Coordinating
                Committee fliers, agendas, leaflets and official statements. In addition, the
                collection includes the responses of faculty, administration and community members
                to the strike. The collection also contains materials from the Independent Committee
                on Vietnam at Columbia University, student protest files against Columbia's
                involvement in the war. The materials consist of fliers, letters, telegrams and
                pictures.</p>
            <p/>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
            <head>Arrangement</head>
            <p>This collection is arranged in three series.</p>
            <p><list type="simple">
                    <item>Series I: Research Materials on Columbia
                University Student Uprisings, 1965-1968 <list type="simple">
                            <item>Subseries I.1: Pre-uprising 1963-1968</item>
                    <item>Subseries I.2: Uprising 1966-1968 </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                <item>Series II: Materials collected from Laura Foner, 1968</item>
                <item>Series III. Photographs of Columbia University Student Uprisings, 1968</item>
                </list>
            </p>
        </arrangement>
        <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia University--Administration.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia University--History.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia University.--Student Strike, 1968.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia University.--Students.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia University.--Alumni and alumnae--Societies,etc.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia University.--Students--Political activity.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia University.--Students' Afro-American Society.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia Spectator.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia University Student Coordinating Committee.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Columbia-Barnard Citizenship Council.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Committee for the Defense of Property Rights.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Community Action Committee.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Black Panther Party.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">College students--New York (State)--New York--Political
                activity.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">December Fourth Movement.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Employees for March 25th.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Faculty Peace Action Committee.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Morningside Housing Committee.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Progressive Labor Party.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Radical Faculty Group.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Student Mobilization Committee (U.S.).</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Student Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam
                a.k.a. SMC.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.).</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Students for a Free Campus.</corpname>
            <corpname encodinganalog="610">Students for a Reconstructed University a.k.a. SRU.</corpname>
            <persname encodinganalog="600">Grant, Joanne.</persname>
            <persname encodinganalog="600">Kirk, Grayson L. (Grayson Louis), 1903-</persname>
            <persname encodinganalog="600">Rudd, Mark.</persname>
            <subject encodinganalog="650">Civil rights movements.--United States--History--20th
                century.</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650">Draft resisters--Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650">Peace movements.</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650">Social movements.</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650">Student-Administrators relationships.</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650">Student Movements--New York (State)--New York.</subject>
            <subject encodinganalog="650">Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.</subject>
            <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Articles.</genreform>
            <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Clippings.</genreform>
            <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Correspondence.</genreform>
            <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Ephemera.</genreform>
            <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Handbills.</genreform>
            <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Newsletters.</genreform>
            <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat.">Press Releases.</genreform>
        </controlaccess>
        <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
            <head>Access Restrictions</head>
            <p>This collection is located offsite. </p>
            <p>This collection has no restrictions. Some personal material may be restricted due to
                the presence of personal names and information.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); Joanne Grant Research Files, Box
                and Folder; University Archives, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia
                University Library.</p>
        </prefercite>
        <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
            <head>Processing Information</head>
            <p>Collection, processed by Megan French GSAS, 2013. </p>
            <p>Finding aid wittten by Megan French, June, 2008.</p>
        </processinfo>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
            <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
            <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish material
                from the collection must be requested from the Curator of Manuscripts and University
                Archivist, Rare Book and Manuscript Library (RBML). The RBML approves permission to
                publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to secure copyright
                permission rests with the patron.</p>
        </userestrict>
        <otherfindaid encodinganalog="555">
            <p>Finding aid in repository; folder level control. </p>
        </otherfindaid>

        <dsc><c level="series">
                <did><unittitle>Series I: Columbia University Student Uprisings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1968</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                </did>
                <scopecontent><p>
                    This series contains materials that document the issues leading up to the uprising and provides a chronology of student, faculty, community and administrative involvement in the 1968 strike.  The folders within each subseries are arranged alphabetically. 
                </p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c level="subseries">
                    <did><unittitle>Subseries I.1. Pre-uprising, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1968</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent><p>
                        This subseries provides early documentation of anti-Vietnam War sentiment on Columbia University’s campus including the official documentation of the Independent Committee on Vietnam as well as student responses to Columbia’s class ranking and draft policies.  Finally there are five spiral bound notebooks of handwritten notes taken before and during the student strikes.
                    </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                            <unittitle>Draft Ranking--Student Responses, circa <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1968</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                            <unittitle>National Reserve Officers Training Corps, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1968</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3 to 4</container>
                            <unittitle>Notebooks, <unitdate>1968</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                            <physdesc><extent>(2 Folders)</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5 to 6</container>
                            <unittitle>Vietnam--Independent Committee at Columbia University,
                                    <unitdate type="inclusive">1965-1967</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                            <physdesc><extent>(2 Folders)</extent>
                            </physdesc>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                </c>
                <c level="subseries">
                    <did><unittitle>Subseries I.2. Uprising,
                        <unitdate>1966-1968</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent><p>
                        contains a compilation of fliers, SCC memoranda, meeting minutes, and statements, press releases, correspondence, and public statements documenting the student uprisings.  A full chronology is followed by the materials of various student groups: the Strike Coordinating Committee, black students and students from Barnard College. Many of the student newsletters are addressed to Morris Grossner, a Columbia University student at the time and a leader in Columbia’s chapter of the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS).  These materials are followed by letters of support and various other responses of those involved in the strike, as well as plans for the restructuring of the University. Also included are submissions, addressing racism, black students and the labor movement, by Columbia University students to the magazine <title render="italic">China Features</title> in Peking.
                    </p>
                    </scopecontent>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
                            <unittitle><title render="italic">China Features</title>--Submissions,
                                    <unitdate>1968</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                            </did>
                       </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><unittitle>Chronology</unittitle>
                            </did>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                                    <unittitle>Student Uprisings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1966-1967</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">9</container>
                                    <unittitle>Student Uprisings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                            March-June</unitdate> (1 of 2)</unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                                    <unittitle>Student Uprisings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                            March-June</unitdate> (2 of 2)</unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><unittitle>Involvement</unittitle>
                            </did>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                                    <unittitle>Barnard, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                        April-May</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                                    <unittitle>Black Students, <unitdate>1968
                                    April</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><unittitle>Responses</unittitle>
                            </did>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                                    <unittitle>Administration, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                            April-May</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                                    <unittitle>Community, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                        April-May</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                                    <unittitle>Faculty, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                        March-May</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
                                    <unittitle>Parents, <unitdate>1968 May</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                                    <unittitle>Students, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                        April-May</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">9</container>
                                <unittitle>Restructuring of Columbia University, <unitdate>1968
                                    May</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><unittitle>Strike Coordinating Committee</unittitle>
                            </did>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">10</container>
                                    <unittitle>Meeting Minutes, <unitdate>1968 March</unitdate> -
                                        June</unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                            <c level="file">
                                <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                    <container type="Folder" label="Folder">11</container>
                                    <unittitle>Official Statements and Pamphlets, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968 March-June</unitdate>
                                </unittitle>
                                </did>
                            </c>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">12</container>
                                <unittitle>Strike Education Committee, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968 May-June</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">13</container>
                                <unittitle>Surveys--Anthropology Department, <unitdate>1968
                                    April</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                </c>
             </c>
      
            
        
             <c level="series">
                    <did><unittitle>Series II: Materials Collected from Laura Foner,
                            <unitdate>1968</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent><p>
                        This series contains research materials collected from Laura Foner, a Columbia University graduate student and member of SNCC.  The papers that were contributed by Foner are marked in the top right hand corner of each page with her initials: LF.
                    </p>
                </scopecontent>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                            <unittitle>Administration, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                April-May</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                            <unittitle>Columbia Students for a Democratic Society (SDS)--Working
                                Materials, <unitdate>1968</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                            <unittitle>Graduate Student Union--Support and Responses,
                                <unitdate>1968</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><unittitle>Strike Coordinating Committee</unittitle>
                        </did>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                                <unittitle>Press Releases, <unitdate>1968</unitdate> April-
                                May</unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                                <unittitle> “The Rational Inquirer”,
                                <unitdate>1968</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                        <c level="file">
                            <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                                <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                                <unittitle>Support and Responses, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968
                                        April-May</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                            </did>
                        </c>
                    </c>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
                            <unittitle>Strike Education Committee--Class Schedules, <unitdate type="inclusive">1968 April-May</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                </c>
              
            <c level="series">
                    <did><unittitle>Series III: Photographs, <unitdate>1968</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent><p>
                        Photographs used by Grant in her 1969 book on Columbia University student uprisings <title render="italic">Confrontation on Campus</title>. Most of the images are annotated on the back. 
                    </p>
                </scopecontent>
                    <c level="file">
                        <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                            <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                            <unittitle>Photographs--Columbia University Student Uprisings,
                                    <unitdate>1968</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                        </did>
                    </c>
                  
                    
                </c>

          
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>