<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="http://eadrepo.cul.columbia.edu:8080/exist/rest/db/ead/nnc-rb_staging/schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
   <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
      <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_9577639_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_9577639_ead.xml</eadid>
      <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the Joseph Parrish Thompson and Leonard Bacon Papers,</titleproper>
            <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
               Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
               Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
               University Libraries</publisher>
            <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2012-09-12">September 12, 2012 </date>
            <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
               <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT conversion
               <date normal="2012-09-12">September 12, 2012 </date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2012-09-12">2012-09-12</date>
            <item>xml document instance created by Carrie Hintz</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did><unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="Joseph Parrish Thompson papers,">Joseph Parrish Thompson and Leonard Bacon Papers,</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1845/1928" type="inclusive">1845-1928, [Bulk Dates: 1845-1879].</unitdate>
         <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">3.5 linear ft. (2 document boxes, 1 flat box)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository encodinganalog="852">
            <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library</subarea>
            </corpname>
            <address><addressline>New York, NY. 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
         <unitid encodinganalog="090$b" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">MS#1631</unitid>
         <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">9577639</unitid>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
            <language langcode="eng"> Material is in English </language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract>This collection is made up of the personal and professional files of Joseph
            Parrish Thompson, documenting his work in the Congregational church and as the editor of
            The Independent. Thompson’s correspondence with fellow Congregational minister and
            co-editor of <title render="italic">The Independent</title> Leonard Bacon makes up a
            significant portion of the material. The collection also contains files pertaining to
            Thompson’s children and grandchildren and some family correspondence of Leonard Bacon.</abstract>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical Note</head>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Joseph Parrish Thompson was a Congregational clergyman and one
            of the first editors of <title render="italic">The Independent</title>, a Congregational
            and abolitionist newspaper founded in 1848 with close ties to the Broadway Tabernacle in
            New York City. Thompson was born in 1819 in Philadelphia. He graduated from Yale in
            1838, and he was ordained as a pastor for the Chapel Street Congregational Church in New
            Haven in 1840, after studying at the Theological Seminary in Andover, Massachusetts.
            Thompson was called to New York to become a minister at the Broadway Tabernacle in 1845.
            His career there spanned a quarter of a century, and he frequently preached to a full
            congregation of 2,500 people. Thompson was well-known for his abolitionist sentiments.
            In 1863, draft rioters attempted to burn his home and the church, but their attempts
            were thwarted by members of the congregation. Thompson had a wide range of intellectual
            interests beyond his duties as a minister. He gained some distinction as an
            Egyptologist, and he frequently entertained musicians, artists, travelers, writers, and
            other prominent political and cultural figures at his home. Thompson was acquainted with
            President Abraham Lincoln through his work in organizing the Christian Union Commission
            during the Civil War. According to a brief biography written by his son William, after
            Lincoln’s death, Mrs. Lincoln presented Thompson with his gold-headed ebony cane.</p>
         <p>While in New Haven, Thompson assisted clergyman Leonard Bacon in the founding of <title render="italic">The New Englander,</title> a Congregational periodical. The two men
            remained close colleagues, and Thompson recruited Bacon to work on <title render="italic">The Independent</title> with him in 1848. Along with the other
            editors Richard Salter Storrs and Joshua Leavitt, Thompson and Bacon molded the paper,
            which became one of the most widely circulated abolitionist newspapers in the United
            States by the time of the Civil War. In the columns of <title render="italic">The
               Independent</title>, Thompson and Bacon attempted to deal with divisions in the
            Congregational church resulting from divergent opinions among various factions on how to
            address the issues of slavery and slaveholding. The correspondence in this collection
            demonstrates the commitment of Thompson and Bacon to a less radical strain of
            abolitionism than outright opposition to the institution of slavery. Instead, they
            advocated a policy of “discreet” or indirect opposition in which they maligned
            individual vices brought on by slaveholding--i.e. the separation of families and the
            deprivation of Biblical literacy. Thompson and Bacon refused to link the paper to a
            particular political party or to the Congregational church as a whole. They insisted
            that the opinions expressed in the paper belonged only to themselves as editors. </p>
         <p>Thompson and Bacon’s tenure as editors of <title render="italic">The Independent</title>
            ended somewhat abruptly in 1861. After disagreements with one of the proprietors, Henry
            C. Bowen, and the sale and takeover of the paper by new owners, the two men were not
            asked to continue as editors. Thompson and Bacon were succeeded by Henry Ward Beecher,
            who was a frequent contributor to the newspaper already. </p>
         <p>Thompson was married twice and had five children. His two eldest sons, John and Joseph,
            served in the Civil War. John succumbed to a fever in camp, and Joseph was a captain of
            a regiment of African American troops. Thompson’s daughter Lucy married prominent dry
            goods merchant and co-owner of <title render="italic">The Independent</title> Seth B.
            Hunt. Thompson resigned from his post as pastor of the Broadway Tabernacle in 1872 due
            to his deteriorating health, and he retired to Berlin, Germany to pursue his studies in
            Egyptology. There he developed an interest in international law and was nominated as a
            minister to the German government by some of his American contacts in Berlin. He
            declined this position, however, and he died shortly after suffering a stroke in
            September 1879.</p>
         <p>Leonard Bacon was a prominent Congregational clergyman and reformer based in New Haven,
            Connecticut. He was born in Detroit, Michigan in 1802, and, like Joseph Parrish
            Thompson, he attended Yale and the Andover Theological Seminary. From 1866 until his
            death in 1881 he acted as a professor of theology and church history at Yale. Bacon’s
            anti-slavery views were moderate. He condemned both the defenders of slavery and extreme
            abolitionists like William Lloyd Garrison, whom he felt sacrificed the viability of the
            anti-slavery cause for his own self-promotion.</p>
         <p/>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>
         <p>This collection consists of correspondence between Joseph Parrish Thompson and Leonard
            Bacon, largely dating to the years they spent as editors of <title render="italic">The
               Independent</title>. The correspondence also includes a number letters between Leonard Bacon’s wife and daughter. Another part of the collection consists of material related
            to the history of the Thompson family, particularly Joseph P. Thompson and his children
            William Gilman Thompson and Lucy Bartlett Thompson Hunt. This material includes some
            correspondence as well as general personal and biographical files. There is also an
            ambrotype of Joseph Parrish Thompson. Finally, the collection includes two issues of
               <title render="italic">The Independent</title> dating to 1853 and 1908.</p>
         <p/>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged in III series<list type="marked">
                    <item>Series I: Joseph
                  Parrish Thompson and Leonard Bacon Correspondence, 1845-1879</item>
                    <item>Series II: Thompson
                  Family Files, 1854-1928</item>
                    <item>Series III: The Independent, 1853-1908</item>
                </list>
            </p>
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610">Broadway Tabernacle (New York, N.Y.)</corpname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Bacon, Leonard, 1802-1881.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Garrison, William Lloyd, 1805-1879.</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Thompson, Joseph P. (Joseph Parrish), 1819-1879.</persname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Abolitionists.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Anti-slavery movements--United States.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Congregational churches--Clergy--Correspondence.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Congregational churches--Newspapers.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Congregationalists.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Slavery--United States.</subject>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Correspondence</genreform>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Newspapers</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>This collection is located on-site. </p>
         <p>This collection has no restrictions.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition</head>
         <p>Freeman's Auction House Purchase, 0 8/02/2012 2012.2012.M028</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); Name of Collection; Box and Folder (if
            known); Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University Library.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>Papers processed 08/2012 Mary Freeman, GSAS, Columbia University. </p>
         <p>Finding aid written 08/2012 Mary Freeman, GSAS, Columbia University.</p>
      </processinfo>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
         <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish material
            from the collection must be requested from the Curator of Manuscripts/University
            Archivist, Rare Book and Manuscript Library (RBML). The RBML approves permission to
            publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to secure copyright permission
            rests with the patron.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <dsc><c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series I: Joseph
                  Parrish Thompson and Leonard Bacon Correspondence, 1845-1879</unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series is made up of correspondence between Joseph Parrish Thompson and
                  Leonard Bacon between 1845 and 1879 (the year of Thompson’s death). Most of the
                  correspondence pertains to their work as Congregational ministers and as the
                  editors of <title render="italic">The Independent</title> between 1848 and 1861.
                  The majority of the letters are from Thompson to Bacon, but there are a
                  significant number from Bacon to Thompson, as well as several addressed to Bacon
                  from other associates including Seth B. Hunt, an owner of <title render="italic">The Independent.</title> Other letters worth noting are a twenty-two page
                  letter from Bacon to Thompson in 1860 that is heavily critical of William Lloyd
                  Garrison and Wendell Phillips and a letter from Bacon’s daughter Rebecca to
                  Thompson in 1863 notifying him of Bacon’s son’s death in the Civil War. One folder contains correspondence between Katherine W. Bacon Smith and her parents Leonard Bacon and Catherine Elizabeth Terry Bacon. These letters detail general family news and Katherine’s pregnancy and the birth of her children with Eugene Smith, a New York City prison reformer.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
              
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">1845-1879</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
                  <physdesc><extent>(11 Folders)</extent>
                  </physdesc>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>(Correspondence is mainly between Thompson and Bacon with some exceptions. Many
                     letters are accompanied by typed transcripts)</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <unittitle>Bacon family correspondence, <unitdate>1861-1881</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                  </did>
                    <scopecontent><p>Mainly Katherine W. Bacon Smith to Leonard Bacon and Catherine Terry Bacon</p>
                    </scopecontent>
               </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series II: Thompson
                  Family Files, 1854-1928</unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series contains various personal files documenting the lives of members of
                  Joseph Parrish Thompson’s family. There are several items, including an ambrotype
                  and two manuscripts of articles, which date to Thompson’s lifetime. There is also
                  a biography of Thompson written by his son, physician William Gilman Thompson.
                  There are several more items that relate to William Gilman Thompson, including a
                  history of his childhood written by his mother, Joseph P. Thompson’s second wife,
                  Elizabeth Coil Thompson. There are several folders of the personal papers and
                  correspondence of Lucy Bartlett Thompson Hunt, who was Joseph P. Thompson’s
                  daughter, as well as her husband Seth B. Hunt and their children Lucy and Seth.
                  The correspondence of Seth B. Hunt (Jr.) suggests that this collection was
                  assembled in the 1920s when Theodore D. Bacon, grandson of Leonard Bacon,
                  consulted Hunt while researching the biography of his grandfather.</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Typescript of a biographical sketch of Joseph Parrish Thompson by his
                     son, William Gilman Thompson</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Manuscripts of articles by Joseph Parrish Thompson-“Can America Produce
                     a National Poetry” and an untitled article on the Library of Alexandria,
                        <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1872-1879</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Ambrotype of Joseph Parrish Thompson, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca.
                        1854</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>William Gilman Thompson obituaries, <unitdate type="inclusive">1927</unitdate> (7 copies)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>William Gilman Thompson family book-by mother Elizabeth Coil Thompson,
                        <unitdate type="inclusive">1873</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Commemoration of William Gilman Thompson</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <unittitle>Retirement from presidency of the New York Botanical
                        Garden</unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <unittitle>Retirement from Cornell Medical College, <unitdate type="inclusive">1916</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <unittitle>Reconstruction Hospital, <unitdate type="inclusive">1927</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>“Lucy Bartlett Thompson Hunt: An Appreciation”-by William Gilman
                     Thompson, <unitdate type="inclusive">1914</unitdate> (2 copies)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Seth B. Hunt and Lucy Thompson Hunt Files, <unitdate type="inclusive">1872-1948</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
                    <scopecontent><p> (includes correspondence, Seth Hunt obituaries and
                  will)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Seth B. Hunt files, <unitdate type="inclusive">1884-1928</unitdate>
                     (son of Seth and Lucy Hunt)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Thompson family correspondence-gift of William Gilman Thompson to Lucy
                     Hunt-daughter of Seth and Lucy Hunt, <unitdate type="inclusive">1862-1902</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
                    <scopecontent><p> (includes a carte-de-visite photograph of Isaac
                  Thompson, 1792-1873-the father of Joseph Parrish Thompson)</p>
                    </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>U.S. Order for Transportation slips-Mississippi-mostly freedmen,
                        <unitdate type="inclusive">1865</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series III: <title render="italic">The Independent,</title> 1853-1908</unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>This series contains a few items pertaining directly to <title render="italic">The
                     Independent</title> itself. These items include an issue of the paper dating to
                  July 28, 1853, during Thompson and Bacon’s tenure as editors, as well as the
                  sixtieth anniversary issue of the periodical, dating to 1908. This issue includes
                  reprinted material from earlier issues that were overseen by Thompson and Bacon.
               </p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Article about the Broadway Tabernacle, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca.
                        1902</unitdate> (photocopy)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>60th anniversary issue of <title render="italic">The
                        Independent,</title>
                     <unitdate type="inclusive">1908</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Issue of <title render="italic">The Independent,</title> 28 <unitdate type="inclusive">July 1853</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>