<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="schema/ead_cul.nvdl"type="xml"?><ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" audience="external">
   <eadheader findaidstatus="publish" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="DC" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
      <eadid countrycode="US" encodinganalog="Identifier" publicid="-//us::nnc-rb//TEXT us::nnc-rb::ldpd_4078569_ead//EN" mainagencycode="nnc-rb">ldpd_4078569_ead.xml</eadid>
      <filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Guide to the William Seward Burroughs Papers</titleproper>
            <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Columbia University Libraries. Rare Book and
               Manuscript Library; machine readable finding aid created by Columbia University
               Libraries Digital Library Program Division</author>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt><publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Rare Book and Manuscript Library<lb/>Columbia
               University Libraries</publisher>
            <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2009-07-25">July 25, 2009 </date>
            <address><addressline>6th Fl. East</addressline>
               <addressline>535 West 114th St.</addressline>
               <addressline>New York, NY 10027</addressline>
            </address>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc><creation>Machine readable finding aid generated from MARC-AMC source via XSLT conversion
               <date normal="2009-07-25">July 25, 2009 </date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="Language" scriptcode="Latn" langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc><change><date normal="2009-07-25">2009-07-25</date>
            <item>xml finding aid created by Carrie Hintz</item>

         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did><origination><persname encodinganalog="100">Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" altrender="William Seward Burroughs Papers">William
            Seward Burroughs Papers,</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1957/1976" type="inclusive">1957-1976.</unitdate>
         <physdesc><extent encodinganalog="300">2 linear ft (5 document boxes and 1 oversize
            item).</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository encodinganalog="852">
            <corpname>Columbia University.<subarea>Rare Book and Manuscript Library,</subarea>
            </corpname>
            <address><addressline/>
            </address>
         </repository>
         <unitid encodinganalog="090$b" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="call_num">MS#0174</unitid>
         <unitid encodinganalog="001" countrycode="US" repositorycode="nnc-rb" type="clio">4078569</unitid>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546">
            <language langcode="eng">In English</language>
         </langmaterial>
         <abstract>Author, artist, spoken word performer, and founding member of the Beat
            Generation. The William S. Burroughs Papers contain manuscripts and galley proofs of
            some of Burroughs's novels, as well as biographical material on Burroughs. </abstract>
      </did>
      <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
         <head>Biographical Note</head>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->William S. Burroughs was born in 1914 in St. Louis, Missouri.
            He attended private schools in St. Louis before a brief stint at the Los Alamos Ranch
            School in New Mexico. He received a bachelor's degree from Harvard in 1936. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->After graduating from Harvard, Burroughs spent a few years
            traveling through Europe, followed by a short stint in the US Army. After his discharge
            from the Army Burroughs moved to Chicago where he worked a string of odd jobs and spent
            time with his friend David Kammerer and Kammerer's obsession, University of Chicago
            student Lucien Carr. When Carr transferred from UC to Columbia University, both of the
            older men used this as an impetus to move to New York City as well. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->It was through Carr that Burroughs met Allen Ginsberg and Jack
            Kerouac. The three, along with Carr, Kerouac's girlfriend Edie Parker and her roommate
            Joan Vollmer, forged close friendships centered around a shared love of literature,
            drugs, and a bohemian lifestyle. It was during this time that Burroughs was first
            introduced to narcotics through the well known Times Square hustler, and writer, Herbert
            Huncke and quickly became addicted to opiates. Jean Vollmer, Burroughs's lover, and
            later common-law wife, also suffered from an addiction that eventually resulted in her
            hospitalization for acute amphetamine psychosis. The two had a son, William S. Burroughs
            Jr., before Burroughs accidentally, but fatally, shot Vollmer in Mexico City. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Burroughs began working on the manuscript that would
            eventually become <title render="italic">Junky</title> in Mexico City before Vollmer's
            death. Though he had briefly worked on the short story "And the Hippos Were Boiled in
            Their Tanks" with Jack Kerouac, he did not have literary aspirations. Even while working
            on <title render="italic">Junkie</title> he assumed that the autobiographical novel
            would be an anomaly, not the beginning of a literary career. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->After his trial over Vollmer's death, Burroughs thought it
            prudent to leave Mexico. He spent more time traveling in South America researching the
            hallucinatory drug yage and corresponding with Allen Ginsberg, who was by this point
            acting as his literary agent, about his search for the drug and its effects. These
            letters formed the basis of Burroughs and Ginsberg's book <title render="italic">The
               Yage Letters</title>. After the yage quest, Burroughs returned, briefly, to New York
            where he initiated an intense but mostly one-sided romantic and sexual relationship with
            Ginsberg before leaving the United States for a brief stay in Rome and then Tangier. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->While in Tangier Burroughs completed the text that would
            become <title render="italic">The Naked Lunch.</title>
            <title render="italic">Interzone,</title> as he called the working manuscript, was, in
            opposition to his earlier works <title render="italic">Junkie</title> and <title render="italic">Queer,</title> a non-linear collection of loosely connected episodes.
            Allen Ginsberg, who, along with Peter Orlovsky and Jack Kerouac, had traveled to Tangier
            to help collect and type a clean copy of the manuscript, presented <title render="italic">The Naked Lunch</title> to Maurice Girodias of the Olympia Press.
            Though Girodias was not initially interested in the work, he did decide to print it
            after all in 1959. An American edition, based on a 1958 manuscript of the novel
            (currently part of the Allen Ginsberg Papers held by the RBML) was published by Grove
            Press in 1962. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Burroughs then moved to Paris where he continued writing and
            producing the episodic sketches that, combined with material from <title render="italic">The Naked Lunch</title> manuscripts, comprise <title render="italic">The Soft
               Machine,</title>
            <title render="italic">The Ticket that Exploded,</title> and <title render="italic">Nova
               Express.</title> While in Paris living in a guesthouse christened the Beat Hotel with
            Ginsberg, Orlovsky, Gergory Corso, and Harold Chapman, Burroughs first came into contact
            with Brion Gysin. Gysin, a painter, had a profound impact on Burroughs and Gysin's
            "cut-up technique" where strips of two different texts were aligned to create a new,
            composite text became a prominent feature of Burroughs's future writing. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->In 1974 Burroughs returned to the United States. He accepted a
            teaching post at City College of New York that Allen Ginsberg had recommended him for
            and settled into an apartment nicknamed The Bunker on Manhattan's Lower East Side.
            During this time Burroughs became acquainted with James Grauerholz, a young beat devotee
            who became Burroughs's devoted manager, secretary, and companion. </p>
         <p><!-- BIOGHIST REQUIRED -->Burroughs moved to Lawrence Kansas in 1981 and remained there
            until his death in 1997. During the later part of his life he wrote less and less,
            focusing on visual art and spoken word performances. He also appears in the Gus Van Sant
            movie <title render="italic">Naked Cowboy.</title>
            </p>
         <p/>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
         <head>Scope and Content</head>

         <p>The William S. Burroughs Papers contain manuscripts and galley proofs of some of
            Burroughs's novels, as well as experimental prose, including early examples of
            Burroughs's cut-up technique, and a small amount of correspondence. The collection also
            contains a series of biographical material on Burroughs collected by Victor Bockris.</p>
         <p/>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
         <head>Arrangement</head>
         <p>This collection is arranged in four series. <list type="marked">
               <item>Series I: Correspondence, 1953-1973</item>
               <item>Series II: Writings, 1958-1969 </item>
               <item>Series III: Photographs and Realia </item>
               <item>Series IV: Victor Bockris Material Relating to Burroughs, 1965-1975</item>
            </list>
            </p>
      </arrangement>
      <controlaccess><head>Subjects</head>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Bockris, Victor, 1949-</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600">Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.</persname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">American literature.</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650">Beat generation.</subject>
         <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Galley proofs.</genreform>
         <occupation encodinganalog="656" source="lcsh">Authors.</occupation>
      </controlaccess>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
         <head>Access Restrictions</head>
         <p>This collection is located on-site.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
         <head>Acquisition</head>
         <p>1959 M-59</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <altformavail encodinganalog="530">
         <head>Alternate Formats</head>
         <p>William Burroughs letters are on microfilm.</p>
      </altformavail>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
         <head>Preferred Citation</head>
         <p>Identification of specific item; Date (if known); William S. Burroughs Papers; Box and
            Folder; Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University Library.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo encodinganalog="583">
         <head>Processing Information</head>
         <p>Cataloged 04/14/1989 Christina Hilton Fenn </p>
         <p>Papers reprocessed 6/2009 Carrie Hintz </p>
         <p>Finding aid wittten by Carrie Hintz, 2009.</p>
      </processinfo>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
         <head>Restrictions on Use</head>
         <p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish material
            from the collection must be requested from the Curator of Manuscripts/University
            Archivist, Rare Book and Manuscript Library (RBML). The RBML approves permission to
            publish that which it physically owns; the responsibility to secure copyright permission
            rests with the patron.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544">
         <head>Selected Related Material-- at Columbia</head>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/lweb/archival/collections/ldpd_4078809/index.html"> Allen Ginsberg Papers, 1944-1991</extref>
            Columbia University, Rare Book &amp; Manuscript
            Library
                
            </p>
        <p>
      
         The Ginsberg Papers contain some correspondence, some additional experimental prose, and
            fractionary drafts of <title render="italic">The Exterminator,</title>
                <title render="italic">Queer,</title> and "The Hot Rod" as well as a full manuscript of
               <title render="italic">The Naked Lunch</title> (here referred to by the working title
            "Interzone.")</p>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findingaids.cul.columbia.edu/ead/nnc-rb/ldpd_4078982/">Jack Kerouac Correspondence, 1945-1965</extref>
          Columbia University, Rare Book &amp; Manuscript
            Library
                
            </p>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://findingaids.cul.columbia.edu/ead//nnc-rb/ldpd_4078472">Barry Miles Papers, 1958-1990</extref>
           Columbia University, Rare Book &amp; Manuscript
            Library
              
         </p>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.columbia.edu/cu/lweb/archival/collections/ldpd_4078597/index.html">Ann Charters Photographs, 1966-1982</extref>
            Columbia University, Rare Book &amp; Manuscript
            Library
                
         </p>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ldpd.lamp.columbia.edu/omeka/exhibits/show/nakedlunch">Naked Lunch: The First Fifty Years</extref> online exhibition, Columbia University, Rare Book &amp; Manuscript
            Library
         </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544">
         <head>Selected Related Material-- Other Repositories</head>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nypl.org/sites/default/files/archivalcollections/pdf/brgburro.pdf">William S. Burroughs Papers</extref>
           New York Public Library, Berg Collection
              
         </p>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.osu.edu/sites/rarebooks/finding/burroughs87.php">William
               S. Burroughs Papers, WSB 97</extref>
           Ohio State University, Rare Books and
            Manuscripts
               
         </p>
         <p><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://library.lib.asu.edu/record=b2676559~S3">William S. Burroughs Collection</extref>
           
                    Hayden Library Special Collections, Arizona State
               University
         </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      
      <dsc><c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series I: Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1953-1973</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>The Correspondence series contains a few select pieces of correspondence between
                  Burroughs and his friends and collaborators. In this series are letters exchanged
                  between Burroughs and Allen Ginsberg regarding their collaborative, epistolary
                  book <title render="italic">The Yage Letters.</title> This series, though small,
                  includes both letters later reprinted as part of the publication and
                  correspondence related to the editing and process. </p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Burroughs to Bill Berkson, <unitdate>June 4,
                  1962</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Burroughs to Allen Ginsberg</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                     <unittitle><unitdate>January 25, 1953</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(published as part of <title render="italic">The Yage Letters</title>)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                     <unittitle><unitdate>January 6, 1955</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(regarding <title render="italic">The Yage Letters</title>)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                     <unittitle>January 9, 1955</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(regarding <title render="italic">The Yage Letters</title>)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                     <unittitle><unitdate>March 9, 1956</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(regarding <title render="italic">The Yage Letters</title>)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                  <unittitle>Allen Ginsberg to Burroughs, <unitdate>1973</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
                  <unittitle>Philip Whalen to Burroughs, <unitdate>1957</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series II: Writings, <unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1969</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>The Writings series is the largest series in the collection and contains working
                  drafts of 1961's Grove Press Edition of <title render="italic">The Soft
                  Machine,</title> as well as annotated drafts and galley proofs of Burroughs's
                  substantial 1965 revision of the novel published by Grove Press. There are also
                  drafts and galleys of<title render="italic">Nova Express</title>; a corrected,
                  signed galley proof of <title render="italic">The Naked Lunch;</title> and full
                  typescript drafts of <title render="italic">The Yage Letters</title> and <title render="italic">Junkie.</title> This series also contains a collection of prose
                  experiments conducted by Burroughs utilizing the cut-up technique that he utilized
                  in much of his longer fiction, as well as experiments in using a grid form to
                  intersplice different texts together. </p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                  <unittitle>"A Brief Statement on <title render="italic">The Naked Lunch</title>
                     <title render="italic">The Soft Machine</title> and <title render="italic">The
                        Nova Express,</title>" circa <unitdate>1963</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
               <scopecontent><p>(carbon copy in WSB's hand)</p>
               </scopecontent>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">9</container>
                  <unittitle>Dealer Catalogs and Book Reviews</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">10</container>
                  <unittitle>"Epic Prose Poem," circa <unitdate>1963</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">11-16</container>
                  <unittitle>Experimental Prose, circa <unitdate type="inclusive">1958-1965</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                  <physdesc><extent>(6 Folders)</extent>
                  </physdesc>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">17</container>
                  <unittitle>"Johnny 23" (with Editor's Corrections)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <unittitle><title render="italic">Junkie</title>-- Manuscript</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle><title render="italic">The Naked Lunch</title>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">18</container>
                     <unittitle>Signed Galley Proofs</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(original proof, 1964 Burroughs's signature, 1969)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">1</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">19</container>
                     <unittitle>Recording of Burroughs reading <title render="italic">Naked Lunch,</title>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                     
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>Please follow these links for digitized clips of the sections 
                    <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ldpd.lamp.columbia.edu/omeka/exhibits/show/nakedlunch/nlreading/item/1071">The Rube,</extref>
                       
                        <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ldpd.lamp.columbia.edu/omeka/exhibits/show/nakedlunch/nlreading/item/2575">Meeting of International Conference...,</extref> and
                     <extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ldpd.lamp.columbia.edu/omeka/exhibits/show/nakedlunch/nlreading/item/2574">The Exterminator Does a Good Job</extref>
                            </p>
                        </scopecontent>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <unittitle><title render="italic">Nova Express</title>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                     <unittitle>Early Drafts, <unitdate type="inclusive">1961-1964</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                     <unittitle>Galley Proofs, <unitdate>1964</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle><title render="italic">The Soft Machine</title>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                     <unittitle>Typescript with autograph corrections,
                     <unitdate>1960</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(for 1961 Olympia Press Edition)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                     <unittitle>Typescript with autograph corrections,
                     <unitdate>1963</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(formed the basis for the 1963 Grove Press edition)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                     <unittitle>Galley Proofs- Grove Press Edition,
                     <unitdate>1965</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6</container>
                     <unittitle>Related Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive">1963-1966</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">2</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">7</container>
                  <unittitle>"The Strange Bed," circa <unitdate>1961</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle><title render="italic">The Yage Letters</title>- Draft,
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series III: Photographs and Realia</unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>The photographs in the collection are mostly snapshots of Burroughs and Herbert
                  Huncke. Also included in this series is the Dreamachine, a device designed by
                  Burroughs and Brion Gysin and constructed by Ian Sommerville, designed to help
                  stimulate brain activity and bring about a hallucinatory state. </p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">3</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Stack">14</container>
                  <unittitle><extref xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ldpd.lamp.columbia.edu/omeka/exhibits/show/nakedlunch/nlreading/item/1072 ">Dreamachine</extref>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>
         <c level="series">
            <did><unittitle>Series IV: Victor Bockris Files, <unitdate type="inclusive">1965-1975</unitdate>
                    </unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent><p>Victor Bockris, a friend and collaborator of Burroughs, Victor Bockris write
                  several articles about Burroughs and edited both Burroughs's collection of essays,
                     <title render="italic">The Adding Machine</title> and the interview-based book
                     <title render="italic">With William Burroughs: A Report from the
                  Bunker.</title> This series of material includes numerous drafts of and notes for
                  With William Burroughs, as well as some of Burroughs's published writings
                  collected by Bockris- including a small run of <title render="italic">Crawdaddy</title> Magazines featuring articles or columns by Burroughs and a copy
                  of <title render="italic">The Paris Review</title> that includes both an interview
                  with Burroughs and his essay "St. Louis Return."</p>
            </scopecontent>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Correspondence and Ephemera</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>With William Burroughs</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">2</container>
                     <unittitle>Draft-- Preface with Barry Miles Comments
                     <unitdate>1975</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">4</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3 to 5</container>
                     <unittitle>Drafts and Notes, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(3 Folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">1 to 2</container>
                     <unittitle>Drafts and Notes</unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(2 Folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                  <container type="Folder" label="Folder">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Notes on Burroughs, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle>Collected Burroughs Writings</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">4</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Black Mask,</title>
                        <unitdate>August, 1974</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(contains Burroughs's "Coldspring News")</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">5</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">The Paris Review,</title> Fall,
                           <unitdate>1965</unitdate>
                            </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(contains Burroughs's "St. Louis Return" and an interview with
                     Burroughs)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">6 to 7</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">Crawdaddy,</title>
                        <unitdate>June-December, 1975</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                     <physdesc><extent>(2 Folders)</extent>
                     </physdesc>
                  </did>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">8</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">New York Arts Journal,</title>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(includes Bockris interview with Burroughs)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
               <c level="file">
                  <did><container type="Box" label="Box">5</container>
                     <container type="Folder" label="Folder">9</container>
                     <unittitle><title render="italic">The Drummer,</title>
                        <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <scopecontent><p>(includes Bockris interview with Burroughs)</p>
                  </scopecontent>
               </c>
            </c>
            <c level="file">
               <did><unittitle/>
               </did>
            </c>
         </c>

      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>